Hey, everyone.
In this video, I want to quickly cover what this message you're seeing in your tenant around auto-enabling passkey profiles means to you and what you may need to do.
I think for most of us, we understand the benefits of passkeys today.
So when I think about this passkey, this cryptographic mechanism gives us a lot of benefits for the end users and then the security of our services, our applications.
One of the huge things is they are phishing resistant because of a number of different things.
They require proximity.
So I've got my passkey that says on my phone or whatever, the device I'm authenticating with that passkey has to be within range of the device via Bluetooth or NFC or even USB.
So, the user can't be tricked to authenticating some bad actor that's trying to pretend they're a help desk or anything else.
Also, it's going to validate that the domain name you're trying to use the passkey against is the right domain name.
So, the passkey is for Microsoft.com.
I can't be tricked to try and use it for micro five of.com or some RN instead of the M.
So I can't be tricked to using it against another site that's trying to grab a token, the credential and then use it in a bad way.
And they're also actually very fast in terms of the authentication.
So it's very strong authentication and it helps protect the users from those types of phishing interactions.
Now, I did a video a few weeks ago on synced passkeys and their support now in Entra.
And what this message is all about is about that support for synced passkeys rolling out, so they will be available to all of the tenants.
Now, what we had before in Entra was the idea of device bound.
Now that device bound meant, hey, it was part of a USB dongle, for example, as part of a FIDO2.
It could have been part of the authenticator app.
So the authenticator app on your phone could have a passkey, but the passkey was only present on that particular phone.
It wouldn't go and sync to your other devices.
And also I could do something called attestation.
So the attestation would say, actually, not only do I have this passkey, but it's cryptographically signed through the hardware of the device through to a root signing certificate from FIDO2 that you can trust this.
But then also we have this idea of synced passkeys.
And what that will do is within a certain ecosystem, so for example, within my Apple
ecosystem or within my Android ecosystem, it could sync.
So all my iPhones, my iPads, my Mac machines could have the same passkey.
I just create it once and it's available on all of them.
Or on all my Android devices or hey, I'm using the Chrome, it would be available there, but it would not sync across ecosystems.
So it made it a bit more user-friendly.
And obviously I could create multiple passkeys, one on Apple, one on Android.
I could absolutely do that.
So these are more consumer-friendly because now they're just available.
There's less chance I lose it because it's hard linked to a certain piece of hardware.
Now with synced, you cannot do that attestation because there is no agreed upon standard on, hey, how can a key be attestation approved and guaranteed?
if it could be on many different parts of hardware.
So you don't have attestation.
And one thing I do want to stress, remember the pass keys are really all about how I would authenticate.
So this is all about the auth N, so the authentication, proving I am who I say I am, and it's very strong authentication.
But you still then have the layout of authorization.
So we think about, for example, conditional access in Entra, which can then check for other things.
So even if the passkey was synced on many devices, well, my conditional access policy could say, hey, yeah, I want a strong credential, but I also want it to be a managed device, for example.
It's managed by Intune.
It's healthy.
So just because the passkey exists doesn't mean it can just be used on any of the different services.
The passkey strength is just one factor I can use as part of my conditional access.
Okay, so what is changing?
So in preview before, when I did the video, you now had this ability to support synced passkeys.
And the way you did that is you could create passkey profiles.
And the passkey profile would let you pick, hey, do I want device bound and or do I want synced and do I want attestation required?
Now if you do attestation required, you can't do synced within the profile.
And so what's happening here is your current settings will control what this new default passkey profile that is going to be established will contain.
So the whole goal here, and let's look at the article for a second, and it's telling us exactly what it's going to do.
So the whole point here is whatever you currently have configured for your just FIDO2 authentication method,
which really today you can put in, do you want attestation or not, will drive what the default passkey profile will be.
So what that's going to do is if you have attestation, it tells you about the timing down here for just general worldwide, it's basically in the month of March, and then the automatic enablement will happen April through May.
For the GCC, GCC hire DoD, the enablement is in the month of April and then automatic rollout in June.
And what it's going to do is we can see here, depending on your configuration, if you currently have attestation enabled, then it's only going to allow device bound.
If you don't have attestation enabled, or it's disabled, then it's going to let you have device bound and synced.
Any targeting you have will be set as part of the assignment to the default passkey profile.
So if we only focus on that for now, what that means is if we go into our authentication methods, so I'm looking at authentication methods under entry ID, and then looking at policies,
Once this is enabled, we see we now have this passkey FIDO2.
And what you're going to now see is, firstly, this enablement is going to disappear because it will just be enabled for everyone.
I'm signed in early.
But you're going to have now this default passkey profile.
And again, if you have attestation currently enabled for the old FIDO2, then you're only going to have device bound because you cannot have synced.
If you did not have attestation, then it's going to have device bound and synced.
That's really the whole thing of what it's going to do.
And also it will honor any other sort of behaviors, any AA GUID you have configured on there.
And then if you've targeted particular groups for the existing configuration, well, then they're going to be targeted for that default profile.
And of course, the whole goal of the profiles is I can actually have multiple profiles.
So for example, I also have a synced passkey profile that I'm only targeting for certain groups.
So hey, the device bound is everyone, but the synced one I'm allowing for specific groups of people.
So that's the behavior.
And obviously, once it's enabled for your tenant, you could go and start creating these and refining them early.
That's totally up to you.
So the other change,
if we go and look, is the idea of the registration campaign.
So right now, if you've got the registration campaign, it kind of targets SMS messages or phone calls.
Well, it's going to change that to go ahead and use passkeys.
So if I'm only using device bound, it's going to be Microsoft Authenticator.
If I have sync available, then it's going to use passkeys.
which is synced as well.
So I can see that as well.
So under my authentication methods, you have the registration campaign.
And all it's going to do is if it's enabled or Microsoft managed, you're going to see it go ahead.
And the method, if you have synced, will change to passkeys.
If it's device banned, it will just stay as authenticator.
If you've disabled it, then it will stay disabled.
It won't do anything.
But that's really all it's doing.
So the whole goal here is passkeys are very much superior when we think about the security.
And so what they're going to do is enable them now for everyone as a choice.
It's going to maintain your existing configuration.
So if today, hey, I want that attestation, it's not going to go ahead and enable sync passkeys for you.
If you're not doing attestation, then it will enable sync passkeys because it's really equivalent to that type of thing.
But what you can do now is be aware.
Once it's enabled for your tenant, you can go and have a look at the configuration.
You can tweak things.
Maybe if I want that device bound for maybe sensitive users, I can do that.
And then enabled synced for the more general task-based workers and everything else.
So that's the change.
You can go and read the full document in the message center.
Hope that clears it up.
It's going to maintain your configuration and just
Hey, now you'll have access to be more granular in who should have device bound and or synced.
Till the next video, take care.