Hey, this is Andrew Brown, your Cloud Instructor from ExamPro, and today I'm bringing you another complete study course.
This time it's for the Azure Administrator AZ-104.
So this course was designed to help you pass the exam and achieve a Microsoft-issued certification.
The way we're going to do that is by going through a lecture content.
You're going to be doing follow-alongs within your own Azure account.
And of course, I'm going to provide you with these cheat sheets at summary points within the course, and this is going to really help you pass your exam.
The whole reason we're doing this is so you can prove on your resume in LinkedIn that you have that Azure knowledge so you can get that cloud job or get that promotion you've been looking for.
Just to tell you a little bit about me, I was previously the CTO of multiple education technology companies with 15 years industry experience, five years specializing in the cloud.
I'm recognized by AWS as a community hero, and I've published multiple free cloud certifications just like this one in other cloud topics.
And if you want to know something personal, I love starting
Star Trek and Coconut Water.
So I just want you to know that these free video cloud certification courses is made possible by viewers like you, and I strongly thank you for your support.
If you're looking for a way to support more of these free cloud certification courses, the best ways to buy your extra study materials over at exampro.co.
And specifically for this course, it's exampro.co/az104.
And on the platform, you'll get access to study notes, flashcards, Quizlet,
downloadable cheat sheets, practice exams, and you'll be able to ask questions and get learning support.
And if you're looking to keep up to date on the upcoming courses, because I'm always making new free courses, what I want you to do is follow me on Twitter, and I would love to hear from you.
So whether you've passed your exam, you want to tell me what course you want to see next, or you just really like my cloud memes, because I'm known for making fun cloud memes as well, I'd love to see you there.
So there you go, and let's just jump into the course now.
Hey, this is Angie Brown from Exam Pro, and we are at the start of our journey for the Azure Administrator, asking the most important question: What is the AZ-104?
So, this certification is for system administrators, or those looking to become system administrators for Azure workloads.
And this certification will demonstrate a person can manage, configure devices, users, permissions, general computing, cloud storage, and cloud networking.
And those are basically all the core services.
So this is a very general certification at the associate level.
The certification is referred to by its course code, the AZ-104, and that is what I'll be calling it throughout this course.
And if you've taken the AZ-900, this is what people generally will take right after that certification.
And usually after this AZ-104, they usually go for the AZ-303.
The solutions are
architect.
The certification is ideal for those seeking a role that is more configuration-based than having to write computer code.
So if you do not fancy yourself a developer or you think that's just not the skill for you, then maybe this is the certification you want to go after.
Now looking at the Azure roadmap, we have four different categories.
We've got fundamentals, associate, expert, and specialty.
And at the start of your journey, you're always going to want to start with the AZ 900.
No matter what associate you're going for, make sure you get the certification first.
But Azure has a lot of associate level certifications.
It has two expert levels and then three specialties.
Currently, so again, you're going to start with the AZ-900, and then once you have that certification, you get to pick whichever associate you want.
So, if you're looking for a generalized role, the administrator is the most...
ideal certification to take.
And I always say that it's very similar to the AWS Solutions Architect because it's so broad.
And it's no surprise that a lot of people who take the AZ-104 are trying to become a Solutions Architect expert.
Okay?
Now, some people aren't always ready to go to the expert level right off the bat.
And so sometimes I'll recommend either taking the developer or more commonly something that's better paired with this is actually the security certification.
Then people move on to the expert.
And if you're looking to do something afterwards, probably look for
SAP workloads here, which is a high-performance database, so that is the general roadmap for most people with Azure.
If you're not looking for some kind of specialty or you don't know what you're going to do, comparing this to other certifications, so you have AWS and GCP, I just want to compare the difficulty so you can figure out if you've already taken these other ones.
how much time or difficulty we'll compare, right?
So for AWS, I'd say it's two times harder, or compared to the GCP, it's three times harder.
And the reason why Azure associate certifications are so much more difficult than these other cloud providers is just because it focuses a lot more on practical knowledge.
So I'll give you an example.
A question you could see on the exam would be, how do you set up an Azure file share sync?
And you would actually be given a list, and you'd have to choose the, the steps that would need to be formed, and also the correct order.
Right.
And so that's not something you would really see on an AWS or GCP exam.
And so Azure exams are very much focused on whether you are a practitioner, can you actually do it, as opposed to do you know how to effectively use these services?
So that could be good or bad depending on the way you look at it.
I kind of like the latter where I'd rather be more focused on the utility as opposed to the practical knowledge because I feel that you could always...
figure that stuff out.
And this is the purpose of certifications is to give you that broad knowledge so you know how to utilize your services.
But that's just how they do it.
So how long should you study for the AZ-104?
Well, if you have two to three years experience with Azure, it could be as little as 12 hours.
If you only have one year experience, I'm going to recommend to you 30 hours.
And if you've already passed the AZ-900, you're looking at a whopping 60 hours of study.
So that's over 21 days, one to three hours.
So that's three weeks of study.
And generally, this is like a week extra for what I would normally recommend at an associate level certification compared to other clouds.
But this is just how Azure is.
So where do you take the AZ-104?
Well, you have two options.
You can do it in person or online.
And from there, there's two types of test centers that are available to you.
The first one is PSI and the other one is Pearson View.
I've used both of them.
And so I would always recommend if you have the opportunity, always do it in person because if you do it online,
And you might run into a lot of trouble where your computer overheats or you forgot to plug in your laptop, or let's say your proctored person, they lose their connection or you have a connection problem.
So many things can go wrong online, but if you have to do it because of circumstance, that's totally understandable.
But if you can have that controlled environment, it's a lot...
I think you'll do a lot better if you do it in person.
And just so you know, if you see the word proctored, that just means a supervisor, a person who monitors your students during an examination.
So generally people say online proctored exam, that's where that word comes from.
So what does it take to pass this exam?
Well, you're going to be watching lecture videos and memorizing key information.
The second one, I probably should give it a lot more emphasis, but you're going to be doing hands-on labs and follow-ongs within your own Azure account.
Even with my course, I probably don't have enough.
You know what I mean?
Because they're always adding stuff and there's just so many things to do.
And so I'd be making this course for 1000 years, but I will kind of point that out when we get into the exam guide breakdown.
We'll talk about how Azure frequently updates their exams and that's what makes it really hard.
You'll definitely, need to use paid online practice exams.
If you're looking for some, I have one bundled with this course.
So this course, my video content is always free, but I always have additional layered paid content that's here to support the free content that I produce.
So, you know, I strongly recommend that you go out and purchase the paid layered content because it helps me produce more free courses for you.
And also it's just going to increase your odds of passing the exam, okay?
In terms of the content outline, and this is basically the domains of the exam, which we will look in more detail in the next video here, but we have Manage Azure Identities and Governance.
I think that's a spelling mistake.
There shouldn't be an R on there, so please nobody tell me about that.
right here.
And then we have implement and manage storage, deploy and manage Azure compute resources, configure and manage virtual networks.
So notice here we got storage, compute, virtual networking, and this is like IAM, right?
So these are the core services.
The thing I'm surprised is they didn't put databases in here, but that's okay.
So we'll go, oh, and sorry, there's one more, monitor and backup Azure resources.
Okay.
Now the passing grade here is
70%.
So I believe they scored out of 1000 points.
So you got to get 700 more points.
I put an asterisk around here to emphasize that you need to be around that score.
So it's totally possible you could fail with a 70%.
So I always recommend, because it's scaled scoring, right?
So I always recommend that you get at least 75.
That's your target goal.
And so when you're studying, whoops, when you're studying, you're looking to get an 85% on your practice exams, okay, before you do that.
So that hopefully on the real exam, you're going to be, you have
have a buffer of 10%.
All right.
In terms of response types, there are 40 to 60 questions.
So that means you can afford to get about 12 to 18 questions wrong.
I put an asterisk here again because Azure is a bit odd.
They don't have consistency across their questions.
They have a bunch of different question types, which we'll talk about here in a moment.
So some questions are worth more than one point.
There is no penalty for wrong questions, so never leave a question blank.
And there are some cases where you cannot skip questions.
So you might face a part and you just feel really stressed because you want to come back to it, but you just can't.
You've got to do what's in front of you.
In terms of the types of questions, we have multiple choice and multiple answer, which most people are common with.
But what's unique here is we've got drag and drop, hot areas, which is basically concept matching, and case studies.
And case studies is really interesting because what they do is they give you a business scenario.
So they give you a bunch of text to read with a huge breakdown, and then they ask you a series of questions all relating back to that
that case, okay?
And so that's what I mean when I put an asterisk where I say, you can get X amount of questions wrong or there's more than one point because we have these different types and this really throws us a...
for a loop, okay?
In terms of the duration, you have 3 hours, which is a very, very long time to study.
And so, again, take this with a grain of salt, but if it was just multiple choice and multiple answers, that'd be one minute per study.
Your exam time is 180 minutes, but that's not the time that you should allocate.
You should make sure that you are blocking off 210 minutes.
That's just 30 minutes on top of that, because
For your seat time, that means it refers to the time you should allocate for the exam.
So things like time to review the instructions, read and accept the NDA, complete the exam, and provide feedback at the end.
Now, once you get the certification, it's going to be valid for 24 months.
So that's two years before recertification.
And I believe that Azure has some kind of way that you can get recertified for free.
I think they have like some kind of like thing you can do online for that.
So I don't have that slide here today, but maybe I'll add it into the course later.
But I just want you to know that if you do get this, you probably can renew for free, but you'd have to do some kind of a reassessment test or something.
OK, so there you go.
Hey, this is Andy Brown from Exam Pro, and we're taking a look at the Azure Administrator Exam Guide Breakdown.
And so what we're going to do is read the official outline so you can have an understanding of what it is that we need to study.
And also I'll just tell you a little bit about how frequently they update their certifications and how do you kind of like deal with that.
Because when I started producing this course, they've already changed it twice on me.
And so, if this is in the future, I just want to make sure that where to look and so that you can, if you need to self-study or just be aware of what has changed, okay?
So, yeah, I went into Google, I typed in AZ-104, Azure Administrator, I got to this page, scroll on down, and they'll have the skills outline.
So I'll just open that in a new tab.
And if it has at the top, see this red text, it'll say, this document contains skills measured on the exams associated with certification.
It does not include the upcoming or recent changes.
They might as well have red text here all the time, because they always have.
have it.
If you scroll on down, it doesn't show any of the changes.
Okay, so if I make my way back here and you scroll on down, what you'll do is you'll right-click on this, and this one's a lot better, I think.
And if you scroll on down, it looks the same, but it's not.
See, it's pretty darn similar, but see, this is Schedule Exam.
And if you scroll on down here, and we open this new tab here,
We have that red text again, and it tells you the date, so this is March 26th, and if you scroll all the way down, it shows you what has changed, right?
So, what I'm going to do is we'll just use this one as our example, but before we do, I just want to point out that...
Azure has a thing, or sorry, Azure or Microsoft has, it's called Microsoft Learn.
And so they have a lot of free content.
And so, should you go use this content for study?
Sure.
Is it enough to pass the exam?
No.
But the thing is, that when you're doing my course, if for whatever reason I don't have a particular follow along and you're looking for more follow alongs, you might find them in here.
So it doesn't hurt to go through it or just to be able to read it in a different way.
But I'm going to tell you that it really is not enough to
to pass the exam, but it is definitely a good accompaniment to the course that I have here, okay?
So let's go make our way back over to the exam here, and I'm pretty sure, I'm just a bit uncertain here, so I'm just going to open up the original one here, just to make sure that they're the same.
Yeah, it looks like it's fine.
So we'll use the one where they have changes.
So at the top here, we have Manage Azure Identities and Governance.
Actually, what we'll do?
We'll just go down below here because they show them all here.
So this is prior to March 26th, and this is the new updated guide.
This is what I'm going to be focusing here on the right-hand side.
So the first thing, and it's just rewording, but manage Azure Active Directory.
Active Directory is a way for you to manage your users and their permissions with their identities, okay?
So you've got to be able to create user groups, manage user groups and properties, manage device settings.
And this is weird because I feel like device management needs a lot more of a section here.
Like what I was saying, I found that like there was a lot more to it.
And so I made just a section just for this in the course because I just felt like it got glossed over.
Because when I started doing practice exams and then taking my real exam, I was so surprised on like how I missed that information.
So I put some emphasis in there.
We got bulk user updates, manage guest accounts, Azure AD join, configure self-service password reset.
Then you have manage role-based access controls, RBAC.
So create a custom role, provide access to Azure resources by assigning roles to different scopes, intercept access assignments.
Then we have manage subscriptions and governance, configure Azure policies, resource locks, apply manage tags resources, manage resource groups, manage subscriptions, manage costs.
A lot of these are just rewordings, right?
So cost management, just to costs.
Okay.
Coming down below here, we have secure storage.
So it's interesting they just put the word secure in there to emphasize it.
They just changed the category name there.
But network access to storage, configure storage accounts, generate out an SAS, manage keys, Azure AD authentication, Azure files.
I think file sync should be here.
It might be, oh yeah, it's down here.
Okay.
So now the next thing here, managed storage.
So we got export Azure jobs, import jobs, Azure Storage Explorer, AZ Copy, replication, blob, object replication.
Then for Azure File, Azure Blob Storage, we got file share, file sync, blob storage, just all the different types of blobs, and the blob lifecycle management.
For deploy and manager Azure compute resources, we got the automate deployment of VMs via the Amazon Resource Manager.
Resource Manager is a really great tool to learn, so I do use it quite a bit in our follow along, so I keep on coming back to it.
The AZ or the Azure Resource Manager template, virtual hard disk template, deploying a template, deploying a virtual machine.
So for configuring virtual machines, we have Azure Disk Encryption.
You can move a VM between resource groups, managing VM sizes,
Adding disks, configuring deploys, high availability, scale sets.
Scale sets are such a pain to set up.
Like I thought they worked like AWS.
Auto scaling groups, they absolutely do not.
So that was something that was very interesting.
I think you should give some attention to.
creating configured containers.
This, I think that mine is a little bit more light.
So when I did this, I just did the bare minimum here for Kubernetes.
And it looks like they've added a bunch of other stuff.
So I will be adding them to the course, but probably I just won't have them initially.
So just watch out for that kind of stuff.
I honestly didn't see, and I took the exam after this date here, but I didn't really see that many Kubernetes questions at the time when I sat it.
So I'm not too worried about it, but I'm just saying like,
just watch out and make sure if I don't have that content, make sure you just read some of the docs there or poke around the panel there.
For Azure App Services, so create app service plans, configure scaling sets, create secure custom domains, backup, networking, deployment.
What's interesting is they don't have, there's a service called Web Apps.
It allows you to run remote scripts.
So they don't have that in there, which I was a bit surprised.
but I found that as I did my actual exam.
Configure and manage virtual networking, so you just have to know the ins and outs of virtual networking, which is not too hard here, like peering and stuff like that.
Secure virtual networks, that's where we're talking about NSGs, the firewall, bastion service, load balancer, so the Azure Application Gateway.
And the last here is to monitor and troubleshoot virtual networking, so monitor on-premise connectivity, network performance monitor, Azure Network Watcher, these stuff.
I honestly found this part the hardest to set up because at least at the time when I did this, the services are so old and they're also being transitioned to something else.
And, I looked around and I figured, maybe other people had better resources and they honestly didn't.
So I don't feel too bad about it, but I'm just, if you feel some pain doing this part, I totally understand, okay?
Then down below we have integrate on-premise.
So we got VPN Gateway, ExpressRoute, Virtual WAN.
I gave Virtual WAN a lot of attention just because I've never had a strong networking background and I just thought that, you know, if you didn't either, that I would give it a very thorough explanation, which I do.
For monitor and backup Azure resources, we got intercept metrics, logs, analyze log queries, application insights.
And for backups, we got recovery services, Azure backup, Azure site recovery, and stuff like that.
So yeah, that is basically everything you need to learn.
Yeah, if something's missing, just go look up that individual item on your own there.
But you know, my course is very complete, but you know what?
It could be like three months later, and then they just add a few little extra things in there.
So just watch out for that, okay?
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are looking at Azure Active Directory, and this is a cloud-based identity and access management service to manage user sign-ins and access to AD related resources.
So Azure Active Directory is Microsoft's cloud-based identity and access management service, which helps your employees sign in and access resources.
So that could be external resources like Microsoft Office 365, Azure Portal, SaaS applications, or internal resources.
resources, so applications within your internal networking or access to workstations on-premise. And you can use Azure AD to implement single sign-on. So you can see that Azure AD is basically like the one solution to log into everything. And we actually use it at Exam Pro. We use it with Microsoft Teams, or for the Exam Pro platform, our admin panel is tied to it. So when we want to log into the mid panel with credentials, we have it there.
We use it with AWS to log into there, and we use it to log into Azure. So it has a lot of flexibility, and if you're building out applications for enterprises, they're likely using AD, and so this is the reason why everybody adopts it or needs to understand it. So it's a service I really, really do want you to understand and know. Azure Active Directory comes in four editions. We have the free tier, and by the way, each...
A tier that goes up has the features before it, but free has MFA, SSO, basic security, usage reports, and user management. Then you have the Office 365 apps, which is...
revolves around if you're using that suite. So you have company branding, SLA, to sync between on-premise and cloud. And then the premium tiers, which really comes into enterprise or on-premise hybrid architectures. So hybrid architectures, advanced group access, conditional access, premium two, identity protection, and identity governance. The only thing I don't like about Azure AD is that you can't really create your custom access controls unless you have premium one or premium two, but that's just how they do it. So there you go.
So let's take a look at the use case for Azure AD. And we basically covered it in the introduction, but I just want to reiterate it in a different way with a bit of a visual so that it really helps it sink into your brain there. So Azure AD can authorize and authenticate to multiple sources. So it can authenticate to your on-premise AD, to your web application, allow users to log in with IPDs. So identity providers could be like use Facebook or Google login.
You can use it with Office 365 or Azure Microsoft. And so just a visual here. Notice that we have Azure AD. And using Azure AD Connect, we can connect to on-premise. Through app registrations, we're able to connect our web application to Azure AD. With external identities, we can use Facebook or Google login. And then for cloud applications, we can connect to Office 365 or Microsoft Azure.
So Active Directory existed way before Azure, and so let's just do a quick rundown of the history so we have an idea of what we're looking at. So Microsoft introduced Active Directory Domain Services in Windows 2000 to give organizations the ability to manage multiple on-premise infrastructure components and systems using a single identity per user. So it's been around for 20 years.
And Azure AD takes this approach to the next level by providing organizations with identity as a service, so ID AAS, solution for their apps across cloud and on-premise. And both versions are still used today because they just have different utility. And so we have Active Directory, which is for on-premise. And then you have Azure AD, which is just the cloud-hosted version. And in many regards, these can also be connected together. But there you go.
So I want to cover some Active Directory terminology. And the honest truth is that for Azure, you're not going to be too worried about these things, but they're going to come up with a documentation. You're going to kind of wonder what they are. And so I just wanted to tell you about these up front, even though they're not core to study, so that it just really rounds out your Active Directory knowledge. Because Active Directory is such a core service to Azure and Microsoft products, you should know these things.
So the first thing is all about domains. So a domain is an area of network organized by a single authentication database. An Active Directory domain is a logical grouping of AD objects on a network. So just think of it in a way as you know how you have resource groups to logically group your Azure resources. Domains are a logical grouping for your AD objects. Then you have a domain controller. A domain controller is a server that authenticates user identities and authorizes their access to resources. Very common to have multiples of these.
because you want to have redundant domain controllers so you can log in or availability or launching domain controller nearby so people can log in to different places. So definitely very core to Active Directory. Then you have the domain computer. This is a computer that is registered with a central authentication database. And a domain computer would be an AD object. So then you have AD objects. So this is the basic element of Active Directory. So you have users, groups, printers, computers, shared folders, et cetera.
Then you have a Group Policy Object, a GPO. This is a virtual collection of policy settings. It controls what an AD object has access to. You have your organizational units. This is a subdivision within Active Directory into which you can place users, groups, computers, and other organizational units. So it's just another way of doing logical grouping.
Then you have a directory service, and this provides a method for storing directory data and making this data available to network users and administrators. A directory service runs on a domain controller. So there you go. That is the rundown of Active Directory terminology. And again, hopefully when you see it in the documentation, you can refer back to this or you'll have a better understanding of all the components. I would have loved to have made a diagram, but I just couldn't find an example of 1. And so, I mean, I feel like there could be a really good picture for all this stuff.
So let's talk about the term tenant, and a tenant represents an organization in an Active Directory, and a tenant is dedicated to the Azure AD service instance. A tenant is automatically created when you sign up for either Microsoft Azure or Microsoft Intune or Microsoft 365, and each Azure AD tenant is distinct and separate from other Azure AD tenants, and so if you
if you were in Azure AD and you click on your tenant information, that's basically what that is, right? So that's my ExamPro one, and it has its own special tenant ID. And we can see that it's licensed for Office 365, and so that tells you that I'm using the Office 365 tier of Azure AD. So remember that the domain controller is the server that users are going to be using to authenticate to the directory service.
And so when you create an Active Directory, Azure sets one up for you, but there's some cases where you might want to set one up yourself. And the reason why is that you could be like an enterprise where you already have your own Active Directory on-premise, but you've decided that you want to move it over to Azure AD because you just want a fully managed Active Directory and you want to tap into the cloud. But the thing is that some domain services, those are features on your domain controller, just might not be available, and that's where you're going to need to set up your own domain controller.
And that's where Azure Active Directory Domain Services come into play, because these provide managed domain services, and so they have managed domain services such as domain joins, group policies, LDAPs.
But Kirby Ross, never can say that properly, NTLM authentication. And so the great thing is here is you can have these domain services, but you're not going to have to deploy them, manage them, patch them. They're just going to work. So there you go.
Let's take a look at Azure AD Connect, and this is a hybrid service that is used to connect your on-premise Active Directory to your Azure account. So, Azure AD Connect allows for seamless single sign-on from your on-premise workstations to Microsoft Azure, and Azure AD Connect has the following features: We have password hash synchronization, so this is a sign-in method, and it synchronizes a hash.
of a user on-premise AD password with Azure AD. Then you have password authentication. This is another sign-in method that allows users to use the same password on-premise and in the cloud. That's the one I like.
Then moving on from password authentication, we have federation integration. So this is a hybrid environment using an on-premise AD FS infrastructure for certificate renewal. Then you have synchronization. This is responsible for creating users, groups, and other objects and ensures on-premise and cloud data matches. So you have the same AD objects, both on-prem and in cloud. And then you got health monitoring. And this is a robust monitoring
Service, and it provides a central location in the Azure portal to view this activity, and it's called Azure AD Connect Health. So, yeah, the big takeaway is that Azure AD Connect is used to create a hybrid connection.
So now let's take a look at some of the AD objects, starting with users. So users represent an identity for a person or employee in your domain, and a user has login credentials and can use them to log into the Azure portal. So here I am, a user, and you can see it shows how many times I've logged in, and I'm part of different AD groups.
And so you can assign roles and administrative roles to users. You can add users to groups. You can enforce authentication, like with MFA. You can track user sign-ins, as you can see on the right-hand side. You can track devices, users' login, and allow or deny devices.
You can assign Microsoft licenses. Azure AD has two kinds of users. We have users, that's a user that belongs to an organization, and guest users. This is a user that belongs from another organization. And we'll cover Azure AD roles in the roles section here, because that is what you're going to be using.
to apply to these users. So groups in Azure AD lets resource owners assign a set of access permissions to all members of the group instead of having to provide the rights one by one. And so on the right-hand side here, you can see I have a bunch of groups in Exam Pro, and groups can contain owners, and owners have permissions to add or remove members, and then the members have rights to do things. Okay?
And so for assignment, you can assign roles directly to a group. You can assign applications directly to a group. And to request join groups, so the group owner can let users find their own groups to join instead of assigning them to them. And the owner can set up the group to automatically accept all users that join or require approval. This is really great when you just want people to do the work themselves, as opposed to having to do all that manual labor of adding them to groups.
Let's talk about how we're going to give users rights to access resources, and there are four different ways to do that. The first is direct assignment. This is where the resource owner is going to directly assign the user to the resource. Then you have group assignment. This is where the resource owner assigns an...
a group to the resource, which automatically gives all group members access to the resource. Then you have rule-based assignment. This is where the resource owner creates a group and uses a rule to define which users are assigned to a specific resource. And then you have external authority assignment. This access comes from an external source, such as an on-premise directory or SaaS application. I just want you to know that there's four different ways to do it to get access to resources.
Let's talk about external identities. So external identities in Azure AD allows people outside your organization to access your apps and resources while letting them sign in and use whatever identity they prefer. So your partners, distributors, suppliers, vendors, or other guests can bring their own identities, such as Google or Facebook. You can share apps with external users, so that's for B2B stuff. If you develop apps intended for Azure AD tenants,
for single tenant or multi-tenant, you can do that as well. You can develop white label apps for consumers and customers. This would be like Azure AD B2C. So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown, and welcome to the AZ-104 follow-along. And the first video in our journey on learning on how to be a good administrator is learning about Azure Active Directory tenants. And so tenants is the way we are going to group all of our users within an organization. So this is like the logical division of organizations within Azure. And so let's just make our way over to where tenants are, and they're under Azure Active Directory AD.
We'll click there. And so the idea is that when you first created your Azure account, you already have a single tenant. That is your organization. So here I can have, I see I have one here called the Hushnook. And down below, I have a license applied to it. So this is the Azure AD Premium P2. But the idea is you can create multiple ones. And so these can act as different organizations. And really what a tenant is, it's just an instance of Azure Active Directory.
That's exactly what it is underneath. But let's go ahead and go create a new one. And we have two options here. We can create an Azure Active Directory. And I think what really is implied here is that it's a B2B. When you read the documentation, they talk about B2C and B2B. B2B means business to business, meaning that you're joining businesses and other businesses together. And then B2C means business to consumer. And so up here in the description, they say the B2C enables users.
to access applications published by your organization and share administration experiences. All right. So what we'll do is we'll go to the next step here. And we're going to need to name our organization. I'm going to name it Starfleet. And we need our initial domain. Notice it's going to be on Microsoft.com. So we will just lowercase that. If it's already used, it might complain. We'll see if I can take that. And it's already taken. So we'll say
the USS Starfleet. Oh, it must be numeric. Take that out there. we go. U and three S's. That's not easy at all, but that's okay. I'm going to change my default location to Canada. I think it still deploys in the US anyway. It's still going to say United States where the data center is going to be. We're going to go ahead and hit review, create, and give it a moment.
It's saying I'm missing some information there, already used by another directory, so I still can't call it that. Boy, oh boy. So I'll just say Starfleet 1984. And I think we should be able to do that. And we'll go ahead and create it. And so you're going to have to play around and find the name that's going to work for you. And then we'll just wait for it to create this tenant. It shouldn't take too long here.
And after waiting there a couple of minutes, down on the right-hand side, it says it created the tenant. So we can just proceed back here. And so I'm just going to go back to Azure Active Directory at the top. I find it just easier to always search and go back this way. And so we'll just wait a moment for this to load. But we're still in our Husnuk
Azure Active Directory, that's my default one there. But let's say I wanted to go ahead and switch a tenant. I can go now and just switch. And so here I have my ExamPro one, Hushnook, and Starfleet. I'm going to go ahead and switch it over to this one. And so essentially now I have all these isolate users. So I can have different users in these other tenants, and that's the way you'd isolate them out. Notice that this one is Azure AD free. And so the thing with...
Azure Active Directory is that the higher up the tier you go, the more functionality you have. And one that is very popular, especially with enterprises, is going to have the P2 tier, Premium 2. I just want to show you how you'd go about upgrading to that. It does cost money, but you also get a free trial. I don't believe that you are billed during the time of the trial. At the end of it, then you have to enter in or make an explicit purchase of it. Let's go ahead here and see if I can do it.
It might not give me trial because I'm already running another one, but let's go find out. So I clicked on licenses on the left-hand side. We'll go to all products, and then we have try and buy. And so on the right-hand side, it says Azure AD Premium 2. And we can click on free trial, and it's going to tell you why you'd want P2, such as multi-factor authentication, policy-driven management, and end-user self-service. And so I'm going to just go ahead and upgrade that. You don't have to do that. You can just watch me do that here.
And so I'll just hit activate, and it's just going to go activate that in my account. And now it's activated. So if I go back to Azure Active Directory here, I'll probably go home, but I'm just going to go back this way. It's a lot more safe that way. Eventually it should update here. So it says Azure AD free, but really I've upgraded. It's just the delay in the console. And so after a few refreshes, it will probably show up.
But what that's going to do is it's going to enable some additional features. They don't really matter so much for the course. I mean, maybe I could show dynamic role assignment if I try to remember how that works. Let me think for a moment. I think it's under roles. But anyway, so, you know, that's how you do that. I just wanted to show you how to create a tenant and then disable the switch between them there.
So we created ourselves a tenant. Let's go ahead and actually create some users. And just before we proceed forward to create a user, I just want to point out, you can tell what tenant you are in if you look in the top right corner. So here I'm in my Starfleet tenant. And there's actually, I think you can switch between here. Yeah, that's an easier way to switch between your directories. But generally, that's not how I do it. I'll go to the top here and just type in Azure Active Directory.
And when I want to switch a tenant, I just click the Switch Tenant button and click on what I want. But we'll make our way back to the Starfleet tenant that I have here. you can see my information, and I've obviously activated Azure AD Premium P2. But before we go ahead and create a user, we're going to have to create a group, and I'll show you why. If I'm going to go ahead, I'm just going to speed through this for a second. But when I scroll on down, I have this option where I need to assign it to a group. I guess I don't have to.
But the problem is I don't have one. And so before I create my user, let's go ahead and create ourselves a new user group. And so we'll go ahead and create a new group here. And we have two options. We have security and Microsoft 365. It explains right here the difference. So 365 is really for giving access to mailbox, calendar, files, SharePoint. We're not doing that stuff here. We're just sticking with regular security groups, which is for Azure stuff. We'll name this developers. And then we'll name this developers.
And notice here that the membership type, I have a drop-down. If you're on the free tier, this is going to be grayed out. But this dynamic user is part of P2. And so this allows us to add a dynamic query. And the idea here is that if I start having users and I just say if a user is from Canada, then they'll automatically be added to this group. And so that's the query that gets outputted. But we're not going to make a dynamic group today. We'll just make our way back
here to the new group. And we'll just manually assign stuff, all right? I'll go ahead there and create that user, or that group there. And now that we have that group, let's make our way over to users. So we'll go back here. I'm going to make myself a new user. And on the top here, we'll go here. And we'll name this one Kevin. And we'll have that lowercase. And we will call them Kevin Uxbridge.
All right.
And you'll notice here it will auto-generate a password.
It's 4 letters and four numbers.
I don't find this personally very secure, but the idea here is that a user is going to reset that password right away, so it's not a big deal, and that's very easy to remember.
And now I can go here and assign groups.
And if I want to assign the role, I can do that here.
So we'll open that up.
We have a bunch of different options.
Maybe we want these two roles here.
And then we have some additional information.
I'll go ahead and create this user.
And so now this user exists.
What's interesting is that I can go ahead and delete users and then recover them.
The groups have this as well, where if you go here, and I actually have a user I deleted previously.
So it just takes some time to show up.
But if you go ahead, you can hit the delete user here.
And then they will remain in here for 30 days, and then they'll automatically be deleted.
So if someone made a mistake, this is a great opportunity to bring them back.
And so I can just go checkbox on Rishon here, and we can just bring her on back, restore that user.
All right.
And again, you know, this is sometimes a bit delayed, so we might have to hit refresh.
There she is.
And so, you know, that is the whole group and user stuff there.
Okay, now let's take a look at the concept of guest users.
So, let's make our way back to users within our tenant, and there's this button here for new guest users.
The idea behind guest users is that we're able to invite other users from other tenants, and this is a much simpler process than using federation.
Federation is the concept of...
of joining Active Directories together.
So if there is an on-premise or other external Active Directory, they would somehow want to connect the two together.
And there's a lot of administrative burden with that.
But if everybody's already using Azure Active Directory, it's as simple as adding a guest user.
So what we're going to do is go back to home here.
I'm just going to go back to Azure Active Directory.
And we're going to switch tenants.
I'm going to go back to my Hushnuk one here.
And you probably won't see that.
It's just showing up because it wants me to use MFA.
And I'm going to go here to users, and we're going to go ahead and create ourselves a new user.
I'm going to call this one a Hushnook.
And we will name it simply that.
And let's make note of the actual e-mail there.
That's Hushnook on Microsoft.com.
And we'll go ahead and create that.
And now what I'm going to do is I'm just going to copy that e-mail there.
Okay.
I think I got it.
Yes, I do.
Good.
And we're going to make our way back to Azure Active Directory.
We're going to switch tenants back to Starfleet.
And we are going to go to users and we're going to add a new guest user.
I'm going to invite a user.
And I'm just going to put in their e-mail there.
And we will say Hushnook.
And we'll just put that both.
And we can assign them to groups and roles.
It's all the same story here.
I'm just going to go ahead and invite them.
And so now they've been sent off an invitation.
Notice that they show up under as guest.
All right, so there you go.
Let's take a look at bulk operations.
Let's say we needed to bring in a bunch of different people into our actual account here.
And so we have this option of bulk create.
And if you look on the right-hand side, we can go ahead and download a CSV template that's ready to use.
I'm going to just double-click that.
I already have Excel installed here.
And off the bat, what you can see is we have a bunch of options that we can fill in.
And here we have one example there.
And so I think that we could try to give this a go here, but we're going to have to make sure we use the same principal username or here thing here.
So I'm just going to grab this here.
And let's just make a few people.
So we need our principal here.
We'll just say Picard.
Whoops.
Did not like that I copied that.
And we'll do up here, we'll say data, Picard, data, Picard, Picard, data, data.
Just see what else I need.
We're going to need a password.
I'm just going to use the same one here.
Set that as no.
I don't think any of the other things there are needed.
We'll go ahead and save that.
And I'm just going to save this somewhere convenient.
Okay.
And what I'm just going to do is pull this up off screen here.
I'm just looking for where I saved it.
Just give me a moment.
And there it is.
I'm just going to drag it on in here.
I think I can drag it in like that.
Maybe not as easy.
Let's go back to, it's under my downloads.
Here we go.
And we'll just hit submit.
We'll give that a moment.
It shouldn't take too long.
You can probably view the status here if we click that there.
Now we're just under bulk operation results.
I'm just going to give it a refresh.
You can see that it's not completed yet.
I can click into it.
And we'll just have to wait a little bit here, okay?
Oh, it looks like it just succeeded.
I'll give it a nice refresh.
It's going to tell me how did it turn out.
To success, 0 failures, total requests.
Let's click into that so we can see what it did.
That looks pretty darn good to me.
So that is pretty good.
We'll make our way back to our users.
And you can see that they're on mass imported.
So there you go.
Let's take a look at how we can enable multi-factor authentication for our users.
And so multi-factor stands for MFA.
You're probably used to it, where it's a secondary step to confirm your identity before logging in, either via a phone or a hardware device such as an UbiKey.
And so there's this button here.
It says multi-factor authentication.
And it could be disabled for you.
It very likely is if you're on the free version of your Azure AD.
Just going back up here one level.
You can tell based on what that is here.
So I'm using Azure AD Premium P2.
That's definitely going to allow me to have MFA.
So if you just don't want to turn on P2 or it's trying to charge you money, don't worry about it.
Just watch me do it here.
You'll pretty much learn what you need to know.
So we'll just go ahead and click that button.
It's going to bring us to a different screen here.
And here we have our users.
And you can see multi-factor authentication is turned off for all of them.
So we can go ahead here and turn it on for a single one if I click enable.
And so that enables it for Kevin.
Then we have some other additional options like manage user settings.
And here you can see we have some extra options.
So require selected users to provide contact methods again, delete all existing app passwords generated by the selected users, restore multi-factor authentication on all remembered devices.
So just some additional things.
Another thing you will want to check out here, it's not very obvious, but we have a service settings button up here.
And this will give us more additional options to enforce for our users.
So first we have app passwords.
So this allows users to create app passwords to sign into non-browser apps, so things that are not part of the website here.
And so you can whitelist some IP addresses for them so that they are trusted from those locations.
Then for verification options, this is something that's important.
We have some options like call to phone.
So it will actually, to do the MFA, it will actually call your phone and it'll tell you the letters and numbers that you enter in, or it can send you a text message, or it can notify you through the mobile application.
So you can install the companion app from the Android or iOS store or the Windows store.
I imagine there's a Windows store too.
And then there is the verification code and mobile app on our hardware tokens.
So hardware tokens could be with an UB key, right?
Then you can say, remember a multi-factor authentication on trusted devices for X amount of days.
That way they don't have to enter it all the time because it might get annoying for some users.
Honestly, for me, I want everyone to enter it every single time because that's just how I am.
But let's make our way back here and see how we can do some bulk assignment.
So what I'll do is I want to enable it for a few people here.
So if I go up to bulk update,
I can download a sample file, and that's going to go ahead and download that.
And you can see I actually did this previously here, so I'll just copy it.
And what we'll do is just paste that in there.
So we're just pasting in, yeah, that's fine, we're just pasting in their name, right, and the MFA status.
You can always get the name from here, just back on the list there.
And so once we have saved that file, we can go ahead and upload that.
They're the same here, so it's not a big deal.
And we'll just wait a few seconds here.
This is pretty darn quick.
Usually it doesn't take minutes, sometimes it takes seconds, but we'll just give it a moment here.
And there we go.
So that was a long wait.
I don't know why, but I verified the two there.
And so if we go next, now those will be now enabled.
There's also this option to enforce.
So let's go there.
After multi-factor authentication is forced, users will need to create app passwords to use non-browser applications such as Outlook or Lynx.
And so that's a great option to have.
So I'll just go ahead and enable that as well.
So now that's enforced.
And so that's all you really need to know about MFA.
Okay, so we're back in our tenant here.
And what I want to do now is actually set some abilities for users to reset their passwords so they don't have to come and bother the administrator all the time.
So under your tenant on the left-hand side, what you want to look for is password reset.
And now we have a bunch of options here for resetting password.
So we're going to have to go ahead and enable it.
We can enable it based on a per group level.
such as developers.
But what I'm going to do is set it for everybody here, which I think is a lot better option.
And then down below, we have a lot of things we can do here.
So looking at authentication methods, we can choose the number of methods required to reset.
So maybe they need to use two options in order to reset their password, which is a lot more secure.
And then we can check box on possible methods they can use.
Then we could require a certain number of questions required here.
So 3 and three.
You can see I was setting something earlier here.
You can create your own custom questions.
And then so we'd go ahead here and just add a new one.
So, you know, what is the best, you know, song?
We'll go ahead and hit add.
And the idea is that you can add them there.
There's also a bunch of predefined ones.
So if you're having a hard time thinking of any, you can definitely check box on some here, right?
And so now we have a large pool of questions that can be used there.
We'll go ahead and save that.
Then under registration, we can say require users to register when signing in.
I think that's a great option to have there.
And then you can have number of days before users are asked to reconfirm their authentication method.
And that's defaulted to 180 days.
So I would probably leave that as on.
And we can notify users on password reset, notify all admins when other admins reset their password.
Very useful.
This was probably turned off, so I'd go ahead and turn that on there.
You can customize a help desk link.
So the idea here is that when someone's having trouble, they might say contact your administrator.
Well, how do you contact the administrator?
Well, you provide that information, either a URL or an e-mail.
So I've just provided my e-mail there.
There's some on-premise integrations.
Never used this stuff before because I'm never working with on-prem.
But that stuff is pretty straightforward as well, and then you have usage and insights, so you can actually see what people are resetting their passwords and things like that, and what is being used, so that seems pretty darn good, but that's pretty much it to it.
Yeah, so there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're looking at the Azure Active Directory Cheat Sheet.
This one's 3 pages long, so get ready for it and let's jump into it.
So, Active Directory, just Active Directory alone, which is AD, is Microsoft's Identity and Access Management Service, helps your employees sign in and access resources.
Then you have Azure AD, and this is the same thing, except it's the cloud-based version.
And one term that you'll hear a lot with this is identity as a service, which just means that it's like the serverless or hosted version of this, so you don't have to think about it or manage servers.
Azure Active Directory comes into four editions.
You've got the free one, the Office 365 apps, Premium One, which is also known as P1, Premium Two, which is P2.
It's good to know the differences.
between what features you have here.
So you should know all the details in between here.
So I highlighted conditional access because that's an important one on the exam to know.
Azure AD can authorize and authenticate to multiple sources.
So if you're doing on-prem, you're going to be using Azure AD Connect.
If it's for a web app, you're using app registers, registration, sorry.
If you're using Facebook or Google, you're using external identities.
If you're, you can also connect to Office 365 or Azure Microsoft.
Okay.
For Active Directory terminologies, when we're talking about a domain, a domain is an area of network organized by a single authentication database.
An Active Directory domain is a logical grouping of 80 objects on a network.
Then you have domain controller.
Commonly abbreviated as DC, domain controller is a server that authenticates user identities and authorizes their access to resources.
If you have a domain computer, a computer that is registered with a central authentication database, a domain computer would be an AD object.
Then you have AD objects, that just is the base element of Active Directory things like users, groups, printers, et cetera.
You have a GPO.
This is a virtual collection of policy settings.
Then you have organizational units.
This is a subdivision of your AD, which you can place users, groups, computers, etc.
in.
You have directory service, such as Active Directory Domain Service (ADS), which provides a method of storing directory data and making the data available to network users.
A directory service can run on a domain controller.
That's only page one.
We're on to page two.
So a tenant represents an organization.
A tenant is a dedicated Azure AD service instance.
A tenant is automatically created when you first sign up, either with Microsoft Azure, Intune, or 365.
Each AD tenant is distinct and separate from other tenants.
When you perform a lift and shift of AD to Azure, not all the features are supported.
In that case, you're going to be using ADDS.
So ADDS provides managed domains
services such as domain joins, group policies, lightweight directory access, and I never can say that word, so I'm not even going to try.
Azure AD Connect has the following features.
It has password hash synchronization, pass-through authentication, federation, integration, synchronization, health monitoring.
You've got the concept of users, so that's an AD object, remember.
So an identity of a person or employee in your domain, a user has login credentials and can use them to log into the Azure portal.
Azure AD has two kinds of users.
We got a user that belongs to your organization.
and guest users, a user that belongs to a different organization.
Groups let resource owners assign a set of access permissions to all the members of the group instead of having to provide the rights one by one.
And the group contains owners, and it contains members.
Just a moment here.
There we go.
Just want to make sure I'm recording the video so I don't end up fighting halfway.
I didn't do it.
So we got assignments.
So you can assign roles directly to a group, and you can assign applications directly to a group.
We're on to the last
slide here in the cheat sheet.
I told you this one was long.
Request to join groups.
The group owner can let users find their own group to join instead of assigning them.
The owner can also set up, set the group to automatically accept all the users or join to require approval.
There are four ways to assign resource access rights to your users.
Direct assignment, group assignment, rule-based assignment, external authority assignment.
No all four of these, please.
And so there we go.
We're at the end here, and that's all there is.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from ExamPre, and we are looking at device management for Azure Active Directory.
So what is device management?
Well, that is the management of physical devices such as phones, tablets, laptops, desktop computers that are granted access to company resources such as printers, cloud resources via device-based conditional access.
So if you were to go into Azure AD,
under device management, you could see a list of devices that are joined to that directory there.
So here we have some desktops and some laptops, could be phones, could be a variety of things.
Why would a company want to manage their devices from Azure Active Directory?
Well, imagine your company, you've got a distributed workforce, and that allows employees to work remotely or allow them to use their own personal equipment, which we call
BYOD, bring your own device, and this company is going to want to protect their organizational assets, such as their cloud resources, because they have less control over the physical securities of the work environment.
They're not in office, so you want to make sure those things are safe.
All right, and so that's the whole idea behind device management.
And so let's talk about the three ways to get devices into Azure AD.
We're going to go briefly over these three ways, and then we're going to dive deep into each three, because it's super important to know the difference
for the exams, okay?
So the 1st way is Azure AD registered.
So this is where you personally own the mobile, it's a personally owned or mobile device, and you're signing in with personal, Microsoft, or local account.
Notice the emphasis on personal or mobile.
And these are for things like Windows 10, iOS, Android, Mac OS.
Then you have Azure AD joined.
This is when the device is owned by the organization, and they're signed in with the Azure AD account belonging to the organization.
And they exist only in the cloud, so they're cloud native.
And again, this could be Windows 10, but then we have Windows Server 2019 VMs, so things like that.
Then you have hybrid Azure AD joined.
This is again owned by the organization, and you are signed in with an Azure Active Directory Domain Service account belonging to that organization.
And these exist in the cloud or on-premise.
So here we got Windows 7, 8.1, 10, Windows Server 2008 or newer.
So notice
that I'm emphasizing for Azure AD, it's personal, right?
For Azure AD joint, it's cloud native, owned by the organization.
And for the third one, it's owned by the organization, and it's cloud on-premise.
So if the question says, you know, for which device, in the case of on-premise, it's going to have to be.
Hybrid Azure AD joined, but this is just a very simple representation of the stuff, but we've got to go digging deeper into all these three categories right now.
So the first join type or way of getting devices into Azure Active Directory is the AD registered device.
And so these slides are going to be really boring, but we just got to go through the nitty gritties because some of these will help you understand how to choose which one on the exam.
So pay close attention to the stuff that I'm highlighting here, okay?
So the definition here is for registered devices to Azure AD without requiring organizational accounts to sign into the device, which means personal accounts, okay?
Primary
is bring your own device, so BYOD, or mobile devices.
The device ownership is either the user or the organization, but really just remember, personal, okay?
For the operating systems that can manage here, we got Windows 10, iOS, Android, and Mac OS for provisioning.
We have Windows 10 settings, iOS, Android, so company portal with Microsoft Authenticator app, the Mac OS company portal for device sign-in options.
We have end user, local credentials, password, Windows Hello, and PIN.
If you've never heard of Windows Hello, we'll cover it here in a moment.
It has biometrics or pattern for other devices for device management.
We can use mobile device management, so that would be Microsoft Intune.
We're definitely going to be talking about that here in a moment.
Mobile application management, which is similar to the one above.
Again, we're going to cover this as well.
For key capabilities, we have SSO to sign for cloud resources, so that stands for single sign-on, conditional access with enrolled.
into Intune conditional access with app protection policy and enable phone sign in with Microsoft Authenticator app.
Okay.
Let's just talk quickly about Windows Hello, because you might see questions on your exam and you might see this word appear and wonder what that is.
So Windows Hello is a way to give Windows 10 users an alternative way to log into their devices and applications using fingerprints, iris scan, or facial recognition.
I've never used this service before, but I would think it'd be super cool to have an iris scanner.
I don't know what the cost of that is.
But that's all there really is to this service.
So just remember that Windows Hello has these alternate ways of logging in.
All right, so now we're taking a look at MDM and MAM.
And I want to tell you that this is probably the most important concept relating to device management because this allows us to actually put in mechanisms of control.
So you definitely want to remember these two absolutely 100%.
The first one is called Mobile Device Management, MDM.
And this allows you to control the entire device so that you can actually wipe the data from it and also reset it to factory settings.
So you can imagine that's a very powerful way of managing company devices or
other devices.
The other one, which is mobile application management, allows you to publish, push, configure, secure, monitor, and update mobile apps for your users.
So you have one where you can actually control the entire device, and then you have one at a per app level.
And so what you do is under your Azure AD, there's a section called mobility, which is MDM and also MAM.
And so here we can actually add different applications to apply MDM and MAM for
Microsoft, you're going to be using Microsoft Intune.
So whenever you think of MDM or MAM, I want you to think of Microsoft Intune.
That is just this service that allows you to apply these two techniques.
To use Microsoft Intune, you have to upgrade to Azure AD Premium 2.
And Microsoft Intune is part of the Microsoft Endpoint Manager.
And then Microsoft Endpoint Manager and Intune are part of the Microsoft Enterprise Mobility and Security EMS.
I'm going to tell you this.
That is so confusing.
I don't know why.
I mean, like, it's probably for marketing reasons or business reasons.
But the thing is, that all these things are very similar.
And so I just want to try to spell a little bit out a bit better in the next slide.
Okay.
Okay, let's quickly talk about EMS.
So EMS is Microsoft's Enterprise Mobility Plus Security, and it is an intelligent mobility management and security platform that protects and secures your organization and empowers your employees to work in new and flexible ways.
And EMS is an umbrella of multiple Microsoft and Azure services.
So here's a list.
So we have Azure Active Directory, Microsoft Endpoint Configuration Manager, Microsoft Intune, and a bunch of others.
The ones that I want you to remember are these two, right?
Microsoft Intune and Azure Active Directory.
It's just confusing because first they had Microsoft Intune, then they had Microsoft...
Endpoint Configuration Manager, which Intune's a part of, and then they rolled it into this.
It's all marketing buzz, and I know it gets confusing, but I just wanted you to, when you see these three things, you know that they're pretty much the same thing, or they're talking about MDM and MAM.
Okay, so there you go.
Let's just touch on Microsoft Authenticator.
I'm pretty sure I covered this in the AZ-900, but let's just cover it again, just in case we don't remember what it is.
And again, this is a method of using it for registered devices, a way of
authenticating or logging in.
So Microsoft Authenticator is an application that allows you to do secure sign-ins from all your accounts using multi-factor authentication.
It's passwordless, meaning you don't have to put a password in, or it will auto-fill your passwords.
And if you are in the Google Play Store or the Apple Store, you can download this thing in.
It's a great tool to manage your devices.
I strongly recommend you install it just to get the experience of what this thing can do.
Okay?
All right, so we're on to our second type of join type, which is AD join devices.
So again, very boring slide, but let's work our way through it.
So the definition here is joined only to the Azure AD, requiring organizational account to sign into the device.
So this means it's not a personal account.
It's going to be the company's account there for the primary audience.
It's suitable for both cloud only and hybrid organizations, but really the way you should, and hybrid usually means on-prem and cloud, but really it's a cloud native thing, okay?
applicable to all users in an organization.
The device ownership here is organizations.
The operating systems that you can utilize is Windows 10 devices, except for Windows 10 Home.
So it's an organization, it's professional.
You're not going to be using the Home Edition, right?
We can do Windows Servers 2019 with virtual machines running in Azure.
Server Core is not supported.
I don't think that'll show up in the exam, but just a good thing to know.
provisioning, it's self-service with Windows OOB or setting or bulk enrollment or Windows Autopilot.
I think we'll talk about Autopilot in the next section here.
For device sign-in options, we have organizational accounts using passwords, Windows Hello, which we covered before, but this is the business version, FIDO 2.0 security keys, which if you've never heard of, we're going to talk about here shortly.
For device management, we have mobile device management again.
We have co-management with Microsoft Intune and Microsoft Endpoint Configuration Manager.
For key capabilities, we have SSO to both cloud and on-premise resources.
It has conditional access via MDM enrollment and MDM compliance evaluation.
We have self-service password reset and Windows Hello PIN reset on the lock screen.
And the last is enterprise state roaming across devices.
Okay?
All right, we're taking a look here at FIDO 2.0 Security Keys, and that stands for Fast Identity Online Alliance.
And this is an open industry association whose mission is to develop and promote authentication standards that help reduce the world's over-reliance on passwords.
So FIDO Alliance has published three sets of open specifications for simpler, stronger user authentications.
And when we're talking about
a lot of authentication devices, you'll see these terms like U2F, UAF, and things like that.
And this is where this comes from.
Okay, so we have FIDO universal second factor.
We have universal authentication framework.
We have client to authenticator protocols, CTAP.
And then there's also CTAP, which is complementary with WebAuthN.
And together, those are known as FIDO2.
So I know we're not digging into what these things are, but I just want you to know where they come from, because when you buy a security device, generally you'll see those initialisms, and you'll want to know, if you need to go digging, you'll find out more.
But what is a security key?
It's a secondary device used as a second step in an authentication process to gain access to device, workstation, or application.
A security key can resemble something like a memory stick, and when your finger makes contact with a button or exposed metal on the device, it will generate an autofill security token.
And a very popular brand of UbiKey, or sorry, a security key is called an UbiKey.
And this is the exact key I have sitting on my desk right now that I use to authenticate to a lot of my devices.
And just in this key particular, what it can do is it works out-of-the-box with Gmail, Facebook, and hundreds more.
It supports FIDO2, WebAuthN, U2F.
It's waterproof and crust resistance.
It works with USB-A and NFC dual connectors on a single key.
So if you do not have a UbiKey, I strongly recommend picking this one up.
This one is super cheap.
I think it's like 30 USD.
So it's not super expensive, but it's just a great way of learning how to better secure your devices.
Okay?
So we're on to the last type of join type for device management.
This one's called Hybrid Azure AD Join Devices.
And this is allowing you to join to an on-premise AD or Azure AD, requiring organizational account to sign in to the device.
So the emphasis there is on-premise, right?
It's suitable for hybrid organizations with existing on-premise AD infrastructure.
It's applicable to all users within an organization.
The device is going to be owned by the company.
For the OS, we got Windows 10, 8.1, Windows 7,
Windows Server 2008, R2, 2012, and a bunch of other ones there.
For provisioning, we got Windows 10 and Windows Server 2016, 2019.
You can join the domain by, or domain is joined by the IT, and it will auto-join via Azure AD Connect or configured with ADFS.
You can join the domain using Windows Autopilot, which we'll talk about a little bit next here in the next slide.
We got Windows 8.1, Windows 7, Windows Server 2012, et cetera.
Device sign-in options here is for the organizational account would be password, Windows Hello for Business, right?
Device management, we got group policies, configuration manager, standalone or co-management with Microsoft Intune.
For key capabilities, we got SSO to both the cloud and on-premise resources.
Conditional access through domain join or through Intune if co-managed.
Self-service, reset password, and
Windows, hello, PIN, reset on the lock screen, and last but not least, enterprise state roaming across devices.
So yeah, those are all really boring slides, but hopefully some of this information will stick in your head.
So when you see these things, you'll be able to identify between which is which.
Okay.
Okay, so we're going to look at Windows Autopilot here.
So this is a collection of technologies used to set up and pre-configure new devices, getting them ready for productive use.
I would have loved to include a diagram for this, but I couldn't find a very consistent one.
So we're going to have to live with text here today.
But this is when you're initially deploying a new Windows device.
And so Windows Autopilot uses an OEM optimized version of Windows 10.
This version is pre-installed on the device, so you don't have to maintain custom images and drivers for every model.
Instead of re-imaging the device, your existing Windows 10
Installation can be transformed into a business-ready state that can, once deployed, you can manage Windows 10 devices with Microsoft Intune, Windows Update for Business, Microsoft Endpoint Configuration Manager, and other similar tools.
So, what's the point of Microsoft Autopilot?
It's just a great way of setting up your Windows devices, okay?
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are on to the Device Management Cheat Sheet.
So Device Management allows organizations to manage laptops, desktops, and phones that need access to cloud resources.
Device Management is found under the Azure Active Directory or Azure AD service.
There are three ways to join types, or we should say bring devices into Device Management.
We have Azure Registered, which are personally owned devices or mobile devices that sign in with a local personal account, uses Windows 10 iOS, et cetera.
You have Azure AD Join.
These are devices owned by the org and signed in with an organizational account, and the access is generally for cloud native, but hybrid's possible as well.
Then you have Hybrid Azure AD Joined, and as the name says, it's really for hybrid architecture.
The devices are owned by the organization.
You're going to be using AD DS as a way of managing them, okay?
So for mobile device management, it's good for you to know this concept here.
So MDM is when you control the entire device, can wipe the data from it and also reset it to factory settings.
Whereas mobile application management, MAM, is all about publish, push, configure, secure, monitor, update mobile apps for your users.
That's at the data layer.
So that's all you need to know about device management.
There you go.
So let's take a look at the type of Azure roles.
And I was honestly first confused with Azure roles because I'm from AWS, and we only have one kind of role.
But Azure happens to have three kinds, and there's definitely good reason for it.
So let's break that down.
And the first one is classic subscription administrator roles.
And this is the original role system.
Now, it's not something you're going to be really using, but you should know about it because it still does exist.
Then you have Azure Roles.
This is the authorization system known as Role-Based Access Controls, or RBAC.
And it's built on top of Azure Resource Manager.
And then thirdly, we have Azure Active Directory, also known as Azure AD Roles.
And these Azure AD roles are used to manage Azure AD resources in a directory.
So let's jump into it.
So let's first talk about access controls, or IAM.
So IAM stands for Identity Access Management, and it allows you to create and assign roles to users.
And so this is the general interface for IAM in Azure.
And so we're going to have Azure Roles, which is part of that role.
role-based access system.
And so roles restrict access to resource actions, known as operations, and there's two types of roles for the Azure role-based access system.
You have built-in role, so this is managed by Microsoft, and they are read-only, and they're pre-created roles for you to use.
And then we have custom roles, and these are a role created by you with custom logic.
And so the place you're going to find it there is you're going to see...
It says roles right there.
And that's what we're looking at down below is a bunch of roles.
So you see owner, contributor, reader.
Those are predefined roles for you.
And so then you have role assignment.
And this is when you apply a role to either a service principal, a user group, a user.
And so that's going to be under the tab there.
So that's just you applying a role to somebody.
And then you have deny assignment.
So these block users from performing specific actions, even if a role assignment grants them access.
And the only
The only way to apply a deny assignment is through Azure Blueprint.
So this is just something where you're just setting up like guardrails to make sure that certain things are never used regardless if a role is applied.
So now let's take a look at classic administrators.
And this is the original role system.
And you honestly want to be using the new RBAC system whenever possible.
But the idea here is that you're going to go
It's in the same place that we just saw, the access control, and there's a tab called Classic Administrator.
And in there, you can set up administrators here.
And so you have three types of roles.
You have the account administrator, this is the billing owner of the subscription, and has no access to the Azure portal.
You have the service administrator, so this is the same access of a user assigned, the owner role at the subscription scope, and they have full access to Azure portal.
And then you have the co-administrator, so this is the same.
access of a user who is assigned to the owner role of the subscription scope.
So those are very three simple roles.
And we actually have one because when Baker, who's the other Andrew, set up our Azure account, I think it just sets you up one.
So even though you're not really going to be using it, I do believe that it still sets you up one when you make your account.
So that's just what it is, but there you go.
So let's take a closer look here at Azure role-based access controls, because this is something we're definitely going to be using a lot.
And so role-based access control helps you manage who has access to Azure resources, what they can do with those resources, and what areas they have access to.
And the idea is that you have a user and you want to assign them a role, so you're going to use a role assignment.
And a role assignment is made-up of three elements.
You have the security principle, the role definition, and the scope.
And we're going to look at those three things in a little bit more detail here in a second.
And there are four fundamental
Azure roles, which we are going to learn, and then Azure RBAC also includes over 70 built-in roles, which we definitely do not need to go into great detail.
So let's take a look at one of those three elements first, which is the security principle.
And this represents the identity requesting access to an Azure resource.
And when we say identity, that's just like a loose term for something.
And that something could be a user in your Azure Active Directory, a group which defines a set of users in your Azure Active Directory, a service principle, so a security identity used by applications or services
To access specified Azure resources or a managed identity, an identity in your Azure Active Directory that is automatically managed by Azure.
So, service principle is basically an Azure service, and then managed identity is something in your Azure Active Directory.
Then we'll move on to scope, and a scope is just a set of resources that access that...
assess the role, the role assignment applies to.
And so scope access controls at the management subscription or resource group level.
So what does that mean?
And we have another slide on this.
I can't remember what section it's in, but you have this breakdown of scope where you have management groups, subscriptions, resource groups, or resources.
So when you're saying I'm setting a scope, you're saying what is the scope?
Is it on a management group?
Is it on a particular resource?
Is it a resource group?
And that's what we're trying to say there.
And then last, the last element there is a role definition, and this is a collection of permissions.
So a role definition lists operations that can be performed, such as read, write, and delete.
And roles can be high-level, like owner-specific, or like a virtual machine reader.
And so Azure has built-in roles.
And we said there were four fundamental built-in roles, and here they are.
It's owner, contributor, reader, and user administrator.
So you want to know those four.
And then across the board, you have those three operations, read, grant, and then create, update, delete.
So you can see the owner can do everything.
The contributor can
both read and create stuff, but they just can't grant access to other people.
The reader just has read-only access.
And then a user access administrator is granting other users privileges, but themselves are not creating anything.
All right.
So now let's take a look at the third type of roles, and that's Azure AD roles.
And so Azure AD roles are used to manage Azure AD resources.
in the directory, such as creating or editing users, assigning administrative roles to others, resetting user passwords, managing user licenses, and managing domains.
And so on the right-hand side here, what we can do is go into Azure Active Directory in Azure, and under Roles and Administrators, we can see there is a bunch of roles predefined for us, like Application Administrator, Application Developer, et cetera.
There's a lot in there.
And a few important built-in roles that you should know is the global administrator, so this gives you full access to everything.
The user administrator, full access to create and manage users.
The billing administrator makes purchases, manage subscriptions, and support tickets.
And I want you to know that you can create your own custom roles, but for whatever reason, you have to purchase this.
to me is a bit unusual because in the AWS world,
This is something you don't have to pay for, but I guess Azure Active Directory has been around for a long time, and so they have this whole big tier in there.
And so if you want to be able to make custom roles, you have to upgrade your Azure AD to premium.
So premium could be P1 or P2, and I'm assuming the higher the number, the more controls.
Okay?
So let's take a look at the anatomy of an Azure role.
And as you saw in the previous slide, it does cost money to be able to have the privilege to create custom roles.
You'd need an Active Directory Premium version one or two.
But it's still a good practice to go take a look at what the contents of an actual role is, because you can actually look at the managed roles, open them up and see what they do.
And you should really look at them and not just take them
Based on the face value of the name of the role, so I want you to know that Azure role documents have two different syntaxes, whether you're using PowerShell or CLI, and so the example here on the right-hand side is going to be using PowerShell, and it's very simple, and it's just the property name is going to change, so see where it says Name.
If you were using PowerShell, I have in parentheses, it'd be role name.
Okay, so if you look one up and it's using JSON and the names are different, you're going to have to do that translation, all right?
So let's just quickly go through the properties here.
So the first thing is the name.
That's going to describe what the role is.
Then you have the ID.
This is not something that you are creating.
It's going to be auto-generated for you.
Then you have is custom, whether it's going to be custom or not.
The description, that's self-explanatory.
And then the actions.
This is what you care about because the actions tell you exactly what you're allowed to perform.
So that's a big list there.
It's pretty self-explanatory.
But then you have not actions.
And this is basically you explicitly saying you're not allowed to do these things.
It's just a guardrail to make things safe.
Do you really need a not actions?
I don't know.
That's just how they designed it.
Then you have data actions.
This is an array of strings that specifies data operations that are allowed to be performed within the data.
within that object.
And then you have not data actions, so things you're not allowed to do with data.
And then assignable scopes.
And this is an array of strings that specify the scope for the custom role.
And you can only define one management group for assignable scopes for a custom role.
I do want to just point out one other things with these roles.
And it really just has to do with these asterisks, just if you're not familiar with them.
But that usually indicates A wildcard permission.
It's like saying match everything.
And so when you're doing that, it's going to match things like you can use it in actions, not actions, data actions, and not data actions.
And so again, it just matches everything in that sub thing because you might have a bunch of options you can put there.
And so for example, what it's doing, like let's see, you see where it says management or cost management.
and it has action, read, write, delete, run, action, all that stuff in red would be matched with that asterisk.
And I know it doesn't match the examples on the right-hand side, but you just got to imagine that there's other things there, okay?
Now let's just do a quick comparison between Azure policies and Azure roles, just to make sure that we're very clear what the difference of these two things are.
So Azure policies, these are used to ensure compliance of resources.
And Azure roles, these are used to control access to Azure resources.
So on the policy side, these are going to evaluate the state by examining properties on the resources that are represented in resource manager and properties of some resource providers.
They do not restrict actions.
And we call this operations.
It ensures that resource state is compliant to your business rules without concern for who made change or who has permission to make the change.
Even if an individual has access to perform an action, if the result is a non-compliant resource, Azure Policy still blocks the create or update actions there.
On the role side, it's very simple.
It focuses on managing user actions at different scopes, and it does restrictions.
it does apply restrictions on Azure resources.
So Azure resource or Azure roles controls what you have access to, Azure policies, ensures compliancy.
All right, just another comparison here.
I want to compare Azure AD roles to the Azure roles, the RBAC versions.
So AD roles, they're used to control access to AD resources.
And Azure roles control access to Azure resources.
And here's a good representation here, where you have AD roles on the left-hand side and Azure roles on the right-hand side.
And the idea on the left-hand side, that actually represents like Office 365, but you can see Azure AD has some coverage both inside and outside of Azure.
So an AD resource could be something like users, groups, billing,
licensing, application registration, or et cetera.
And then on the right-hand side for Azure resources, this could be virtual machines, databases, cloud storage, cloud networking, and et cetera.
By default, Azure roles and Azure AD roles do not span Azure and 8 and Azure AD.
And by default, the global administrator doesn't have access to Azure resources.
So that's just good to know.
And global administrators can gain access to Azure resources if granted the user access administrator role, so the Azure
Azure role.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are looking at the Azure Roles Cheat Sheet.
And when we say Azure Roles Cheat Sheet, we're actually talking about all the roles, not just the Azure Roles, okay?
Because there's three types.
You've got the classic subscription administrator roles.
You have Azure Roles, which is also known as role-based access controls.
That's built on top of ARM, and then you have Azure Active Directory roles.
Okay, so you need to know the difference between the three when we're talking about Identity Access Management (IAM) that allows you to create and assign.
Azure roles to users.
Roles restrict access to resource actions, also known as operations.
There's two types of roles.
You've got built-in roles, managed Microsoft roles are read-only pre-created roles for you to use, and then you have custom roles, a role created by you with your own custom logic.
For a role assignment is when you apply a role to a user, and a role assignment is composed of a security principle, role definition, and scope.
measures for built-in roles are owner, contributor, reader, and user access administrator.
I don't have the table here, but you should know the difference between them, but usually they're pretty self-explanatory based on their name.
For classic administrators, we have three types of roles.
We've got account administrator, service administrator, and co-administrator.
For important Azure AD roles, you need to remember you have global administrator, user administrator, billing administrator, and on the exam, you might even see more kinds there, so I would encourage you to go look up all the different kinds.
Or I might end up making a video going in more in-depth for some of them in this course.
You can create custom Azure AD roles, but you're going to need that P1 or P2.
So there you go, that's Azure roles.
So Azure policies are used to enforce organizational standards to assess compliance at scale.
And policies do not restrict access.
They only observe for compliance.
So here on the right-hand side in the Azure policy portal, you're going to see a big list of policies.
And Azure has a bunch of policies built in for you right away that you can use.
So if you need to meet NIST or FedRAMP or HIPAA, what you can do is just turn those on, and it's going to check based on the categories to see if you're using Cosmo DB.
It's going to check for that compliance and tell you whether you're being compliant or not.
And there's a bunch of components that are involved when you're making Azure policies.
So you have the policy definition file.
This is just a JSON file that describes business rules to control access to resources.
You have policy assignment.
This is the scope of a policy that it can affect, assigned to a user, a resource group, or a management group.
You have policy parameters.
These are values you can pass into your policy definition, so your policies are more flexible for use.
And you have initiative definition.
And these are an initiative definition is a collection of policy definitions that you can assign.
So it's a group of policies to enforce some kind of compliance like PCI DSS compliance.
And I want you to carefully look at the screenshot on the right-hand side where it says definition type and you see policy initiative.
So the ones at the top there is talking about policy definitions.
And then you have initiative definitions which are just a group of policy definitions.
All right.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro and we're looking at Azure policies which are used to enforce organizational standards.
standards for compliance.
So once you turn on some policies, you're going to want to see when things are becoming non-compliant.
And so what you can do is you can just go under policies and compliance, and you're going to see whether something is compliant or not.
So that's what we're seeing.
And then down below, I launched an Azure Virtual Machine for disaster recovery, and you can see that it's in a non-compliant state.
So it's as simple as that.
I just wanted you to know that, okay?
So let's take a look at the anatomy of an Azure Policy Definition file.
Probably not going to be in your exam, but I think it's a really good practice just to open these up and see what they look like.
So on the right-hand side, we have an Azure policy definition file, and we'll just walk our way through it.
The first thing you're going to have is the display name that's going to describe what the policy is for.
Then you're going to have a certain type, and we have built-in, custom, and static.
So built-in means that it's maintained by Microsoft.
Then there's custom, whether it's created by you, and then static, where it's owned by Microsoft, but it's for a regulatory compliance, so maybe HIPAA or FedRAMP or something like that.
Then you have the description, so that's going to elaborate on the actual policy itself.
But generally, the display names are pretty darn robust.
Then you have metadata, and this is just going to be optional data that you can provide.
So if you look down below in the parameters, we have some metadata explaining what that parameter is.
Then you have the mode.
And so the mode is determined by the type of resource it is.
And so it can either be a resource provider or an Azure resource
or Azure Resource Manager.
In the case of Resource Manager, it's going to either be all or index.
And so for all, that's going to basically select everything like resource groups, subscriptions, and all resource types.
And for index, it's only going to be resource types that support tags and locations.
For resource provider, it's a very limited list.
And so we have the MicrosoftContainerService.data, which is now generally not used.
And then you have Kubernetes data and Key Vault.
Data, okay, and then just moving on a bit further here, I just want to go into parameters.
So, for parameters, these are values you can pass into the policy to allow the policy to be more flexible, and so here we are just to find the parameters.
So, we have the name of the parameter, the type, so string, array, object, boolean, integer, float, etc.
You'll notice that there's no name on that parameter, which is totally fine.
And then you have the metadata actually follows a particular structure.
So you have description, display name, strong type, assigned permissions.
You have the default value, which you don't necessarily have to set.
You have the allowed value.
And then when you want to reference a parameter, you're going to use this field and in.
So you say field location in.
And there you can see that we're using a function, which is very similar to the ARM templates.
And then over there, you can just see that it's over there how it's referencing it.
And then just the last thing here, I just want to talk about policy rules.
So this consists of an if and then block.
So in the if block, you define one or more conditions that specify when the policy is enforced.
And you can apply logical operators to these conditions to precisely define the scenario for a policy.
So here you have the if, and if the if is met, then make that thing happen.
So there you can see on the policy rule, if it says, if you have a type of virtual machines, then you want the effect and you'll pull in the effect parameter.
And then what it's going to do is it's going to check for the status code and make sure whether it's healthy or not.
And so that's basically how they work.
And just one more thing.
Let's just talk about the policy rule a little bit more about the policy effect.
So we have that if and then statement.
We'll just talk about what we can do there.
So deny is whether the resource as creation update failed due to policy.
Audit.
So create a warning event in the activity log when evaluating A non-compliance resource, but it doesn't stop the request.
Append.
add additional parameters fields to the requested resource during the creation or update.
A common example is adding tags on resources such as cost center or specifying allowed IPs for storage resources.
Then you have an audit if not exists.
Create a warning event in the activity log when evaluating A compliance resource, but it doesn't stop the request.
Deploy if not exists.
So execute a template deployment when a specific condition is met.
For example, if SQL encryption is enabled on a database, then it can run a template after the DB is created to specify a way.
And the last one here is disabled.
So the policy rule is ignored, often used for testing.
The reason I'm just showing you this last one here is I just wanted to show you what action is taken
based on the policy, okay?
And again, probably not going to be in your exam, but it's something I want you to know so that you understand what a policy can actually do.
And this is basically the last one I really want you to know, okay?
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're going to take a look at how to keep things compliant within our Azure account with Azure Policy.
So let's make our way over to the Azure Policy Portal by typing policy at the top here.
And right away, you can see already that I have a policy assigned.
I didn't assign this.
Azure did this for me by default, and it's a great way to start understanding how this is useful.
So I'm going to go ahead and just click into that one there.
And this is an initiative policy, meaning that it's made-up of a bunch of policies.
We'll go over that over in a moment.
But you can see here that's saying, hey, you should turn on all these things.
They're not turned on by default, so you should turn them on.
And these are ones that you have not turned on.
You might not want to consider turning some of these on if you have to consider costs, but I think most of these are free.
But that's something that you'll have to decide on your own.
But that gives you a general idea there.
So let's go back to policy at the top.
On the left-hand side here, we can see our assignments.
And here I have that initiative type there.
If I click into it, allows me to edit it there.
And what's really nice is if I want to disable it, I could just disable it.
But I think this is the default one.
So, oh, no, I can disable it.
Okay, great.
And you can see it was assigned by who.
And then you can also take remediation actions here.
So by default, this assignment will only take effect on newly created resources.
Existing resources can be updated via a remediation task after the policy is assigned.
So if you need this, apply to ones that are created or prior.
updated, that's something you might want to do.
But anyway, we'll get out of there.
And we'll go take a look at all the big list of predefined definitions that Azure gives us.
So this is a great way for us to get started.
You'll notice on the right hand side, we have initiative and we have policy.
Again, initiative is a collection of policies down below.
And these are individual ones.
Let's just go take a look at some policies.
And maybe we can go apply one to like a virtual machine.
So what I'm going to do is just drop down
This here, and we can just unselect here, and let's just go take a look.
Do we have one called virtual machines?
Not really, but we can go for compute here, and we can just take a look here.
So, audit virtual machine without disaster recovery.
Let's take a look at that one.
And I just want to see the full description here.
Audit virtual machine without disaster recovery configured.
I think that sounds really good to me.
So I'm going to go ahead and assign that.
And we can choose a scope.
And so I'm going to choose my subscription here.
And then we can choose a resource group.
And you're going to notice that I don't actually have any resources.
So to scope that within.
So what we'll go do is launch ourself a virtual machine.
So make our way over to the virtual machine portal here.
We'll add a virtual machine.
And I want something really cheap.
And so here it's set to a more expensive one because I was launching a Windows server previously, but I want the cheapest server I can get.
Actually, before I do that, I'm just going to go back and oh yeah, it's on Ubuntu, just making sure.
And the one I had that was really cheap is the B1LS.
And so I'm just going to go up here to the top.
We'll name this Bajor.
And we'll put it in the Bajor group there.
This size does not support Azure spot.
That's totally fine.
I don't need spot.
Did I turn that on by accident?
Oh, I did.
And this all looks fine to me.
I'm not going to be logging into this machine.
We just want to launch it up as an example.
I'm going to move to standard SSD because I don't need premium here.
And this looks fine to me.
We'll go ahead and hit review and create.
So we'll go ahead and create that.
And I guess we have to download that private key.
Probably a good idea.
We're not going to use it for anything, but that's okay.
And now that's deploying, let's see if we can select the scope as it's creating.
I'm not sure if it'll let us do that.
I'm just going to hit cancel here and reopen here.
And let's see if it shows up now.
It doesn't.
So we'll just wait a moment here.
I'll go back to my policy here.
And I'm just going to wait for this server to create.
And once that is created,
What we'll do is we'll just come back here and see if we can now scope that.
All right, so after a short little wait, our server is ready here, so let's make our way back to our policy here, and I guess I lost it, so I'll have to go back to definitions and we'll drop down categories, deselect, we'll go to compute.
And we'll go ahead and click on disaster recovery again.
Here you can see the policy in its entirety.
So that's kind of nice.
And we'll go ahead and assign that.
And we'll choose our scope.
So we'll go back here to subscription one.
Now we should have Bajour.
And I'll go ahead and hit select.
We can assign it exclusions, not something I'm going to do today.
There is the name of it.
That's totally fine.
And we can hit enabled.
And I'm the one who's enabling it.
So that sounds like a good idea.
We'll go next.
We're going to leave remediation off.
We don't need to do that today.
We'll hit create.
And so now this policy is assigned.
It says here, please note that the assignment takes around 30 minutes to take effect.
So we work our way back here and look at assignments.
I don't see it here yet.
So there it is.
And it's probably not going to show us on there.
So we'll go back to our overview.
And so I want to see, it hasn't started yet.
So we'll just wait for a while here.
It might take 30 minutes, might take 10, not sure.
And we'll just see what happens.
It should show up as non-compliant, but let's see that actually happen.
All right, so after waiting a little while here, I think it was about 15, 20 minutes, we can now see that it's saying that it's non-compliant.
So we'll go ahead and click into there.
And we can see what exactly it is complaining about.
Let me click over to that resource.
So there you go.
It's not too complicated there.
We'll go ahead and just delete that assignment.
And if you're wondering where blueprints are, they're all the way over here.
We talked about blueprints in the actual course, not something we actually have to do for the AZ 104, but because it is probably a better way of doing things, I just wanted to point that out to you.
But yeah, there you go.
So it's as simple as that.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro and we are looking at Azure Policies Cheat Sheet.
This is an extremely short one because there's not a whole lot we need to know, but let's get through it.
So Azure Policies enforce organizational standards.
and to assess compliance at scale.
Policies do not restrict access.
They only observe for compliance.
Once a policy is assigned, it will evaluate for compliance state periodically.
The rules of a policy are described in JSON file and is known as a policy definition.
A policy definition can be grouped together, which is known as a policy initiative, formerly known as a policy set.
So there could be some interesting information you might want to read in the Azure docs where they talk about different kinds of use cases.
I didn't see any kind of questions on the exam that were like that, so it's only for you.
own benefit, but I just want to tell you, you might round out your knowledge there, so there you go.
All right, so let's take a quick introduction into Azure Resource Manager, which is short for ARM, and is a service that allows you to manage Azure resources.
And one thing that really confused me about the service when I first started using Azure was that you couldn't just type in Azure Resource Manager.
And the reason why is because it's actually a collection of services, and it makes up what we call this
Management layer, and it allows you to do things like create, update, delete resources, apply management features such as access controls, locks, and tags, writing infrastructure as code via JSON templates, and there are very specific features we're going to be looking at that make up the ARM layer, and it's going to be the following: so we're going to be looking at subscriptions, management groups, resource groups.
resource providers, resource locks, Azure blueprints, resource tags, access control, so also known as IM, role-based access controls, Azure policies, and ARM templates.
I don't know why I don't have tenant in there.
I might have it in another slide, but it's not a big deal.
But that is what we're going to be covering in this Azure Resource Manager section.
All right.
Hey.
Hey, this is Angie Brown from ExamPro, and we are taking a look here at Azure Resource Manager, which is a deployment and management service for Azure that enables you to create, update, and delete resources in your Azure account.
So let's take a quick look at the use case for Azure Resource Manager.
And this is just to kind of give you a visualization because it is an abstract thing.
So I just want you to have some kind of picture in your head of what it is.
So here I have this diagram and just to follow up with this tech, think of Azure Resource Manager as a gatekeeper and all requests flow through ARM and it decides whether that request can be performed on a resource.
And so on the left-hand side, you have your requests.
And so requests could be happening in the Azure portal.
be the Azure PowerShell, the CLI, or the REST client, which would be the API.
And then you can see the two middle ones would use the Azure SDK.
And then in the middle, that's the gatekeeper.
And so we have Azure Resource Manager.
That's going to work in conjunction with your authentication, which generally should be Active Directory.
I don't think you can swap that out for anything else.
And then on the right-hand side, you're going to get access to resources.
So this could be virtual machines, containers, databases, and storage.
There's obviously a lot of Azure
services, but that is what it is in a snapshot.
So let's understand the concept of scoping, because this is going to help you understand all the components that are involved with Azure's Resource Manager.
So what is a scope?
A scope is a boundary of control for Azure resources, and it is a way to govern your resources by placing resources within a logical grouping, applying logical restrictions in the form of rules.
And so let's now go break down what
these scopes are.
And so the first scope we're going to talk about is management groups.
And this is a logical grouping of multiple subscriptions, just because you can have lots of subscriptions in your account.
And you might want a subscription to a collection of subscriptions to belong to some kind of domain.
So maybe it's for development or business or data sciences, whatever you want.
Then you have a subscription.
And this grants you access to Azure services based on a billing and support agreement.
So the idea is that
When you launch resources, you're going to choose what subscription to go under.
It's just going to determine the billing, okay, under that things you're going to pay for.
Then you have resource groups.
This is a logical grouping of multiple resources within a subscription.
Then you have resources.
This is...
The actual service itself, like Azure Virtual Machine, and I just want you to know that we're going to revisit the scope when we go look at role-based access controls, because that's going to really help it make a lot more sense.
Okay, but let's just go jump into some of these scopes in specific and talk about them a bit more.
So let's take a closer look here at subscriptions.
So the thing is, before you can do anything in your Azure account, you're going to need a subscription.
And the reason why is that you need to have a subscription so that when you're launching resources, they know what kind of plan to put you on because they want to bill you, right?
And so in Azure, you can actually have multiple subscriptions.
And the most common ones are a free trial, pay as you go, Azure for students.
And the most common three ones I want you to know about are
those three there.
And so there's actually a lot more boxes than that.
And so just as an example to show you outside of the scope of those, if you wanted developer support, you'd have to pay for a developer support subscription.
And the thing is that the subscription level, you'll have the ability to do a lot of things.
So this is where you can set resource tags, your access controls, which you're going to look at here in a second.
Resource groups and a lot of other things, so just to pull up there, you can see under the description there's access controls, and I've added myself as a user, and that is that there.
So let's take a look here at Azure Management Groups.
And the idea here is you're able to manage multiple subscriptions within a hierarchical structure.
And so each directory is given a single top-level management group called the Root Management Group.
And all these subscriptions within a management group automatically inherit the conditions applied to the management group.
So here is this hierarchical structure that we're talking about.
And you can see that the root is on the top, and underneath we have management groups such as human.
resources, IT, marketing, and within those accounts we have different subscriptions.
And you can even see that you can have a resource group within a resource group to really narrow that down.
And again, the whole point is that you're creating these choke points where you can apply access controls and other permissions so that, you know, let's say you only want people within the marketing account to only have access to billing information, then you're locking down all those sub-accounts or subscriptions
in order to only have access to that kind of stuff.
So there you go.
So let's take a quick look here at resource groups.
So here is a visual representation of a bunch of virtual machines within a resource group.
And all resource group is a container that holds related resources.
And then an individual resource would be one of those virtual machines.
And then you have the resource provider.
And that's a service that supplies Azure
The Azure resource, and so, in this case, we have Microsoft.compute, and we're going to look in greater detail at resource providers next, because there's a little bit more to it than just that.
So, in order to use an Azure resource, you're going to have to register resource providers, and many resource providers are already registered by default for you within your subscription, and that's why you're able to use a lot of services right off the bat.
So here in Azure subscriptions, if you go down to resource providers, you're going to see a bunch of provider names like Microsoft Compute or Microsoft Consumption and a variety of other ones.
And the idea is that you're going to register them, basically turn them on.
And so there's some services that you might search for that are just not available.
I think Kubernetes might be one.
And so the thing is that if you are following a tutorial or you're trying to find something in the documentation, but you're typing it in into the search bar and it's not showing up, it's possible you just don't have it registered.
And so all you'd have to do is to go to your subscription and then register that.
And it's just kind of like a safeguard so that, you know, if there are services that are expensive or things like that, you are making the conscious decision to say, yes, I want to use this.
Okay?
Let's take a look at the concept of resource tags, or just sometimes known as a tag.
And this is a key and value pair that you can assign to Azure resources.
So generally when you are launching a new resource, you're going to have a tags page, and this is where you can apply that key and value name.
And just to give you some examples of tags you might want to apply, you might want to have a department and then the type of department, status approved,
a team, an environment, or the project, or the location.
And so you have a lot of tags that you can apply.
And tags allow you to organize your resources in the following ways.
You can organize them via resource management, so that's where you are specifying workloads, environments like developer environments.
There's cost management and optimization, so cost tracking, budgets and alerts, operation management, so the
That could be business commitments to SLA operations, so you might want to tag services that are considered mission-critical services.
There's security, so that's classification of data and security impact.
So, if there's certain databases that have very specific compliance rules, you might want to do that as well, which I think is the next example here, or maybe you're defining...
Services that are used for automation or services that are for workload optimization, so there's a lot to do with tags, and even though I don't use them frequently in my follow-alongs, it's definitely something that's a good habit to do and you should do in your production workloads.
Let's take a look at resource lock.
So, as an admin, you might have a case where you want to lock a subscription, resource group, or resource to prevent other users from accidentally deleting or modifying critical resources.
So, within the Azure portal, you can set the following lock levels: you have the cannot delete.
which basically prevents deletion.
So authorized users can still read a modified resource, but they can't delete the resource.
And the other mode is read-only.
So authorized users can read a resource, but they can't delete or update the resource.
So those are the two modes, and that's something you might be interested in doing.
Let's take a look at Azure Blueprints.
And this is a way to enable quick creation of governed subscriptions.
The keyword there is governed.
So the idea is like you can go in your account and just create a subscription.
But when it's a governed subscription, that means there's a process and certain expectations on how the subscription should be set up.
So the idea is you're going to compose artifacts based on common or organization-based patterns into reusable blueprints.
And the service is designed to help with environment setup.
So blueprints are
declarative way to orchestrate the deployment of various resource templates and artifacts.
I just want to emphasize that we're declarative.
Declarative means that everything is spelled out, so we exactly know what's going to be created.
And so artifacts could be role assignments, policy assignments, Azure Resource Manager templates, also known as ARM templates, resource groups.
And the Azure Blueprint service is backed by the globally distributed Azure Cosmos DB.
Blueprint objects are replicated to multiple regions, so they're definitely well backed up.
And so the main question people are going to ask, well, what's the difference between an ARM template and an Azure Blueprint?
Because an ARM template can automate the setup of stuff.
Well, basically, nearly everything you want to include for deployment in an Azure Blueprint can technically be accomplished in an ARM template.
But the thing is that an ARM template, you are storing that either locally or in source control, and there is no active connection or
relationship to the ARM template.
Whereas Azure Blueprints, the relationship between the blueprint definition, what should be deployed, and the blueprint assignment, what was deployed, and it can also be upgraded, it can also upgrade several subscriptions at once that are governed by the same blueprint.
So blueprints support improved tracking and auditing of deployments, that is a thing.
So they're very similar to ARM templates,
But generally, if you have the option, you should always use Azure Blueprints.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andy Brown from Exam Pro, and what we're going to be doing is moving resources from one resource group to another and understanding the limitations around that.
So I just have this page pulled up here because I just want to emphasize that I've seen exam questions on this stuff, and there's a lot of little nitty-gritty things that could show up as a solution.
So the idea is that when you're talking about moving
resources, you're moving them into different regions or to different subscriptions or different resource groups.
And generally, they're pretty straightforward, but there are some edge cases where things will not work as expected, and that's based on some particular services.
So when we're looking at app services, DevOps services, classic deployment, network movement guidance, recovery services, virtual machines, so I definitely know that for app services, you're going to run into issues
Like if you're moving from one subscription to another, and you already have a web app service in the one that you're moving it into, it won't allow you to do it.
And so there's a lot of little things like that, okay?
And also, if you are migrating them, you can go ahead and use the diagnostic tool to debug it, and it will tell you some additional information.
So you will have to read through all of these.
I just can't show you all of that in a follow along.
But what we'll do is we'll just go through the basics here of moving things between resource groups.
And so what we'll need is a few resource groups.
So I'm going to add a new one.
And we're going to call this one the USS or the Federation of Planets.
And we'll put that in East US.
And then we will make another resource group.
We'll call this the Klingon Empire.
And for fun, we will place it in West.
So we'll go ahead and create that.
So now we just need something we can move around back and forth.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to make my way over to disk, because that's a great example of something we can move around and change.
And so I'm going to add a new disk.
And I'm going to place this in the Federation.
And I'm just going to say dilithium.
I can never spell that right.
Well, let's see if I can get the proper spelling for this thing that is not real.
Dilithium here.
And so it's going to be over here.
I don't care about availability zones and stuff like that.
Source type, this is fine.
And so we have the initial size.
I do not need to drive that big.
Let's go super small.
We could even do an HDD because those are even cheaper.
And we'll just choose the small size down here.
And so we'll pick 32.
And so this should be all final encryption, networking, we don't really care.
We're not doing anything other than moving this around.
So we'll go ahead and review and create.
Right.
And so then we'll go create that resource.
And we'll just wait a little while here, it shouldn't take too long.
Alright, so the disk is ready.
So we'll go to this resource.
And here it is.
So now let's say we want to move that to our other resource group, which is in another region, what we're going to do is we're going to go back to our resource groups here.
And if we go into the Federation of planets,
what we can do is go to overview, select the disk, go over here and say move to another resource group.
And I'll just click these other ones to show you.
I don't have any other subscriptions to move this to.
So I'll just go back there.
I thought maybe I could show you some stuff, but I just realized I don't have much in this account or with other subscriptions.
So we'll just go back to overview here and just move it to another resource group.
And technically we're moving it to another region, so we'll see how that goes.
And so we will select the Klingon Empire, I understand that the tools and scripts associated with the will not work, etc, etc.
So we'll hit OK.
And that's going to take a little bit of time to move.
So while that is going, I'm going to make a new tab so we don't lose that history there.
And I just want to talk about some settings you can put on your resource groups.
So if we go into the Klingon Empire, and we go down below here, we should have the ability to apply locks.
And there are a few different types of locks, we have read only and delete.
So read only means it's a read only resource.
And delete means we cannot delete the resource, which makes sense, right?
So read only should mean we shouldn't be able to modify this.
So I'm going to say, don't touch, do not touch.
And I say OK here.
And so what that means is that I should not be able to modify the resource.
Whether I can delete it or not is another story.
We'll find that out.
And another question is, can I move that resource outside of this if it's set to those modes?
And that's what we're going to find out.
So moving back over here, has this finished moving?
It's still validating.
So we're going to have to wait a little bit here, and I'll see you back in a moment.
All right, so after waiting a little while here, I believe that it's done moving.
So I'm still in my old resource group here.
What we'll do is click back into here, go to overview, and we see that it's no longer there.
But if we go over to the Klingon Empire, we go back over, just click into overview.
There it is.
So we had no problems moving a disk to another region and another resource group.
Now we did apply this lock over here.
So what is going to happen when we try to modify
this disk.
I think you know the answer, but let's give it a go just to see what happens.
So over here, we're going to want to resize it here.
I'm going to pick 64.
I'm going to go hit resize.
And it says fail to update the disk because of that reason.
So you cannot perform a write operation because of the lock.
So there you go.
Now let's go back and we are going to go apply another lock here.
This time I'm going to make it so you can't delete it.
And so we say, don't, do not delete me.
All right.
And so what we'll do is we'll go back and we'll try to delete it.
So we'll hit the delete button.
We'll say yes.
Again, it says you cannot do it.
Now here's the next question.
Can you move that resource out or in to resource group if it has lock or read only on?
And that's what I want you to guess whether you can or not.
Because you are in read-only, so would you be able to move something that's read-only?
So we'll go ahead and move it.
We're going to move this to another resource group, and I'm going to send it back to the Federation of Planets.
I say, I understand.
Hit OK.
And it failed to check.
We'll see why.
Cannot perform the write operation because there are locks.
Please remove some of the locks.
So which is it?
Is it delete?
Is it the read-only?
Do I have to remove both?
That's what we need to go find out.
So back in our resource group, I'm going to go ahead and 1st remove pair resource locks can't be edited here.
Okay, that's fine.
So we'll go back to here and we will go into the locks and we'll first delete the read only.
And then what we'll do is we will attempt to delete this again.
See what happens.
It looks like it's moving.
So it's not that you can't move it out if it's in read-only, or sorry, in delete, but you can't if it's read-only because it's read-only, right?
Now, when we're talking about moving resources into a group that's set to read-only, I'm almost certain that you can absolutely do that.
So we could stage that, I guess, just to make sure.
So what I'm going to do
is I'm just going to set up another resource group, just to make sure that we know this for certain, just in case I'm wrong, the Romulan Star Empire, Romulan Star Empire, and I'm going to just leave it in the same region.
And so for this one in particular,
What I'm going to do is apply a read-only.
I might as well just put both on here, but I'll just, I'm just going to do read-only.
And we'll say, do not delete me.
And then what I'll do is I'll go back to the Federation planets.
And I'm just going to, actually I'll just go to disks and we'll create a new disk here.
And we will place it in the Federation here.
And we will just say,
dark matter, or antimatter.
And we will just change this to HHD as small as we can go.
We'll review and create that.
And we'll go ahead and create that.
And this will not take long, we do not have to wait that long for this.
And notice here that
We could not, this is interesting.
So there was an error moving the resource.
Moving resources failed because resource group federation has active deployment.
So if you are moving stuff and then you do deploy, it's going to cancel that deploy.
So that's interesting to know.
So I believe that this new one is deployed.
I cannot remember.
I think we set this one to have read only here on the
what do you call the Romulan Star Empire, which isn't showing up.
There it is.
Just double check there.
So the question is, can I move a resource into a read only?
We'll go here.
And I guess we need to actually go to the Federation of Planets.
We'll go to overview, we have antimatter, and I want to move that into Romulan.
Star Empire.
See, I understand.
It will either say we can or we can't.
And we absolutely can.
Otherwise, it would error it out at this point.
So hopefully you can keep that straight.
So you can move a resource into a group that has read-only.
You cannot move it out if it's set.
You can absolutely move it out if it's set to delete.
Delete just protects against delete.
If you are moving a resource from one resource group to another,
And then you deploy something, it's going to cause that movement to fail, and then there's those edge cases for moving resources with Azure, and that's something you should spend some time reading up on those use cases, or maybe I'll just pick out the most important ones and put it into a cheat sheet.
All right, and so what I'm going to do is just go ahead and clean this stuff up.
So what I need to do here is go and remove the delete.
I think it's only on here.
So we go to my locks.
I'm going to go back to resource groups here.
And we will delete the locks here.
And so now I can go ahead and delete these.
Groups.
I guess I have to do them one by one, which is kind of annoying, but that's just how it goes.
It says it's locked.
It's not locked anymore.
Oh, it's still there.
Look at that.
Okay.
Could have swore I definitely did something there.
we go.
And we will go ahead and delete the last one.
There we are.
So, hopefully a bit more about moving resources around.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're looking at the Azure Resource Manager Cheat Sheet.
So ARM is a service that allows you to manage Azure resources.
It is a management layer that allows you to create, update, delete resources, apply management features such as access controls, locks, and tags, writing infrastructure as code, as JSON templates, and we have a totally separate section and cheat sheet for just ARM templates alone.
ARM is a service layer that spans multiple features and services, so subscriptions, management groups, resource groups, provider resource
providers, resource locks, Azure blueprints, resource tags, IAM, role-based access controls, Azure policies, ARM templates.
So it's all over the place.
Think of Azure, or sorry, ARM as a gatekeeper.
All requests flow through ARM and it decides whether the request can be performed on a resource.
Scope is a boundary of control for Azure resources.
It's a way to govern your resources by placing resources within a logical grouping and also applying logical restrictions in the form of rules.
And that hierarchy
The structure of that is management groups, subscriptions, resource groups, and resources.
An Azure account has multiple subscriptions, and the most common three are free, trial, pay-as-you-go, Azure for students.
Resource providers is a list of possible services within Azure, and some services are registered by default, and others need to be explicitly registered.
So if you're using the Azure portal and a service, you type in the search and it's not working, it's probably just because you need to register it.
Resource tags is a
key and value pair that you can assign to Azure resources.
Resource locks prevent users from accidentally modifying or deleting resources at the subscription, resource groups, or resource scope.
We got two types of resource locks, cannot delete.
And again, there's inconsistency between the portal and also the API.
So cannot delete is delete.
And this just means users cannot delete resources, and read-only means they cannot modify them and things like that, okay?
Blueprints enable quick creation of governed subscriptions.
Nearly everything you want to include for deployment in Azure Blueprints can be accomplished in an ARM template.
Relationships between blueprint definitions, what should be deployed, and the blueprint assignment, what was deployed.
So there you go.
So let's take a look at ARM templates.
And before we jump into it, let's just make sure we're familiar with infrastructure as code, because that's what ARM templates are all about.
And this is the process of managing and provisioning computer data centers, such as Azure, through machine readable definition files, such as a JSON file, and in this case, an ARM template, because that's all it is, a JSON file.
And rather than physical hardware configuration or interactive configuration tools.
And just to simplify that even further, basically you're writing a script that's going to set up your cloud services
for you.
And with IACs, they usually come in two different flavors.
We have declarative, that's where exactly what you write is what you get, and imperative.
So you're going to generally define what you want, and then the service will guess what you want.
It's going to fill in the blanks to save you a lot of time writing those scripts.
And so ARM templates are JSON files that define Azure resources that you want to provision.
and Azure services that you want to configure.
And with ARM templates, they are going to be declarative, so you get exactly what you define.
They're going to stand up, tear down, or share entire architectures in minutes, and they're going to reduce configuration mistakes.
And you know exactly what you have defined for a stack to establish an architectural baseline for compliance.
So you definitely want to use ARM templates or IAC whenever you can, and try to avoid using the console unless you're doing development or test workloads.
But
But let's just run through the big list of what you can do with an ARM template.
I know this is a big boring list, but let's just get through it as quickly as possible, just so we know what we can do with ARM templates.
So with ARM templates, they're declarative.
So what you see is what you get.
You can stand up, tear down, share entire environments in minutes.
You can reduce configuration mistakes.
You can establish an architectural baseline for compliance.
They're modular, so you can break up your architecture in multiple files and reuse them.
They're extendable, so you can add PowerShell and Bash scripts to your templates.
It has testing, so you can use the ARM TTK to test, make sure exactly what you've deployed is what you wanted.
You have preview changes, so before you create infrastructure via templates, you see what it will create.
Built-in validation, so it will only deploy your template if it passes.
Track deployments, keep track of changes to your architecture over time.
Policy as code, so apply Azure policies to ensure you remain compliant.
And then you have Microsoft Blueprints, which we did cover here.
which establishes the relationship between resources and templates.
So it's just one step further where ARM templates don't have any relationship with the resources, where Blueprints is like a better version of ARM templates.
And then you have CICD integration, exportable code.
So exporting the current state of the resource groups and resources, authoring tools, I believe, is the last on our list here.
So you can use Visual Studio Code that has advanced features for authoring ARM templates.
Makes it a lot easier to write them.
So there you go.
So now we were talking about what ARM templates can do.
Let's actually take a look at what one looks like.
And so just to get a good snapshot or overview, let's just define what the skeleton is, the general structure of an ARM template.
So here on the right-hand side, we have JSON, and you can see that we have a structure there.
So we have schema, content version, API profile, parameters, variables, functions, resources, outputs.
and let's go down the list here and see what all these things are.
So the schema describes the properties that are available within a template.
And so the idea is that you have that JSON link there, and it's going to say, we expect the schema, the actual structure, to have these parameters.
Then you have the content version.
This is the version of the template, and you can provide any value for this element.
It's totally abstract.
It's just your way of keeping track of the version of your current template.
Then you have the API profile.
You use this value to avoid having to specify API versions for
for each resource in the template.
You have parameters.
These are values you can pass along to your template.
You have variables.
This is where you transform your parameters or resource properties using function expressions.
You have functions.
These are user-defined functions available within the template.
You have resources.
These are the Azure resources you want to deploy or update.
And then you have outputs.
And these are the values that are returned after deployment.
So let's go more into deep into some of these things.
So let's take a deeper look here at the resource section within your ARM template.
And so a resource is an Azure resource you want to provision.
Could be a virtual machine, could be a database.
And so here on the right-hand side, look at where it says resources, and we're going to take a breakdown of the actual columns or attributes that we can set.
So the first thing is the type, and this is going to follow the format of the resource provider and resource type.
So there you can see that we are setting up a storage account.
Then we have the API version, and this is the version of REST API that we're going to use for that resource.
And each resource provider publishes its own API version.
So you've got to go look up each one because they all could be different.
Then you have the name of the resource.
And so I believe there that is using a variable, so that is going to be dynamic.
Then you have the location.
So most resources have a location property, and that's the region that you want it to be deployed in.
Then you have other properties, and other properties can
will be based on different kinds of resources.
So for a storage account, you want to be able to set the kind, and within the properties, you're going to have a bunch of other options there.
And it's just going to vary, okay?
But anyway, let's take a closer look next at parameters.
So let's take a closer look here at parameters.
And these allow you to pass variables to your ARM template.
So on the right-hand side, we have
Our ARM template, and we saw before resources, but if you look above there, we have a thing called parameters, and so there we are setting a parameter, and then down below in the resource we are accessing.
a parameter.
And so let's just actually talk about some of the parameter options we have.
So the first thing you'll want to do is set a type.
And on the right-hand side, you can see that we're saying it's a string.
And so we can define that as a string, secure string, int, bool, object, secure object, and array.
And there are some other things that we can provide when we are defining our parameters that we're not showing in that diagram, but we have default values.
So this is if you do not provide, if there's no value being passed in, this is what it should use.
Then you have allowed values.
So this
where it's an array and you're restricting it to only the values that are there.
Then you have the min value.
So if you, let's say it's an integer, you want to say this is the minimum value, so it can only, like nothing lower than 10.
Then you have the max value, so nothing above 10.
You have the minimum length.
So if you're working with strings, you might say it has to be a minimum of five characters.
Then you have the maximum.
So let's say you have a maximum of five characters.
Then you have the description.
So this is just going to be something that when you are using the ARM template within the portal, you know what it's for.
So if you don't have a great description for that parameter or name and you want to provide more information, that's what you can do.
So there you go.
So.
So let's take a look here at functions for ARM templates.
And these allow you to apply transformations to your ARM variables.
And they come in two flavors.
We have template functions, which are built-in functions, and then user-defined functions, which are custom functions that we're creating to allow what other kind of functionality that we want.
So the way functions work is you give the function name.
So here it's called equals.
And then you have parentheses, and you pass in what you want to transform.
So if you see parentheses,
That's how you know that is a function.
So let's talk about some of the built-in functions.
And so there are a lot available for us, and they're generally self-explanatory, so I'm not going to be showing examples.
Let's just go quickly through the list.
So you have array functions like array, concat, contains, create, array, empty, first, et cetera.
Then you have comparisons like less, equals, less, lesser, equals, greater, greater, or equals.
You have date functions.
You have deployment functions, and for example, parameters and variables are actually functions, so that's kind of interesting.
Then you have a logical operator, so end, or if not, or numerical functions like add, div, float, int, min, max objects, so contains empty intersection, and then you have resources, so extension resource ID.
Providers, references, et cetera, like that, and there's one more I think we have strings, so we have base sixty-four, concat, contains, et cetera.
I'm not going to show you how to do user-defined functions I don't think that's that important, but I just want to show you that you have a lot of functions available to you, okay?
So let's take a look at variables.
And variables are used to simplify your ARM templates.
And the idea is that you're transforming parameter and resource properties using functions and then assigning them to reusable variables.
So under your variables section, notice that we have storage name.
And on the right-hand side, we're just using a bunch of functions and assigning it to storage name.
So the idea is that when we have to go call them in our resources, it's going to be a lot shorter than if we had to write that whole thing in there.
And what's more interesting is that you can nest your variables within a JSON object.
So on the left-hand
side, you have this variables, environment settings, test, instance sizes, et cetera.
And then on the right-hand side, we have a parameter that were defined here.
And then down below, you can see that we're calling that parameter, and then we're calling variables, environment settings, and then using the square braces to then call within that nested object.
I know that seems really confusing, but just take a moment to look at it and it will make sense.
And you'll just understand that there's a lot of power there.
So there you go.
So last on our list here for ARM templates is outputs, and outputs return values from deployed resources, so you can use them pragmatically.
This is very simple.
So the idea here is that you have outputs, and let's say you want to output the resource ID, so you can say it's a string, and in the value you could use a variable or a bunch of functions.
And the idea is that when you use the CLI, so imagine here you are using the CLI and you're saying, show me this deployment group, and
I want to see the output of values.
So see where it says creates this properties output resource ID value.
The idea is that now I'm going to be able to pragmatically access it after I've created the resource.
And this is a great way of chaining things.
So you might have a bunch of ARM templates you want to run in sequence, and you're going to need the outputs to go into the next one, and that is what you're going to use outputs for.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from ExamPro, and we are looking at Azure Resource Manager Templates, also known as ARM Templates, and this helps you deliver infrastructure as code, meaning that when you have a resource such as a virtual machine or a storage account, instead of manually configuring it every single time through the portal, what you can do is provide a configuration file that defines all the properties that you want it to be configured with, and the idea is that you can...
But keep this file and share with other people so they can easily create the same resources as you.
And then exactly how your stuff is configured.
So what we're going to do is launch a new template.
Now, you can't go up here and just type in ARM because these ARM templates are managed at different levels.
So at one level is a subscription or they're resource groups.
So when you have a resource group, you have deployments within them, and that's where these templates are deployed.
But just to deploy one from here, what we're going to do is type in deploy.
Why they didn't make it so you can type in ARM, I do not know.
But if you go down here, we have deploy a custom template.
And so from here, we have some common templates.
So if I click into web app and I go edit a template, we already have some stuff pre-filled in.
I'm just going to go back and discard that, go back to select a template, and we're going to build our own.
And by default, we'll have that schema, that content version, which is 1.0.0.0, our parameters and our resources.
So today I want to launch a virtual machine.
And what you normally would have to do is go here and look up what it is that you want to create.
So if it's this, Microsoft Compute Virtual Machine, you'd go through here and you'd have to make sure you have all these properties.
So you define the resource here, right, the type.
And then you define the properties that you want.
And down below, you can go through here and see them all.
That's a lot of work.
I don't want to do that.
So I'll go to add resource here, drop this down and click.
Or is it virtual machine?
Where are you?
There you are.
And I'm going to call this one WARF.
And then WARF and WARF, because it's not just going to create a virtual machine, it's going to create other things that I need with it as well, such as the storage account, the network interface, and the virtual network.
So you can see that we have a bunch of parameters here.
So the name, the type, the name, the admin username, the password, and the OS version.
and you know what?
I think I chose a Windows one.
I do not want a Windows one.
I want a Linux one because that is easier for me to work with here.
So we choose Ubuntu.
So I'll just fill this in again.
All right.
And so back up here, you know, we have the Ubuntu version between some versions here.
And then there's the type.
So that's for replication.
Then we have variables here.
So if we go to VM size, this is the VM it will set here.
Variables are either you can have string values or you can use functions to transform other parameters into other stuff that you'll reference throughout your template.
Then down below we have those resources here.
So what we'll do is actually I'm going to copy this because it's very highly likely we're going to want to make some kind of change.
And so I have VS Code over here on the left or right hand side.
I'm just going to paste that on in there.
And what we will do, this is a JSON file, make things a little bit easier here.
Great.
And what I'll do is just move that off screen and we'll go ahead and we will save this and we'll see if we can deploy this.
So I'm going to type in WARF here and we'll launch in Canada East.
I'll name this WARF.
We will name the username WARF, but lowercase, and then we'll do testing, 123456, capital on the T.
Notice that it is hidden there.
And then we will choose 14, which is defaulted here, and LRS.
We'll go ahead and do review and create.
And we'll hit create here.
So this is going to fail.
I already know because it has a misconfiguration.
It'll tell us how.
But while that's going, we'll take a look at our inputs.
So this is the values that were inputted.
These are the outputs, if we had defined any, which we have not.
And if we go back to our template, I just wanted to show you that we have that secure string.
So when we were typing our password, that's why we didn't see it.
So just things like that.
So I'll go back up here and our deploy failed.
Why?
What happened?
So we open it up here.
The requested VM size, standard D1, is not available in the current region.
So the template we have is not that great.
It needs some configuration because we can't use D1.
I think that doesn't exist anymore.
And so what we really want to use is the standard B1 LS.
All right.
Standard B1LS.
So I'm going to cut that.
And for the time being, I'm going to go back to our original template.
And this is 1 big template.
I'm going to look for those variables.
Oh, they're all the way to the bottom here.
Nice.
And so I'm going to just go ahead and paste that in.
B1LS, just double check, making sure I spelled that right.
Standard.
Standard B1 LS looks good to me.
So I'm going to move that off screen.
And the question is, what do we do?
What do we do when a deploy fails?
So let's go take a look at what has happened here.
So this all got deployed into a resource group.
And under here, this is where our deployments are.
So when we look at this template, we can see that it failed.
We can click into here, get the same information.
And if we click into here, it just brings us back to where we just were.
But if we go look at what was actually deployed under our resource group, under the overview, we'll notice that it created the virtual network, the storage account, and the network interface.
So when it fails, it creates what it can, but it doesn't roll back.
Okay?
So the question is, then how do you do cleanup?
So you might think, I'll go to deployments.
And what I'll do is go ahead and delete that template.
And we can go ahead and do that.
Which by the way, you can't edit this template, all you can do is all we can do here.
See, I just want to show you that you cannot edit it.
We can download it and stuff like that.
But so you might think, well, if I go ahead and delete that template, just making sure we're in the right place here.
You might think that might roll back those resources, but it doesn't, it just deletes the template.
So if you really want to get rid of this stuff, what you got to do is go ahead and delete all these resources manually.
So I wish it kind of had a rollback feature, but that's just how it is.
But there are some nice things that Azure does here, which we'll talk about in a moment.
So I think we have adjusted it to the correct value now.
So hopefully this is going to be all we need to make it work.
So what we'll do is go to our deployments here.
And we can't do it here.
But so we'll go back to the top here and type in deploy.
And we'll go to custom template.
And what we'll do is build our own template in our editor.
And I'm just going to copy the contents here.
Okay, we'll go copy.
And I will go paste.
And we'll make sure that this is all good looks fine to me, we'll go ahead and hit Save.
And we will choose WARF so we don't have to make a new one.
And we will fill in the name as WARF.
The username is WARF.
I'll call WARF 2 just in case.
Helps us keep track of what we're doing here.
Testing 123456 with a capital on the T.
14 LRS.
And we'll go ahead.
Oh, we have one issue here.
Cannot deploy resource group WARF deleting.
We'll go back.
And we will hit create here.
I don't think I deleted the resource group.
Let me just go double check.
I'm almost certain I deleted all the contents of it, right?
Oh, so there's already one here, so we're just waiting for that to delete.
It's going to go delete for us, please.
Thank you.
It failed to delete.
We'll go take a look as to why.
Resource is not found.
We'll go back to our resource groups.
Give us a refresh here.
Okay, so you know what?
I must have deleted the resource group, which is totally fine.
I could have saw I only deleted the contents of it, but we'll just call this warf regular then.
We'll go ahead and hit create here.
And so this time, I have a better feeling about this.
And so we'll just have to wait a little bit.
It won't take too long.
I'll see you back in a moment.
Okay, so after waiting a little bit here, our thing seems to be deployed.
So if we go to resource groups, we can see that our virtual machine is deployed.
So that's pretty much all there is to it.
One other thing I'd like to show you is that whatever you have, whatever is in your resource group, you can actually export the template.
So if you did configure something manually, all you'd have to do is find the resource, go up here to, it is export template, and there's your template.
So it just has that single resource in there.
I can't remember if I go into here, if I select multiples, and I go, or where is it?
Export template.
look, it's gonna include all that stuff.
So if you already have existing resources that you provisioned, and you want to have them, that's what you can do.
Notice that some things won't be included in the template when you do that, but you can just go ahead and download them.
And then you have them for later.
So yeah, that's all there really is to arm other than learning the, the nitty gritties of the actual language.
That's just how you work with it there.
So what I'm going to do is make my way over to my resource group here.
And I'm just going to go ahead and delete
this here.
And we're all good to go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are looking at Azure Resource Manager templates, also known as ARM templates.
So the thing we need to know is infrastructure as code.
This is the process of managing and provisioning computer data centers through machine-readable definition files, such as JSON files, rather than physical hardware configuration or interactive configuration tools.
IAC comes in two flavors.
We've got declarative, which is what you define is what you get, and imperative.
So you say generally what you want, and it will guess or fill in the blanks for you.
For ARM
templates.
They are JSON files, as we're suggesting above there, that once you provision Azure services, you want to configure, they are declarative, so you get exactly what you define.
An ARM template is made of the following JSON structure.
You should know the structure pretty well because you might see questions where they're showing you that code.
So be sure you know all these parts.
Schema describes the properties that are available within a template.
Content version, the version of the template, you can provide any value for this element.
API profile uses value to avoid having to specify API versions for each resource in the template.
Parameters, values you can pass along to your template.
Variables, things you can transform parameters or resource properties using functions and expressions.
And I didn't include them in the cheat sheet, but there is a bunch of variations on variables and functions, but I think that's practical skills you should just grab.
We don't want this in a cheat sheet.
Functions use defined functions available within the template.
There are so many functions, it wasn't even worth.
pulling them out and putting some here.
Resources, the Azure resources you want to deploy or update.
And under resources, you've got type of resource, API version, the name, the location, other properties, which can be a bunch of different stuff, so there's no consistency there.
And then outputs, which are values that are returned after deployment, so you can do things with them pragmatically.
So there you go.
That is the ARM templates cheat sheet.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are looking at Azure Storage Accounts, which is used for containing all your Azure Storage data objects, such as blobs, files, queues, tables, and disks.
So storage accounts is one of those services where it has a bunch of different storage types within it.
So it's quite the multi-purpose service.
And with each different type of storage, it's going to have different features and their own pricing models.
So let's just quickly break down the type of storage we have.
So we have general purpose, version 1, version 2, BLOB storage, block BLOB storage, and file storage.
And so I just want you to know that when you are using storage accounts,
I'm saying storage type, but for whatever reason, the UI calls it account kind, just to be aware of that small little discrepancy there.
But storage accounts are going to vary based on features.
And so the common features we'll see across storage will be supported services.
So where can I put the storage account?
And so on the right-hand side, you can see.
if you make a general purpose version 2, what you have access to, such as containers, queues, tables, or fosters, those options are going to change based on what you're using.
All right.
For performance tiers, this is how fast you'll be able to do reads and writes.
You have standard and premium.
You have different kinds of access tiers.
So how often do I need to quick access these files?
And then there's replication.
How many redundant copies should be made and where?
And the last thing is deployment models.
So who should deploy the supported service?
Resource Manager Classic.
And in generally most cases, it's going to be Resource Manager.
So here I have all the storage types on the left-hand side, and we have the feature set and how it's going to vary based on a certain type.
So let's just quickly look through this to see where there are some standouts.
And you might want to actually review this at the end of this section just so you're a bit more familiar with all these types of features.
So it clicks a bit better, but let's just quickly go through this.
So you're going to notice for version one, this is the only case where you're going to have a deployment model of classic.
Everything else is
going to be the resource manager.
From A practical standpoint, you're not going to really notice because you're just going to be pressing buttons, but underneath, that's the only case where it varies.
For replication, you're going to notice that version two has the most options with replication, and if these don't make sense, don't worry, we're going to cover all the replication in an upcoming slide.
For BLOB block storage, you can see it's very limited, same with file storage.
So that's there.
When we're talking about access tiers, how quickly you can access files, you're going to notice that it's only available for general version 2 and BLOB storage, where we're choosing these different tiers.
For these ones, it doesn't really matter, because, well, especially with like a file storage, because the drive is as fast as it's going to be, right?
For performance tiers, you're going to notice that with version one and version two, we have standard and premium.
When you're using file storage and block BLOB storage, you're always using premium, and with BLOB storage, which is again a legacy format there, that's going to be using standard.
BLOB storage comes in three different types, and you're going to notice that, based on what you want to use, there'll be some variation there.
I don't know where Page is.
I think that they both support Page, but there are three types in there.
I wouldn't really worry about it too much.
You're going to notice that file storage only supports file types, and then you have version two, and this pretty much supports everything.
So you can see general-purpose version two is a really great storage to choose.
So we were just talking about storage types.
Now let's talk about the actual storage services that we can actually launch or utilize within these storage types under storage accounts.
And there are five core storages available to us.
The first is Azure Blob.
This is a massively scalable object store for text and binary data.
And it also includes big data analytics through Data Lake Storage Gen.
2.
And so Azure Blob is really great because you just don't have to think about the file system.
You just upload files and they're treated like objects.
Well, that's really nice.
Then you have Azure Files, and this is a file share.
And so the great thing about Azure Files is that if you want to have a bunch of virtual machines and have it so like they have...
The same file system sharing all the same files that's what you're going to use that for.
Then you have Azure Queues.
To me, this really is a database, but for whatever reason, it's under storage accounts, and it's a NoSQL store for schema-less storage of structured data.
This is another unusual one I don't know why Azure puts it under here, but...
It's a messaging store for reliable messaging between application components.
To me, that's like an application integration service, but Azure categorizes it as storage.
And the last one is Azure Disk, and this is block-level storage volumes for Azure VMs.
And so the idea is that when you want to do the top four, the above, you're going to be launching storage accounts.
And for disks, you're going to be launching disks.
It's a bit unusual because one of the storage accounts say that you can
use or store disks in, I think, general purpose version two.
I'm not really sure I understand that.
Maybe it's talking about backing them up or something like that.
But anyway, from a practical standpoint, and for what we need to know, is that this is the breakdown here, and we do have a full section on Azure disks.
So we will get into that.
So now let's take a look at some of the features that are available on account storage.
The first being performance tiers.
And generally, this is going to be for BLOB storage.
And we have two types of performance tiers.
We have standard and premium.
So it's as simple as just choosing between the two.
And when we're talking about performance, especially when we're talking about storage, we want to be thinking about IOPS.
And that stands for input output operations per second.
So the higher the IOPS, the faster a drive can read and write.
So you can definitely assume that a premium is going to have
a higher amount of IOPS.
And so when we're looking at the premium performance, these are going to be stored on solid-state drives, SSDs, which we have in the picture there.
It's optimized for low latency, higher throughput.
And the use cases here is going to be interactive workloads, analytics, AI or ML, and data transformation.
On the other side for standard performance, these are running on hard disk drives.
And you're going to have varied performance based on your access tier.
And we're going to talk about access tiers
very shortly, but the tiers would be hot, cool, and archive.
And this is great for backup and disaster recovery, media content, bulk data processing, and things like that.
And so the reason why SSDs are generally really, really good for premium performance is because they have no moving parts within them and the data is distributed randomly.
So if you have to do a read and write, the distance between the read and writes are going to be a lot faster.
And that's generally why you're going to see solid-state drives with premium performance or things with higher IOPS.
And then for hard disk drives, it does have moving parts.
So you see that it has an ARM, and that ARM needs to read and write data sequentially to the disk.
And so it's very good at writing or reading large amounts of data.
That is close together, that is sequential, but the idea is that neither format is good or bad, it's just the use case that you need, so you don't always need to go with SSDs.
Sometimes you want to save money, and HDDs are really good for that, so...
Let's take a look at access tiers.
And there are three types of tiers for standard storage.
We have cool, hot, and archive.
And so you're going to have this option between cool and hot and archive.
Archive might not show up depending on how you configure your storage account.
So for example, if you use a particular type of replication, that might not be available to use with archive.
So just be aware if that option doesn't show up, you might have to change some of your settings.
Let's quickly walk through the three options.
So hot is for data that's accessed frequently and has the highest storage costs.
lowest access cost.
So again, it's for data that's frequently accessed or inactive use, or data that's staged for processing and eventual migration to the cool access tier.
Then you have the cool tier.
This is data that's infrequently accessed and stored for at least 30 days, lower storage costs, higher access cost.
And the use case here is for short-term backup and disaster recovery data sets, or older media content not viewed frequently anymore, but is expected to be available immediately when accessed.
And I think there's actually a third use case, which is large data sets that need to be stored cost effectively while more data is being gathered for future processing.
Then we have the archive tier.
This is for data that's rarely accessed and stored for at least 180 days.
It's the lowest storage cost, but it also has the highest access cost.
And so its use case would be long-term backup, secondary backup, archival data sets, original raw data that must be preserved even after it's been processed into its usable form.
in compliance and archival data that needs to be stored for a long time and is hardly ever accessed.
So just make use or note of the cool is at the least 30 days and the archive is at least 180 days.
I should have highlighted those for you.
I don't know why I didn't.
And so just some other things you need to know.
So for account level tiering, any BLOB that doesn't have an explicitly assigned tier infers the tier from the storage account access tier settings.
So you can set blobs at different storage bubbles.
BLOB level tiering.
You can upload a BLOB to the tier of your choice and change the tiers, happen instantly with exception for moving out of archive.
The concept of rehydrating, this is when you're moving a BLOB out of archive into another tier and it can take several hours.
You have the BLOB lifecycle management, so you can create rule-based policies for transitioning your data to different tiers.
So, after 30 days, we can move it to Cool Storage, and here is just the option here.
You see where it says 30?
I think 30 is the minimum days you have to choose, but I could be wrong, and so you have the options down below.
So, move to Cool Storage, move to Archive Storage, delete the BLOB.
And just a few other things here.
When A BLOB is uploaded or moved to another tier, it's charged at the new tier's rate immediately upon the tier change.
So when you're moving to a cooler tier, the operation is billed as a write operation to the destination tier.
And when the write operation per 10,000 and data write per GB charges for the destination tier applies.
When moving to a hotter tier, the operation is billed as a read from the source tier, and where the read operation, again, in the 10K, and the data retrieval, again, in gigabytes, charges for the source tier applies, and early detection charges for any BLOB moved out of the cool or archive tier may apply as well.
And just lastly here, when we're talking about cool and archive early detection, any BLOB that is moved into the cool tier, so this is only for general purpose version 2 accounts, is subject to
To a cool early detection period of 30 days, and any BLOB that is moved into the archive tier is subject to an archive early detection of 180 days, and this charge is prorated.
So, you know, access tiers aren't the funnest thing to talk about, but there is all the information you need to know.
So let's take a look at replication and data redundancy.
And so when you create a storage account, you're going to have to choose a replication type.
And the reason why is that you're going to want to have multiple copies of your data, so you're protected from a bunch of things.
So maybe your data center has a planned outage, so you have to make sure you have a backup of your data if you need to access it.
Maybe there is a hardware failure or network or power outage or natural disaster.
And so that is the whole point of replication.
And the greater level of redundancy, the more
expensive the cost of replication will be.
And talking about cost, we can break it down into 3 categories.
Each of these categories have two types of replication.
So let's just quickly go through the list and then we'll deep dive into all of them.
in the upcoming slides.
So for the first part, we have primary region redundancy.
So we have local redundant storage, LRS, and zone redundant storage, ZRS.
And locally redundant storage is the most cost-effective tier.
So that's the one I'm usually going for a lot, especially when I'm using development accounts.
That's what I'm always setting.
And so the reason, and so the use for this tier is generally disaster recovery and failovers.
The secondary region redundancy, we have geo-redundant storage, GRS.
and geo-zone redundant storage, GZRS.
And the reason you'd want to use this tier is for also disaster recovery and failovers, but it has a higher level redundancy.
Then the last one here is secondary region redundancy with read access.
And for this case, what we're going to have is read access geo-redundant storage.
So that's RAGRS and read access geo-redundant storage, RAGZRS.
and that's going to generally be for read replicas.
And if you can't remember all the initialisms, don't worry, I don't either.
But, you know, there you go.
So what we're going to do is take a closer look at the replication type, starting with the primary region redundancy.
And so for this tier, all the data is going to be replicated at least three times in the primary region.
And we got two options.
We have LRS and ZRS.
And by the graphic, you can tell that they're slightly different.
And so for LRS, it's using synchronous
replication for those other pieces of data.
So you notice in that region there are three, there's three versions running.
And so when we say synchronous, we mean that if I want to read from any of those copies, they're all going to be 100% up to date.
So that's what synchronous means.
And so here we have a durability of 11 nines.
And this is the absolute most cheapest option when choosing storage accounts.
So if you're running this for developer accounts and you do not care about replication, choose LRS.
For ZRS, we have copies of data synchronously to three different availability zones in the primary region.
And this has a durability of 12, 9, so it's clearly more durable.
And so why would you want to choose the primary region over the LRS?
Well, the idea is that if an availability zone goes out, you still have your data into other regions, where in the case of LRS, if the availability zone goes out, your data is gone, okay?
So that is the first tier.
So now we're taking a look at secondary region redundancy, and the purpose of this is
If you have your primary region suffers a regional disaster, and so all the data centers are out in your primary region, you can rely on that secondary region.
And your secondary region is going to be determined based on your primary's pair region.
So regions are paired with another region, and so you don't get to pick your twin.
It's just, it is what you get.
Okay?
And so secondary regions.
aren't available for read and write access, except in the event of failover.
So basically, the redundant copy in the secondary region is just there on standby, but it's not in use.
And so let's just talk about GRS and GZRS.
And you'll notice again by the graphic, they look a bit slightly different, but you can kind of get the idea based on our previous version, or our previous primary storage tier.
And so
Data is copied synchronously within the main primary region, and then data is asynchronously copied to another region.
So asynchronous means that if you try to read from the second region, all the data might not be there.
Okay?
Again, synchronous means if you read from something, there's a guarantee that it's going to be the same, and asynchronous means that there's not a guarantee that the data is one-to-one to the original.
And the durability here is 16 nines.
Going over to GZRS, we have data is copied asynchronously across 3 availability zones in a physical region.
And then the data is copied asynchronously to another region.
And I believe that the data in the secondary region is not necessarily in three other AZs.
At least that's the graphic I made there.
So hopefully that is true.
But yeah, there you go.
So now we're going to take a look at redundancy in the secondary region with read access, and the whole purpose of this region is so that you can actually have a read replica in another region.
And so the concept of that is having your data in sync, okay?
And so down below we have RAGRS and RAGZRS, and it's going to look very similar to the last setup, but the key difference is that now data is synchronous in both the primary and the secondary region, because if you're going to be reading from it, you want to make sure that your data is one-to-one with your primary region's data.
So there you go.
So we keep on mentioning about Azure Blob Storage.
Let's actually talk about it now.
So Blob Storage is an object store that is optimized for storing massive amounts of unstructured data.
And unstructured data is data that doesn't adhere to a particular data model or definition, such as text or binary data.
And Azure Blobs are composed of the following components.
So I have this graphic here.
So the first thing is your storage account.
And I didn't mention this prior, but when you create a storage account, you actually get a fully qualified domain.
A lot of Azure services are like this, where you get a
fully qualified domain so that you can access it from everywhere.
And this is a really nice feature, but that means that when you're naming your storage account or other Azure services, you have to treat it like a domain name and you have to choose a unique name.
The next thing are containers.
And this is a little bit confusing because when we think of containers, we think of computing.
But Azure Account Storage has the concept of containers for blobs, and it's just what they call folders.
So just be aware of that.
And then you actually have the actual data being stored, and these are the blobs.
So there are three types of BLOB storage.
We have BLOB blocks, and this is what you're going to primarily be using.
And so this is when you store text and binary data.
It's made-up of blocks of data that can be managed individually, and it can store up to 4.7 terabytes of data.
Then you have append blocks.
and these are optimized for append operation.
So imagine that you have logs from a virtual machine and you want to write them to BLOB storage.
This is going to be a lot more efficient if you're using append blobs because they just append to the end of the file.
And the last is page blobs.
And these store random access files up to 8 terabytes in size.
And these are just for storing virtual hard drives, so VHD files.
and serves as disks for Azure Virtual Machines.
So there's the three types.
So let's talk about all the different ways we can get data into Azure.
Of course, there is the portal and the File Explorer, but let's just take a look at...
all the possible options because this is something you need to know.
And the first is azcopy, and this is something we actually do look in greater detail in this course.
And this is easy to use command line tool for Windows and Linux.
Then you have the Azure Storage Data Movement Library.
This is a.NET library that's just using azcopy underneath.
Then you have Azure Data Factory.
This is an ETL service by Azure, so it's a way of moving data into Azure.
that.
Then you have Blob Fuse, which is a virtual file system driver, and it accesses data through a Linux file system.
I believe it's called Fuse because that is the library that's being used or the compatible library in Linux.
Then you have Azure Data Box.
This is a rugged device used to physically transport data to Azure.
And then you have Azure Import Export Service.
This is a service where you ship your physical disks for data transfer onto Azure.
So let's take a look at Azure Files.
And this is a fully managed file share in the cloud.
And the idea behind this is that it's like a centralized server for storage that allows multiple connections.
Or the way I like to think about it, it's like having one big shared drive that everyone can use or work on at the same time.
And when I say everyone, I mean their virtual machines.
So here is a visual representation, but let's just talk quickly about it.
So the idea is that you're going to be using a network protocol in order to facilitate communication.
And so the two most common ones is Server Message Block, which I believe was created by Microsoft, and Network File System, NFS, which is very commonly used on Linux files or Unix-based file systems.
And what you're going to be doing is you'll have to establish a connection with your file shares file system.
And what you'll be doing is making it accessible within a specific directory, so a folder within your drive.
And this is called mounting.
So you notice there it says Z, X, and Y.
So on Windows, you'd actually have the option when you mount it to say, I want to mount it to Z.
And so anytime you access Z on your Windows server, it's actually going to be using Azure Files.
So let's talk about all the use cases for Azure Files.
Normally they have a spiffy graphic here, but because Azure Files has so much utility, all I have room for is a bunch of text, but we do need to learn it all because it is such an important service.
So the first use case is that it can serve as a replacement or supplement for your on-premise file, servers, network attached storage, your NAS devices.
If you're performing a lift and shift, a lift and shift is when you're moving data in the cloud, we'll describe it in a second here.
You can use Azure files for that.
And so we actually have two different kinds of lifts we can do that Azure defines.
We have a classic lift and a hybrid lift.
So in a lift and shift, this means when you move workloads without re-architecting.
So the idea is like you used to use on-premise, you want to use Azure, but you're trying to keep things as similar as you can.
Very commonly, lift and shifts from on-premise to the cloud will just be taking your virtual machines and then just
copying and then bringing them onto the cloud with nothing else, right?
But anyway, in the case here for storage, we have the classic lift.
This is where both the application and its data are moved to Azure.
And then in a hybrid lift, this is where the application data is moved to Azure Files and the application continues to run on premise.
So clearly the classic lift is bring everything over.
Hybrid lift is like leave the application behind.
Another reason you'd want to be using Azure Files is that it's going to simplify your cloud deployment.
So imagine you have shared application settings, so you have multiple virtual machines and workstations, and they all rely on the same configuration files.
You can just go ahead and mount that drive and share that information.
If you're doing diagnostic tests, so let's say you have a bunch of virtual machines and they're logging to those machines.
And you want a developer to go in and quickly debug them?
Maybe there's a reason why you don't want to use a third-party provider because of compliance or security reasons, but the idea is that all these VMs can just log to the file share, and so now you have centralized logs across many machines.
Another use case is that you need to quickly share development tools, so you could put all your tools onto the drive, and so the developer would mount it, and now they can set up a local environment a lot faster.
When we're talking about containerization, we have a few options here.
So if you are using containers, generally by default, containers are stateless, and so you need to persist volume somehow.
And so that's what you're going to do.
You're going to be using Azure files to do that.
And also, another question is, why would you use Azure Files instead of setting up your own file share server?
Because that's definitely an option that you can do, and the reason why is that shared access, so it already has the standard protocols, so you don't have to configure them it's already baked into the service, it's fully managed.
And this is something that I don't think should be underlooked because it's very difficult to scale a file server.
So they will apply patches for it and it will just automatically scale.
Another thing is that it already has a lot of scripting and tooling built in.
So if you want to use the Azure API or PowerShell, you can automate the management and creation of files and things like that.
And it's also extremely, extremely resilient.
So you can be sure that it's going to stay remain running.
So there's a lot of use cases there, but definitely worth it.
Our time, so there you go.
All right, so now let's talk about all the different kinds of features with Azure Files, starting with backups.
So, with backups, you can backup your file share.
With shared snapshots, and these are read-only, and they're done incrementally.
And the great thing about incremental backups is that it's only storing the data that is changed.
So let's say you have a drive or a file share and it's 100 gigabytes and you only add 1 MB.
Well, that snapshot is only going to add an additional 1 MB.
You're not going to have two snapshots that are 100.
Gigabytes.
All right, you can have up to 200 snapshots per file share.
You can retain backups for up to 10 years, and backups are stored within your file share.
So, if you end up deleting your file share, you'll end up deleting your backups.
And so, because of this, that's why we have soft delete.
And so, soft delete lets you prevent accidental deletion by turning on.
Turning on this feature, and your storage will be marked for deletion and retained for a period of time before the final delete occurs.
So, really, it's just like you want to delete.
Okay, great, we're going to give you a wait period, and then, if you're absolutely sure, it'll be deleted.
Then we have advanced threat protection.
So that's ATP.
This is an additional layer of security intelligence that provides alerts when it detects anomalous activity on your storage account.
I'm pretty sure in my AZ9000, I cover this a little bit more in detail there, but not so important at this level of certification.
Then you have your store tiers.
So there's premium.
So this is stored on SSD with single digit milliseconds for the most IO operations, as we learned earlier.
The higher the IOPS, the faster this is, and SSD is always great for that.
Then we have transaction optimized.
So this stores on HDD with transaction heavy workloads that don't need the latency offered by premium file shares.
Historically, this has been called standard.
Why they call it transaction optimized?
I don't know.
Maybe it just helps people understand the better usage for it.
Then you have hot.
This is optimized for general purpose file sharing scenarios, such as team shares and Azure File Sync.
So that one might be one you're using quite frequently.
Then you have cool.
So this is stored on HDD for cost-effective storage optimized for online archiving storage scenario.
And there's still more to go.
So we have different types of storage here that you can use with Azure Files.
And we saw this earlier in our comparison, but we'll go over it again.
So we have general purpose version 2, and these are deployed on HDD.
Then you have file storage, and this is deployed on SSD.
Then we have
identity. So identity is how you're going to authorize or access Azure files. So for on-premise, this can be joined with your Azure Active Directory Domain service. If you're using managed, this is where you're going to be using the Microsoft managed version of Azure Active Directory Domain service. Then you have store account key. So this is a username and password that can be used to be mounted. I kind of feel like we cover this more in later detail here.
But I guess we'll find out. And then so on to networking. So Azure files are accessible inside and outside your AWS account from anywhere via storage account public endpoint because we saw that storage accounts, it's not Azure files, it's storage accounts, has that fully qualified domain. And again, a lot of Azure service has that. And I really like that feature about Azure. For SMB, the port you're going to be connecting to is 445.
And your organization may need to unblock this port so you can mount your file share. For encryption, Azure files are encrypted at rest using Azure Storage Service Encryption, so that's SSC. And for Azure files, for encrypted in transit, it's going to be using the SMB 3.0 with encryption or it'll use HTTPS. Okay, so there you go.
All right, so we heard of Azure Files, but there's also another service called Azure File Sync. And so the idea behind this service is that it allows you to cache Azure file shares on an on-premise Windows Server or cloud virtual machine. And so here is the visual graphic here where you can see on-prem, Azure VMs, and your Azure backups. And so the idea here is that you can use any protocol that's available on the Windows Server to access your data locally, including SMB, NFS, and even FTP.
And you can have as many caches as you need across the world. So, I mean, this is kind of like having a OneDrive, right, for your file share, because it's keeping, or like any kind of cloud storage, it's just keeping your files in sync. And the nice part is like you can have files in the cloud and they're referenced on your computer, but you only need to access them when you need them, so you don't have to have all these files locally. Okay?
Let's talk about Azure Storage Explorer. So this is a standalone app that makes it easy to work with Azure Storage data on Windows, Mac OS, and Linux, and you can create a variety of things. So I just want to show you, and here I am running on a Mac, but on the left-hand side you can see I have my subscriptions, my storage accounts, my disks.
And we have some options where we can upload files, download files, open stuff, clone stuff, create some things. And so this is just an easy and convenient way to access your file or your account storage and work with them.
Let's take a closer look at azcopy, and this is a command line utility that you can use to copy BLOB or files to or from a storage account. So the first thing you're going to need is the executable file, and there you can see they have it for Windows, Linux, and Mac. And then once you download that file, what you're going to have to do is also make sure that you have the right level of authorization for the user account they're using with it. So you might need to, for download, you'll need Storage BLOB Data Reader. For upload, Storage BLOB
Data contributor and storage BLOB data owner, so just be aware that you need to have those roles available to you to your user account. I think that I have access to everything, so I don't think I even set this it just works, but if you're in a larger company and you have more permissive, least permissive roles, you just need to know about that.
And so you can gain access via either the Azure Active Directory or a shared access signature. So let's just take a look at that right now. So the idea here is that we'll type in az copy login, and this is going to ask us whether we want to sign into the web browser. So that should be Azure Active Directory option one. And so what you'll do is you'll enter your username and password, and you'll then have to enter the code displayed there. And so now you're ready to use the CLS.
And so all you have to do is type in az copy, copy, and then you have the file, and then you give it the endpoint to the storage account and the container and the location you want it to go in. If you want to download files, it's the same command. You just reverse the order. You say, this is the location of the file. I want to download it locally. All right.
So let's take a look at Azure Import Export Service. And this is used for moving large amounts of data to Azure Blob Storage and Azure Files by shipping disk drives directly to the Azure data center. And you got two options here. You can use your own disk drives, or you can use the Microsoft provided drives. And so that's what their drive looks like. And they'll send up five of those to you. They're solid state drives, and they call them the Azure Data Box Disks.
And you can ship up to 40 terabytes per order to your data center through regional carriers. So if you need beyond 40, you've got to make multiple orders. And you can quickly configure these Azure Data Box disk drives, copy the data to the disk drives using a USB 3.0 connection, and then ship it right back on to Azure. And so in order to prepare these drives, you're going to have to use the command line tool called WA Import Export Tool.
And so what this tool will do is it will help you prepare your disk drives that are going to be shipped for import. It's going to copy your data to the drive. It's going to encrypt the data on the drive using AE-256 BitLocker. BitLocker is a software that is applying the encryption. And then it's going to generate out a journal file that you're going to be using to import the stuff for your order. Then it's going to help identify numbers of drives needed for export jobs.
So there are two versions of WA Import/Export. You have version one, and this is for Azure Blob Storage, and then version two, so this is for Azure File. So neither version's good or bad, it's just what do you want to import it into. And WA Import/Export Tool is only compatible with Windows 64-bit. So if you're using Linux or Mac, you're out of luck.
So, once you have prepared your drives and you've generated out that journal file, you're ready to create your import job. So, the journal file stores basic information, such as the drive serial number, the encryption key, and the storage account details. So, the idea is that you're going to upload that file there, then you're going to specify a region and storage account, and so you'll provide shipping address information, and then...
So that is the import job, and let's talk about for exporting. So for exporting, you will only export from Azure Blob. I don't believe you can do it for Azure Files. You can ship up to 10 empty drives to Azure per job, and you will create an export job, and the data is loaded onto those drives and shipped back to you. Okay, so there you go.
Let's take a look at shared access signatures. This was something we saw when we were looking at a copy, as it was an option besides Active Directory to authorize, and so this is something that...
is a multi-step process, so I gave it extra attention here. So shared access signature, also known as SAS, is a URI that grants restricted access rights to Azure resources and the share. And so the URI is going to grant clients temporary access to a specific set of permissions. So the types of shared access signatures we have here is account level SAS.
And this is when you want to access resources in one or more storage services. You have service level. This is when you want to access a single storage account by using storage account keys. Then you have user delegated. And this is when you want to access storage accounts using Azure AD credentials. And this one here is only limited to Blob and containers. So if you need to use something else, you'll have to do something there. And Microsoft considers this method to be the best practice for accessing via SAS. OK.
So a shared access signature comes in two different formats. You have ad hoc, and this is where you have the start time, expiry time, permissions are part of the URI. And any type of SAS can be an ad hoc SAS. And then you have service SAS with stored access policy. That's when you have a stored access policy that's defined on a resource container. This is going to be limited to BLOB, container, table, queue, and file share. So the only one that's not in the mix there looks like it's disks.
And the stored access policy can be associated to multiple SaaS to manage constraints. So let's just take a look at what this URI looks like. Whenever I say URI, I always just think URL. And so down below, we have it there. You can see that we have the BLOB URI. So that's the storage account, the name of the container, the name of the file we want to access. And then down below, we have a bunch of query strings. And so SV stands for storage service version, which is the version of storage service to use.
Then you have the start time. Then you have the expiration time. Then you have the storage resource, whether it's a BLOB or a queue. So B is for BLOB. Q is for queue. I guess it's the same word. That was a bit confusing. Then you have SP, which is permissions. So what operations can be performed against the storage resources, so read or write or both. And then you have the signature. So this is used to authenticate the access via a SHA-256 algorithm.
And so, I mean, if you want to generate one of these shared access signatures, they're actually really easy. All you got to do is open up the portal, and under your storage account, go to shared access signature, choose what you want. So there's all the options, and then you're going to press the button, and it's going to generate that URI for you, and then you just use that URI. So that's all there is to it.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro. And in this follow along, we're going to learn a bit more about storage accounts and how to copy content back and forth using AZ copy. So what I want you to do is go all the way to the top here and we'll type in storage accounts. And then from here, we're going to create ourselves a new storage account. And we'll make a new resource group. I'm going to call this one Fajo. Let's type in Fajo here.
And we can have it in any location that we so desire. We're going to stick with standard here. General Purpose 2 seems okay to me. We'll go ahead and hit Review and Create. And then we'll hit Create there. And I'll see you back here in a moment.
All right, so now that our storage account is ready here, we'll go in here and we'll create ourselves a container. So I'm going to call this one Kivas Fagio. We're going to leave it as private because we technically don't want anyone to have public access to it. And so there is a tool that you should definitely know how to use called AZ Copy. So if I just type that in there quickly here and we go and scroll down, here are some versions we can download. So if you're on Mac, Linux, Windows, or et cetera, we can use it. I want to try to give you
A consistent experience on how you can utilize it, so I'm going to just try and stumble my way through and use it via the Cloud Shell, because I think that would probably be the most consistent way for all of us to use it. So, make sure you are in Bash, and we're going to need two things: we're going to need this azcopy.tar file, and we're also going to need some kind of file to upload. Okay, so...
The question is, how are we going to get things into our Cloud Shell? Well, the great thing about Cloud Shell is when you launch it, asks you to create a storage account, and we should probably be able to place those files into there. So if we go back to storage accounts at the top here, and we go here, this is a storage account. So if we go in here, if there were containers, we go back, but I believe what they do is they set you actually up a file share here, right? And so in here, this is what it's doing. So what I'm going to do is upload
two files, so I'll just go here. And one is going to be this, which is the Kivas Faggio, which is just an image. Okay. And what we can do is I will download this Linux here. And once that is downloaded, what I'm going to do is also upload that, okay? So I just drag that onto my desktop. It's a bit easier to access. And I might just rename it so it's a bit easier to work with.
So I'm just going to rename the targe GZ to a copy here, if you can see. And we'll go back here and we'll just go ahead and upload that, okay? So we'll upload that as well. And it's only 11 megabytes, so it shouldn't take too long here. But what we need to do is find out where these files are. So what we'll do is make our way back to our shell. I'm going to type in LS. And I think it might be mounted here, so we'll do LS. And there's our file. So
What we'll have to do is untar the AZ copy so we get the binary. So I have a handy dandy command over here from... I just found one over here because I can never remember this command, the tar command. So we'll type in tar-xvzf and then the name of the tar. So I'm going to start typing AZ and I'm going to hit tab to autocomplete and that should untar it.
And so now we have our... Oh, we made it into a folder, so I'm going to go into that folder there. And so now we have our az copy here, okay? So just to make our lives a bit easier, I'm going to want to move that az copy back one directory. So I'm going to type in mv for move. I'm going to type in az copy, and I'm going to do period, period, backslash. So it says, or forward slash, it'll go back a directory. We cd and do an ls.
Just do clean again, we'll do LS, we can now see that it's a bit easier to work with. I'm going to delete the that long folder there because we don't need it. When it's a folder, you got to do a recursive. So hyphen R. And we'll also go ahead and delete the az copy dot tar file. Okay, and we'll do clear.
And then we'll do an LS hyphen LA. That'll list everything because what I'm trying to see is whether this file is executable. It appears that we can execute it. If we can't, it usually could happen to do chmod u plus x az copy here. And then if we run this again, yeah, it looks the same. So I think we'll be in okay shape here. But yeah, now we're all set up to go ahead and use the az copy command. So let's give it a go.
All right, so there's two ways we can get or authenticate with AZ copy. And if you remember from my handy dandy AZ copy slide, we have two options, which is we can use this login or use a shared access signature. We're going to give both a try, but we'll start out with AZ login. Okay, so we'll do type in AZ copy login. And what that will do is it will prompt us and ask us to sign into the browser and enter this code. So I'm just going to grab this link here and we will copy it.
I'll make a new tab, paste it in. And once here, we'll go ahead and enter in this code, okay? And we'll just say, yep, Andrew Brown. And so now that is now synced. So now we should be able to use the az copy command. In order to use this, again, we pull up my reference here. We have az copy, copy, the name of the file, and then the name of the path we want it to go to, okay?
So what we'll have to do is in our container here, it's called Kivas Vagio. So I'll have to remember that. But if we go here, we're looking for that publicly accessible URL or that fully qualified domain URL. I would have swore it was here. Oh, sorry, we're in the wrong storage account. By the way, we have to go into our actual Vagio one here just in case.
Just making sure we're in the right place. But let me just go find that URL. I can't remember if we have to assemble it by hand or if they just have it handy here. So just give me a moment. All right, I'm back. And I had to pull up the docs for this one, which is not a big deal. But the structure here is we're going to have HTTPS, the account, blob.core, windows.net, the name of the container, and the path to the BLOB. Okay. So that's what we're going to do here. So let's give it a go and see if we can get it to work the first time around here. So we are typing, well, before we do that, I'm going to type clear.
and then do ls. So we're going to type in az copy. And the command is cp. Or actually you can type in copy if you want. It looks like cp is abbreviation. And so the path to the file. And so in our case, it's going to just be local. So I just typed in K and I tabbed. And the next thing we have to type is https colon forward slash forward slash the name of the account. So it's Fajo. And then blob.core.windows.
dot net forward slash, and then we named the container here Kivas Fajo. And then we'll type a forward slash. And then we can name the file however we want. So I'm going to name it the same as the JPEG. Okay. And so hopefully this just works. And I mean, it looks like it worked pending. Says the file transfer might have failed here. Hold on.
So it says we're not performed to other, we don't have access to perform that there. So just give me a moment, okay? All right, so I figured it out. There was one key thing we forgot to do. So the reason we were getting a 403 was, as plain as it was, is we didn't have access to do it. So if we just go back to our storage account there, and this is within the container, so I'm just going to go all the way back to storage accounts.
We'll go into Fagio here. And so on the left-hand side, you see it says access controls, right? So if we were to go into here and we go to role assignments, we can see what role that people have. But in order to access BLOB storage, you need to, like to be able to upload and download, you either have to be the storage BLOB data owner or the storage BLOB data contributor. So if you want to do that, you just have to go up to add and do a role assignment and assign yourself this role.
It does take about five minutes to take effect. So even after doing at doing this, adding it to my user here, I wasn't able to do it right away. But after waiting a little bit here, I was able to go and do a test like with list. And it didn't print anything. But that means that there is no error, right? So we probably do have access. Another little thing I found out, which was nice is that if you go, let's say into a container here,
And then you just clear that out, we'll click into that container. And on properties here, it actually gives us the URL. So it makes our lives a little bit easier. So we don't have to type that whole thing out and try to figure it out. But let's go back and try to actually do a copy now. So that's what we've been trying to do this entire time. So what I'm going to do is type in az copy. And then we want Kivas Fagio. And then I'm going to paste in the URL that I just got from there. And I'm
I'm just going to put a forward slash here, I'm going to type in Kivas Fajo dot jpg. Oh, you know what, we got to put the word copy or CP in front of it. And it looks like it completed. That looks good to me. And so if we make our way back here to
To our container, we can see that it's uploaded, so there we go.
We were able to upload it with Active Directory, so now let's go give it a try with a SAS.
Okay, all right, so let's give this another go here, and this time what we're going to do is use an SAS, so it's as simple as attaching it to the end of the URL for the destination or the source, depending on what we want to do.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and delete this file here, just because we already have it.
And what I'm going to do is go back to my storage account.
And what we need is a SAS here.
So I'll type it in here.
I wonder if we can type it.
Oh, yeah, we can here.
That's great.
So type it here at the shared signature access.
And we'll say, what do we need access to?
Well, we're only using Blob storage.
So we get rid of file queue and table.
Allowed resource types will be for container because that's what we're doing.
And we aren't deleting, we don't necessarily need the list, but we can have that there.
Read, write, add, create, that seems okay to me.
Enable deletion of versions.
Sure, I mean, we don't have to turn that off.
But we'll just leave it in place.
I think we will do HTTP or HTTPS, just have some flexibility here.
And this looks okay, we have a few different keys, we're gonna stick with key one.
And so I'm going to go ahead and generate out an SAS connection string.
And so this is the token we want.
See how it has a question mark?
It's going to allow us to put that on the end of our URL.
So what I will do is I will, I don't know if we can write az copy log out.
Let's see if we can do that.
Oh, we can.
Great.
So just making sure that it's not authenticating that way.
And so what I'll do is I'll go back up to this link here, and this should fail, right?
Because we don't have access, right?
And so what we should be able to do is just take this string and place this on the end as such, and hopefully it just works.
And it says done, done, done.
So if we go back to our storage here to see if that is working as expected, we go into that container.
Let's just move this down below here.
It gets a bit hard to see when you have that open like that.
Oh, we're in storage account right now.
Okay, so we're going to type in container, go here, click into give us vajo.
And we don't see the file.
So let me give it let me give a try here.
Okay.
All right, let's give it another go here.
You know, I just don't necessarily trust URL.
Actually, it says fail to perform copy, no SAS token or OAuth provided.
which is fine.
But in this case, we did and we saw done, done, done.
And so here are the values it's printing out.
So maybe what we should do is just regenerate this out and be a little bit more permissive.
And maybe that will give us an easier time because we want read.
This is slightly different for the container.
Not sure why this looks different all of a sudden, but what we'll do is we'll go back here.
We'll just go close a bit.
We'll go back into Fagio.
I'm going to go look for the container again.
And what we'll do is click into the container.
And then from here, we'll do shared access properties.
We'll do account key, which is fine.
So key one, I want, I'm just going to put everything on here to make our lives a bit easier.
The start date is fine, the end date is fine.
We'll allow HTTP or HTTPS.
And we'll generate that token.
So here we have it again.
what we'll do is we'll just grab this whole thing here.
Actually, we probably Yeah, we'll just grab the token.
And then what we'll do is make our way back to here, I'm going to hit up.
And what I'm going to try to do is remove the end here, give us another go.
Okay.
So paste that in.
I don't see the question mark on that, so this is not an easy one, okay?
We'll put question mark here, hit enter.
It just says stopped, done, done, done, done.
So it makes you think that it's working.
Clearly it's not.
But let's just double check the container to see what's there, okay?
No file still.
Well, what if we grab this one here?
Maybe it's an encoding issue, or maybe it doesn't like the way we did the link.
Hit enter.
Still says stopped.
I don't know.
All right, I'm back.
So, you know what?
I thought I was doing everything right, and so just as a sanity check, what I did was I opened up my command prompt.
And I installed just a different version of azcopy.
It's the Windows version.
And using the exact same command, it worked.
So I just want you to know, this is kind of something that I run into a lot with Azure, whereas if you try it one way, it doesn't work, but some other place, it works no problem.
Just because Azure tries to support all use cases, sometimes you'll be spending a lot of times second-guessing yourself.
But definitely the command I showed you was correct.
But, it could be that the AZ copy version's out of date.
So remember when we wrote an AZ copy here for Linux, it was suggesting to get a newer version, but I had downloaded the latest version.
So, you know, it could be that.
It's really hard to say, but I want you to know, like, that's just how you do an AZ copy.
And, you know, don't get frustrated if you get stuck on stuff like this, okay?
So we're all done here, and let's go ahead and tear down our stuff.
And we'll just go to Fagio here, that's the one we set up there, and we'll go ahead and delete that resource group, and we're all done here, okay?
Hey, this is Angie Brown from Exam Pro, and in this follow-along, I'm going to show you how to set up a file share.
and mount it to a virtual machine.
So let's get to it.
So the first thing we're going to do is go all the way to the top and we're going to type in storage accounts, because if you type in files or Azure files, you're just not going to get anything because it is a sub-service within a storage account.
So we'll go ahead and hit add.
And I think I will name, I'll make a new resource group as I always do.
I'm going to name this one as KeyVoss.
Okay, and then we'll name the account as such.
Now I want to show you something here.
So under the account kind, if you remember from our lecture content, you can create a file share under general purpose 2.
But if you go to premium 2, you'll have just a file storage type.
That means only this storage account is only for creating a file storage.
And that's if you want to use the premium tier for access.
And we don't today.
But I will show you when we get to that in a moment here, just to point that out to you.
So what we'll do is go ahead and hit Review Create.
Actually, before we do that, let's just double check if there's anything interesting here.
Sometimes there is.
So under Azure Files for large file shares.
provides file share support up to 100 terabytes.
So right now it's disabled, but if you wanted larger files, you could go ahead and enable that, but we're just going to leave it off.
I'm going to go ahead and hit review and create.
Now, as this is creating, and this goes pretty darn quick, what I'm going to do is launch a new virtual machine because we need something to mount the file share to.
So make your way over to virtual machines.
And what we're going to do is launch a Linux one just because that's a lot easier for me to do here.
And they're generally more inexpensive.
So we'll choose Kivas.
I'm also going to name the virtual machine Kivas, and we'll choose Ubuntu as our image.
So just go down here, make sure you choose 18 LTS, generation 2.
And under the sizes, we'll expand it.
Make sure you choose B1LS, because that costs around $6 a month.
Under your password, we will choose Azure User as the name.
And then for the password itself, testing123, capital on that T, so capital T, testing123456.
Sorry.
It's always 123456.
We should probably open up port 445, but we'll get to that when we get to the, actually we have to recreate it here.
So I'll hit review and create.
And we will go ahead and just give it a moment.
Just takes a little bit of time and we'll just go and create that there.
So, as that is creating, we'll go back to our storage account, we'll go into it, and as you notice, these are the services, the things that we can launch in our storage account.
What we want is a file share that's Azure Files.
But notice here that the capacity is set to 5 terabytes and it has a soft delete for seven days.
It's not configured with Azure Active Directory as of yet if we wanted to use that to authenticate.
But what we'll do is click on file share on the right-hand side.
I'm going to name our file share as Kivas.
I'm going to set the total to 3 gigabytes because we don't need a lot of data.
And remember that tier I talked about?
Well, here it is, it's disabled, but if we had created it a premium storage account and a file storage, we could have chosen that all right.
So we'll go ahead and hit
hit create, and this doesn't take too long.
As that's going, let's make our way back to our virtual machine.
It looks like it's deployed, so we'll go to that resource, and then on the left-hand side, we'll go to networking, because I want to open up that port 445.
That's what SMB communicates on.
And so down below, all this is fine, but if we were to go here, there isn't one for SMB, so what we'll do is just put in 445, and we'll say TCP, and I'll just write down here SMB, and we'll go ahead
and hit add.
And that only takes a moment there, we'll make our way back to our storage account, we'll click or sorry, into our files, yeah, search account in our files.
Notice we have connect and upload.
And so what we're going to do is click Connect.
And it's going to give us some instructions here that we can run.
And this is going to be the mount point.
So I'm going to go make my way back to here.
And I see that that record has been created.
And I'm going to open up our cloud shell.
And so if you've never opened up Cloud Shell before, it'll ask you to make it a storage account that is specific just for it.
So say yes, make sure you're in bash mode.
We cannot do this in PowerShell.
And within your virtual machine, if you're on the right tab here, you'll go to overview, and we're going to grab that public IP address, type SSH, Azure user at sign, paste in the IP address.
We'll hit enter.
Type in yes to accept the fingerprint, and then type your password, capital T, testing 123456.
Okay.
and it'll let us in.
And what we're going to need to do is do a sudo apt update, and I'm going to do ampersand ampersand just so we can run this in one line.
We're going to type in sudo apt install cifs utils.
This is the utility that we're going to use to do this part of the mounting, so we need to make sure that is installed.
And so we'll let that go.
Apt update can take a lot of time or a very little amount of time.
It just depends on how many updates there are, but it shouldn't take too long.
And so what we're going to do is prepare this because this is not the easiest to work with.
And so what we'll do, I already have it open here because I was giving this a go earlier.
This is the exact same thing, but I'm going to delete it out.
So it's one-to-one because I think it might have changed a little bit here.
Whoops.
And so I will copy this here and paste it in.
And we'll just give it a quick read.
So what it's going to do, I don't know if it would color this if I went to bash here.
Shell script.
There we go.
It's a bit easier.
So it's going to create a directory called Mount Kivas.
And then it's going to create another directory for the SMB credentials.
It's going to store the username and then the password in these credentials.
We're going to chamod it so we have our permissions.
And then we have this bash script here, which is a little bit hard to read, but
It is using CIFS, so it's doing some something there and setting that stuff up.
And then it's using CIFS.
It's actually mounting in this case.
So that's what we're going to do.
So just going back over here and back to this other tab.
What I'm going to do here is, oh, sorry, now this is ready.
We're going to just type in clear.
And I'm going to run each of these commands.
So I'm going to grab the make directory here and I'm going to paste that in.
If you paste all this in, half the time it messes up when you have multi-line like that, so it's not even worth trying.
So we'll do copy, we'll make that other directory here.
And then we have this pseudo bash line here, so we'll copy that.
Okay, hit enter, and then we'll grab this next line here.
We'll copy that, paste that in, hit enter.
It did not like the space in front of it, I think.
It's just a really long line, so what I'll do is I'll just grab that line, move it to the wall, make my life a little bit easier, and we'll paste that in like that.
It's saying the credentials does not exist.
Hold on here.
So we'll just write clear.
It's okay if it happens.
So this directory should exist, right?
So if I do pwd.
etc.
Or we should just be able to autocomplete it.
So it's a CD, etc.
I'm hitting tab to autocomplete, and then we want SMB.
And this says credential.
So it's missing the S.
So there's my mistake.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and remove that, because if we don't have it named right, it's just not going to work, right?
So we'll go ahead here and make sure we copy the entire line.
That was my mistake.
And we'll paste that in there.
We'll go to the next line.
Copy that, paste that in.
Copy the next line here, paste that in.
And what we'll do is we'll chmod the file.
Okay, so if we want to check to make sure it's the correct permissions, what we can do is do an LS, paste in the, or just write in the path, which is SMB credentials here.
And here we can see the file.
If we do a hyphen LA, it will show us that it has the correct permissions.
So it's really locked down there.
That's what the Chabad did.
If we want to see the contents of that file to make sure that those things are in there, what we can do is type in cat and just grab that whole link here.
We might have to give it sudo.
We might complain for that.
It does.
So we'll put sudo in front of that.
And so we just want to make sure there's one username and one password and everything looks okay there.
We'll type clear.
We'll make our way back here.
And so now we'll run these commands.
So that's the first one.
And then this is the second one.
We'll make sure that that end matches up.
I-N-O, yep, I-N-O, hit enter.
And so now it should work.
So if we were to upload a file, that should be in good shape.
But if we want to get to that directory, we'll just type in mount.
And if we keep on hitting tab, it'll show us there's Kivas.
Okay, and so this is where we're going to create some files.
So I actually don't have a file prepared, so give me a moment.
I'll be back in a moment with a file.
All right, I'm back and I've prepared an image for us to upload.
So going back to our file share in here, we have the upload button.
Just go ahead and click that.
And on the right-hand side, it's going to give you a pop-up.
And within that pop-up there, just go find your image.
I'm just off screen grabbing it.
So this
is my image, what I'm uploading, which is Kivas Faggio.
It's who we named it after.
He's the collector in Star Trek Next Generation.
And so what I'll do is go ahead and hit upload, right?
And so that file is supposedly there.
If we go back here and do LS, there's the file, right?
And so probably it should be reflective.
So if we were to go and delete this file,
So we'd say remove, or maybe if we made a new director, let's see what happens if we say, the episode's called the most toys in Star Trek.
Just see if it actually reflects back and forth.
So we do a refresh.
There it is.
Can I drag?
No, I can't drag, but I could probably move this file over there.
So we'll say move Kivas Faggio into the most toys episode.
And if we go back here and refresh,
You get the idea, right?
So yeah, I mean, that's as simple as it is with the file share there.
Okay?
So now that we're all done here with Azure File Share, we can't use this to make a file sync because we would have to use Windows for that.
So this is all pretty much done.
So what I want you to do is go to your resource groups.
We'll find Kivas and we'll go ahead and delete this.
And we'll call this part of our follow along 100% done here.
Okay?
So see you in the next one.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are going to take a look at using Azure File Sync.
So previously we set up a file share with just Linux, but we're going to take it a bit further and set up a sync.
So what we're going to do is we're going to do 2 things.
We're going to need to set up a new storage account, and we'll also have to launch a virtual machine.
Since virtual machines take longer to launch than a storage account, what I want you to do, I saw the old tab here from the last file along, but what I want you to do is make your way over to virtual machines.
open that a new tab and we'll go ahead and launch ourself a Windows Server.
So up in the top left corner, hit add virtual machine.
We'll give it a moment.
I'm going to call this new one.
Well, we can use Kivas again, so I'm going to go ahead and do that.
We'll say this is Kivas and I'm going to choose this time Windows 2019 Server.
So we have a Windows Server and I want 2019.
It doesn't necessarily have to be, let me just double check here.
Yeah, we'll just do 2019 generation 2 here.
And we'll scroll on down here.
And I'm going to put in Azure user.
And then we'll do capital T, testing 123456, capital T, testing 123456.
Scroll on down.
We are definitely going to want port 3389 open.
We'll open up these two ports as well.
I think that's okay.
And we'll go ahead, hit review, and create.
actually, before we do that, I don't think I choose the right size.
So we'll just wait a moment here as it's complaining, and we'll change this because you can't have a B1LS.
We're going to have to go with DSV.
DSV3, okay?
Because it has two VCPUs at the minimum.
Actually, we can go with this one here because it just has to be two and four.
So I think we can get away with a V2, which is 50 bucks a month, which we're not going to keep that around for very long.
We'll go ahead and hit create.
We might need, actually before that, I'm just going to add another disk just in case because I really don't want to have to do this if I have to make another one.
And so we're just going to say an empty disk here, I suppose.
Yeah, that seems fine to me.
And I'm going to go ahead and hit, yeah, we should enable disk.
No, we'll do nothing there.
And we'll say OK.
And go ahead and hit review create.
And we'll just give it a moment.
It takes a little bit of time.
Go ahead and hit create there.
And while that's creating, now we'll go over and make ourselves a storage account.
So we'll make a new one here.
And we'll call it, we'll put it in our Kivas, and we'll call it Kivas.
We'll stick with standard general 2, that's totally fine for our use case.
We'll go ahead and hit create, and this will not take long.
It's very fast at making storage accounts.
Windows virtual machines, not as fast.
So we'll just give it a moment here.
And it looks like it's created, so we'll go to the resource, and then under file shares, we'll click on that. We'll create a new file share, and this will be called Kivas. And we'll set 5 gigabytes, because we really don't need a large one. We'll create it. And so this can be used for Windows or Linux. In this case, we're going to be using it for Windows. So what we can do,
We'll just have to wait for that to finish deploy. But we're going to have to set up Azure files. So if we go files, I think we type it in here, will it show up? No. So the thing is we need to get file sync and it's in a kind of a weird spot. So if we go to all services and then we type in files, whoops, it was a little bit too quick there. I'm just looking for it here. What if we type in sync?
There we go. So what I'm looking for is storage sync services. Can we type it up here sync? Yeah, so that would have been the way I would have gone gone gone and found it there. But we need to find Azure files. I'm just trying to remember how to get to there. So I could have swore we could type in file sync. Yeah, here it is. Azure file sync.
And so this is how we get to it. I know it's quite a, let me just double check to make sure if that's somewhat, if we can actually type that up here, file sync. No. Okay. So what we would want to do is go ahead and create this. If we want to take a look, we can check the plans. This seems okay. So we'll go ahead and hit create. And under here, we're going to put it into Kivos. And then for the provider name, it will be the storage sync service name will just be Kivos as well.
And I guess we'll stick with central US. I guess it just really depends on where our virtual machine storage account is. I hope everything's launching in the same place. I don't think it matters, but I'm just going to double check here. So this one is in Canada East, and then our storage account, let's just go take a look where it is. It is in Canada East. So maybe we could launch this in Canada East. It doesn't give us any grief. It doesn't, so that's great. We'll go ahead and hit create.
And we'll give that a little bit of time there. And if our instance is ready, we should go ahead and connect to it because there's going to be a couple things we need to install, okay? So I'm going to go over to RDP here and we're going to download the RTP file. And that's going to open up that. So we'll just double click it. We'll say connect. If you're on a Mac, you've got to download the client. If you're on Windows, it's already, it should be pre-installed. If you're on a Chromebook, you'll have to use a Bastion. But I'm going to type in Azure user.
and that password capital T, testing123456, we'll hit OK. I'll say yes, I'll connect. And we'll just give it a moment there to load. We are going to need two things we need to install, but just give me a moment here, I'll go fetch them. All right, so now that we have our Windows machine, we're inside of it here, what I want you to do is open up
PowerShell. So if you type in PowerShell, we do need to run this in administrator mode. So just type it in. It's a little bit slow when you're RDPing, which is totally fine. And what I want you to do is right click and run as an administrator. And what we're going to do is install Azure RM because we need it in order to use the Azure File Sync Agent. Okay. So type in install hyphen module and then type in name.
Azure RM. And then we'll say allow clobber. Don't ask me what clobber does. I have no idea. But that's what Microsoft or Azure tells us that we should whoops, did I spell it right? No, it's all correct. Okay, that we should do. This thing is pretty darn slow. So we'll just have to wait here a little while. And once that's done, we'll continue on to the next part. Okay. so after waiting a little bit, it asks us a question. So we're just gonna hit Y to everything.
All right, and as that's going here, it can take a little bit of time. So what I'm going to do, if I can even minimize this here, I did not mean to minimize Azure or this here. Oh, the other one already prompted. That was pretty fast, actually. It's going really fast as of today. But as that's going, what we'll do is we'll make our way back over.
to sync storage here or storage sync. We were waiting for this to get set up because we're going to have to go set up a sync group. So I'm going to just call this Kivos, make everything easy. We'll stick with that Azure subscription. We'll drop this down and we'll choose Kivos in here. And then for the Azure file share, we'll choose Kivos. And once that's created, we'll click into that. And what we are trying to do is we're adding a cloud endpoint here.
So we would choose our storage account, and we would choose this here and hit create. Okay, and so now we have a cloud endpoint, but we still have to continue on with our virtual machine here. So just wait until this is done. This will take a little bit of time, okay?
All right, so now that we have that installed, the PowerShell for Resource Manager, what we're going to need installed is the Azure File Sync Agent. In order to do that, we're going to have to go to the Internet. But before we do that, we really want to turn off a particular feature. So turn back on protected mode. I was fiddling with it earlier, but if we were to go, and it doesn't matter where we go, we say Azure File Sync Agent. Okay.
And if we were to go, see, we start getting this pop up and it drives us crazy. So what we can do, because this isn't a big deal, it's just for testing here, we're going to turn that off. So go to your local server where it says IE enhanced security configuration, click on that and just turn it off, you know, because it'll drive you crazy. And then we'll go back to Internet Explorer, completely close it, reopen it. And now what we can do is look for that Azure file sync. So we'll type in Azure file sync agent download.
And this is azuremicrosoft.com, maybe later for that experience. It's easier if you go to the Microsoft site. And if you go here, just give it a moment, scroll on down, click on the download button. And we want 2019 because that's the server we launched, right? And we're trying to sync with storage sync. So we'll go ahead and hit next. This is 50 megabytes, so it shouldn't take too long. And we're going to wait for it to download. If it doesn't,
We'll say allow once for the site here. So maybe it was trying to download. Yeah, there it goes. And we will save it. And we will always allow for Microsoft here. It's totally fine. And it's already finished downloading. So we'll go ahead and run that. And just give it a moment here. We'll hit next. We'll accept the terms. We'll install it there. That's totally fine.
We'll use the existing proxy configuration. Custom configure proxy. Well, we don't have any custom, so we'll leave it alone. We'll leave Microsoft updates on. It'd probably be good to checkbox that on, but I'm just going to go install next here. All right, and so we'll let the agent install. Usually doesn't take too long. Anyway, I'll see you back here in a moment.
All right, so now that we have our search agent set up, we'll just hit finish here. And I don't know why it opened up a bunch of windows, but that's just what it does. And so we're just going to wait for it to pop back up here. And then we'll say OK. And then what it'll want to do is connect. So it says Azure Environment. So it is Azure Cloud, right? And I'm just going to sign into my account. And I'm going to try and log in here. So let me just go grab my credentials.
All right, so I entered my credentials in here, so we'll go ahead and hit sign in, and we'll give it a moment there. We're going to choose our subscription. We'll choose our resource group, which is Kivas, and our storage sync there. Hit register. And I'll see you back here in a moment. All right, so it looks like our registration was successful, so that means that we should be able to create a server endpoint and go from there. Okay, so I'm going to just go ahead and hit close.
and I'll come back here to you in a moment. All right, so now what we're going to do is set up a folder that we're going to want to be synced, okay, because the idea is to back up or sync that directory there. So what's going to happen here is we're going to make our way down to File Explorer and from this PC, I'm just going to go to the C drive. I made that other drive because I assumed we were just going to throw it on there, but honestly, I'm just going to put it in the window or the C drive here. We'll make a new folder called Kivas. We'll make it all lowercase. And inside of here, I'm
I'm just going to make a new file here called hello.txt. Nothing super exciting. And so probably we need to turn on sharing. So that's just a habit of mine. So we'll go to properties here, sharing, share, and we'll just make sure that Azure user has both that. And it'll ask us to turn network discovery on. We'll say okay, Kivas, Kivas, okay. I can't remember if we have to turn that on or not, but
as long as we have this working, that's the most important part here. So now that we have that going, what we want to do is make our way back to Azure here. And so we had our, what was the sync? Sync storages. And what we'll need to do is go into our sync storage once it ever lets us get there. We'll click on Kivas. And we'll go into sync groups. We'll click into our Kivas sync group.
We have a cloud endpoint, but we'll need to create an add server endpoint. Drop down here, we have a registered server. So you know how we typed in our, we typed in, we logged in to the Azure File Sync Agent. That's how this registered server is showing up. We're going to give it a path. So this is going to be C backslash Kibos, right? So this all looks okay.
And what we'll do is we will say, let's just check this here. This is all okay. And we'll go ahead and hit connect. All right. And so this takes a little bit of time to provision. It's going to show up here in a moment. If I hit refresh, it's provisioning. So I'll see you back here in a bit. You know, I just remembered is that we do actually have to turn on cloud tiering or it's going to stay in pending forever. So I'm going to go to enable here and always preserve specific percentage of free space on the volume.
Sure, we can do 20% here. We don't need a date policy here. And this all looks okay. So we'll go ahead and hit save. Because if we don't do that, it's not going to actually, it's not going to move it to the cloud, right? So we'll give that a go. Oh, the health is good. But we'll just give it a moment here, okay?
So we gave it a little bit of time here. It says the endpoint failed, which I really don't believe it because I just checked and it was working totally fine. But what I want to do is show you if I go over to Microsoft Azure here, and we go over to storage accounts, and we go to Kivas, and we go into file shares, and we click into this one, we can actually see the files here. So it clearly is syncing. I'm not sure why we got that error. I've never seen that error before.
Cloud journey is not supported for the specified path. Well, that's fine. Okay, so if the server path didn't work, maybe it's the cloud endpoint, but generally that is the workflow to get syncing working. So you pretty much have all the working knowledge you need. But what we'll do is go ahead and tear all this stuff down because we are 100% done. So I'm going to go to our resource groups here. And what we'll do is go into Kivas.
And we'll just make sure that everything is there, even the storage sync service. I just wanted to make sure it was all there. And what we'll do is go ahead and write in Kivas and go ahead and delete. And that should take everything down, no problem. All right, so there you go.
All right, so just one more thing. I was doing that cleanup and then today I woke up the next morning and when I checked my resource groups, the Kivas was still here. So I went in here and we still had the storage sync service. So what you're going to want to do is go in here and I think what it wants you to do, actually tell us the message here if we go delete resource group, we type in Kivas. And it will complain that it still needs, you have to get rid of the resources within it. So I already know that's going to fail.
But what I want you to do is delete the sync group A. So if you select the sync group here and go ahead and delete that, we might also have to delete the endpoints first. Usually Azure is really great about tearing everything down, but in this case, it's not giving us a lot of help here. So we'll just say, yeah, we want to delete this endpoint too.
Let's delete all the server. So you got to first delete the server endpoints, to delete the cloud endpoint, to delete the group, then to delete the actual service. So it's a little bit convoluted, but you know, I guess for whatever reason, this one is not automated like the other one. So just go through those processes, make sure that you get everything deleted out okay, and then you should be in good shape, okay?
Hey, this is Angie Brown from Examro, and we are on to the storage accounts cheat sheet. This one is 6 pages long. I do not know why I did not break it up into more fine or fine-tuned or specific cheat sheets, but that's OK. We'll get our way through it here. It's all summarized for you here, so...
Starting at the top here, Azure has five core storage services. You have Azure Blob, Azure Files, Azure Queues, Azure Tables, Azure Disks. Know the difference between these five. For Blob Storage, there are two types of performance, Standard and Premium. Standard is when you're using hard disk drives. Premium is when you're using solid state drives. And you're going to get varied performance based on the access tiers. We'll see those in a moment here. Azure Storage supports three types of Blobs, Block Blobs, Append Blobs, Page Blobs. Please take the time to read these and understand
The difference for BLOB storage, there are three types of access tiers. For standard storage, you've got cool, hot, and archive, going into detail, hot data that is accessed frequently, cool data that's accessed infrequently, and archive data that's rarely accessed and stored for at least 180 days.
For the account level tiering, any BLOB that doesn't have any explicit assigned tier infers the tier from the storage account accessing tier settings. For BLOB level tiering, you can upload a BLOB to the tier of your choice. Changing the tier happens instantly, except when you are moving out of the archive. Then there's the concept of rehydration. This is when you're moving a BLOB out of an archive into another tier, and it can take several hours. For the BLOB lifecycle management, this is so you can create rule-based policies to transition data to different tiers after 30 days.
days it moves to cool storage. When A BLOB is uploaded or moved to another tier, it's charged at the new tier's rate immediately upon charge. When moving from a cooler tier, the operation is billed as a write operation to the destination tier. When the write operation is per 10,000 and the data writes is per gigabytes charges of the destination tier apply. When moving to a hotter tier, the operation is billed as a...
A read from the source tier where the read observation for at per 10,000 and data retrieval per GB charge for the source tier apply. Early detection charges for any BLOB moved out of the cool or archive tier may apply as well. Cool and archive early detection any BLOB is...
has moved into the cool tier. This is only for GPV2. That's general purpose, right? It is subject to a cool early detection period of 30 days. Any BLOB that is moved into the archive tier is subject to an archive early detection period of 180 days. This charge is prorated. There are multiple ways to move data into Azure Blob Storage. You've got AZ Copy, Azure Storage Data Movement Library, Azure Data Factory, Blob Fuse.
Azure Databox, Azure Import/Export Service. You definitely want to know how to use Azure Copy, not in the cheat sheet, but it's something you need to know in practice. Okay, when you create a storage account, you need to choose a replication type. So, primary region redundancy is, sorry, there's a bunch of different types of replication types, and we've broken these into categories. So, locally redundant storage.
Then you have zone redundant storage. Then you have geo redundant storage. Then you have geo zone redundant storage. And then there's the third tier of these, which is RAGRS and RAGRGZRS. I got it. Okay. And so there's a bunch of different variations here. You have to carefully look at all this and make sure you know the difference.
Now we're on to the third page. Azure Files is a fully managed file share in the cloud. A file share is a centralized server for storage that allows multiple connections to connect to the file share. The network protocols use either SMB or NFS. When a connection is established, the file share's file system will be accessible in a specific directory within your own directory tree. This is known as mounting. You can back up your file shares with shared snapshots, read-only, incremental up to 200 snapshots per file share, retain backups for
up to 10 years. Backups are stored within the file share. So if you delete your file share, you will delete your backup. Soft deletes prevent accidental deletion by turning on soft delete. It's going to be marked for deletion, retained for a period of time before it deletes. For store tiers, you've got premium, transactional, optimized, hot, cool, dead for types of storage. And this is GPV2.
Deployed on either HHD or file storage, it's going to be deployed on SSD. For identity, you can use on-prem or managed via the ADAS, so that's Azure Active Directory Domain Services, or using a store account key. That's where you have a username and password, the username being the storage account name, the password being the account key.
For Azure files, they are accessible inside or outside your AWS account from wherever or anywhere via storage account via public endpoint. SMB connects on port 445. Remember that. I highlighted it for a reason there for you. Your organization may need to unblock this port so you can mount your file share. For encryption, we have encryption at rest, which is Azure Storage Service Encryption, SSC, encrypted in transit using SMB 3.0
Protocol there with encryption or HTTPS. Azure File Sync is a service that allows you to cache Azure file shares on your on-premise Windows Server or Cloud VM. I don't remember seeing super detailed questions on Azure File Sync, except for the fact that you might need to know how to set it up, but not conceptually like use cases and stuff. So that's why it's so short there. I had to take a drink. It's just too much.
Too many slides.
Azure Import/Export Service is used to securely import large amounts of data to Azure Blob Storage and Files.
You have two options for shipping drives on import.
Use your own disk drives or use the Microsoft provided drives.
For the Microsoft provided drives, you can do 5 encrypted solid-state drives known as Azure Data Box Disks with 40 terabytes total capacity per order to your data center through a regional carrier.
To prepare your drive, you'll need to use the file.
following, use the command line, WA import export tool.
I put the details in here because I saw this on the exam.
So I just want, in case you see it, I want you to know all these steps.
Prepare your disk drives that are shipped for import, copying your data to the drive, encrypt the data using BitLocker and generate the data.
drive journal files during the import creation, help identify numbers of drives needed for the export job.
There are two versions of the WA Import Export, version one and version two.
One is for blobs, two is for Azure files.
The WA Import Export tool is only compatible with Windows 64 bit, so you're not using Linux here, okay?
For export jobs, you can only export from Azure Blob.
You can
ship up to 10 empty drives to Azure per job.
You can create export jobs and the data is loaded onto these drives and shipped back to you.
And then this might be the last page.
I'm not sure.
We'll see here in a moment, but we have shared access signatures.
SAS is a URI that generates restricted access rights to Azure storage resources.
Share the URI to the grant client temporary access to a specific set of permissions.
Type of shared access signatures.
You have account level SAS.
This is access to
resources in one or more of the storage services.
You have service level SaaS access to single storage account by using the storage account key, user delegated SaaS access to storage account using Azure AD credentials, limited only to BLOB or containers.
Microsoft considers this method best practice for accessing via SaaS.
A shared access signature comes in different formats.
You've got ad hoc SaaS.
you have service SAS with a stored access policy.
And there we go.
So we're all the way through there.
That was a lot of slides, and hopefully you can retain all that information for the exam.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Prev, and we are looking at Azure Virtual Machines, which makes it easy for you to choose your own OS, compute, memory, and storage, and launch a server within minutes.
All right, so let's take a quick look here at VMs for Azure.
And this is a highly configurable server that relies on virtualization, meaning that you're running a server without having to actually buy and maintain physical hardware that runs it.
You will still have to manage things at the software layer, so you would have to apply your own OS system patches and installing the configuration packages.
But the nice thing is that you're not dealing with that hardware.
It's just going to work for you.
And some things I want you to know about Azure Virtual Machines is that the
Size of the virtual machine is determined by the Azure image, and so the image defines the combination of VCPUs, memory, and storage capacity.
The current limit on a per subscription basis is 20 VMs per region.
I would think that if you wanted more, you could just use another subscription.
I don't know if they have service limit increase for that, but that might be possible as well.
Azure VMs are billed at an hourly rate.
An instance...
or a single instance that you launch is going to have availability of 99.9% when you're using premium disk.
If you have standard disk, I have no idea what it is, but it's going to be less than that.
If you want to get 99.95% availability, you're going to have to launch 2 instances within an availability set, and you can attach multiple managed disks to an Azure Virtual Machine.
Now, just to give you like a quick visual of what's actually happening when you launch an instance, because when you do launch a virtual machine, there's going to be other networking components that are going to be created or associated with you.
And you definitely need to know all these components here.
So I have this nice diagram.
We're going to do a quick run through with it.
And I want you to just know that when you do launch a virtual machine, it actually does give you a list of all the components that it creates.
This is actually very common with most Azure services.
And sometimes what they'll do is they'll put it within a resource group for you so that
that they're all grouped together, which is very nice.
But let's just run through these common components that you need to know, such as the network security group.
And this is going to be attached to your network interface.
It acts as a virtual firewall with rules around ports and protocols.
So that is what's protecting our virtual machine.
You have the network interface that handles IP protocols.
So that's how the virtual machine talks to the internet or other things on the network.
You have the virtual machine itself or the instance.
That's the version or the
instance that is currently running.
It's going to get a public IP address assigned to it.
So that's how people from the internet can actually access the virtual machine.
And then you're going to have to launch it within a virtual network.
And so you're going to have that VNet.
So you'll either choose one or you'll be creating one during that wizard process.
So there you go.
So now let's take a quick look at the options for operating systems on Azure VM, and let's just define what an OS is.
So the OS is the program that manages all other programs in a computer, and the most commonly known operating systems are Windows, Mac OS, and Linux.
And when you want to launch a virtual machine, the way you determine what operating system you use is based on the image that you choose.
Okay?
And Azure has a marketplace, so they have
So many different kinds of operating systems you're going to have every possible option you want, and Microsoft has also partnered with specific companies to make sure that they're providing you images that are updated and optimized for the Azure runtime.
So, let's do a quick run-through of these supported or partnered.
OSes, so we have SUS, we have Red Hat, Ubuntu, Debian, FreeBSD, then you have Flatcar Container Linux, RancherOS, which is for containerization, Bitnami.
Bitnami is more like images that have preloaded software on them.
They're very popular for their Bitnami WordPress.
You have Mesosphere.
And then you have images that have Docker with it.
So you have a lot of options open to you there.
And I always forget about Jenkins, and Jenkins is on the end there.
Now, if you want to bring your own Linux version, you can totally do so.
All you have to do is package it into a virtual hard disk or a VHD.
If you've never heard of VHDs, these are just virtual hard disk formats that you can create using Hyper-V software, which would be on your Windows machine.
And just be aware that Azure doesn't support VHDX, which is a newer format.
It only uses VHD.
Okay, so there you go.
So let's take a quick look here at Cloud Init, and this is something that's not going to be on your exam, but it's something you absolutely should know and need to know because it's an industry standard and it's just something that you...
If I didn't show it to you, no one's going to show it to you, so let's just get to it.
And so, CloudInit is this multi-distribution method for cross-platform cloud instance initialization, and it's supported across all major public cloud providers, so Azure, AWS, GCP, provisioning systems for private cloud infrastructure.
and bare metal installation.
So what is cloud instance initialization?
Well, this is the process of preparing an instance with configuration data for the operating system and the runtime environment.
And so the idea is that you're going to have cloud instances that are initialized from a disk image.
and instance data, right?
So the image is whatever the VM image is, but you're going to have data such as metadata, user data, and vendor data.
And I'm not going to get into all the datas.
I just want you to know the one, which is the one you'll be working with, is user data.
And so user data is a script that you want to run when an instance first boots.
And so if you've ever used AWS and you launch an instance, you'll see a box
in the wizard that says user data, and that's what this is.
In Azure, I don't think they make it as clear.
I don't think they call it user data, but if you're pragmatically doing it with ARM templates when you're doing infrastructure as code, that is what you're doing.
You're using Cloud Init underneath.
I just wanted to make that association to you.
So when you see that word user data, you think Cloud Init.
And so Cloud Init really only works with Linux distributions.
So, it should work with all the Linux distributions on Azure.
I'm pretty sure it's not being used for Windows machines, but there you go.
Azure Virtual Machines come in a variety of different sizes that are optimized for specific use cases.
And the way Azure groups these are into types.
So that would be like general purpose, compute optimized, and sizes.
And sizes is kind of a weird word because I've seen in other places in their documentation called series or SKU family.
So you'll see me using those 3 terms interchangeably.
They definitely confused me when I was looking at it at first.
But let's just go quickly through some of them.
There's a lot of them, so they're not going to be all of them on the list here.
But we'll just quickly go through it.
So the first is general purpose.
These are balanced CPU to memory ratio, testing and development, small to medium databases, and low to medium traffic web servers.
This is pretty much what you're going to be using unless you work for a company that has a lot of money.
And the one you're going to see the most is called B1 because it's super, super cost effective.
And that's the one I'm always using when I'm launching Linux machines.
You'll see me using it through follow-alongs here in this course.
The next one here is compute optimized.
So that's high CPU to memory ratio.
Good for medium traffic web servers, network appliances, batch processes, and app servers.
So this just has more CPU here.
The most common one is the FSV2 or the F series.
Then you have memory optimized.
So high memory to CPU ratio, great for relational databases, medium to high large caches, and in-memory analytics.
We have a variety of SKUs there.
Then you have storage optimized.
So these are high disk throughput and IF and ideal for big data, SQL, NoSQL databases, database warehousing, and large transactional databases.
And we just have LSV2 for those.
Then you have the specialized ones for GPU, for heavy graphic rendering, video editing, model training, and interferencing with deep learning.
So available with single or multiple GPUs.
And so we have a variety of SKUs there.
And then you have your HPCs, your high performance compute.
And these are the most fast and powerful CPU virtual machines with optional high throughput network interfaces.
All right.
And I just want to point out that there are more here.
but I'm just showing you ones that are current.
So there are previous series here, like we're not showing basic A, all right?
Like the A series is not being shown here.
Now, when you want to actually go see this full list here, it's very easy.
You just launch up a virtual machine and you're going to be able to choose two things.
You're going to choose the first, the image.
So that's going to be what do you want to run, right?
So it's going to be Ubuntu or Windows machine.
And then you're going to choose your standard size image.
I believe that if you choose certain images,
Not all sizes will be available to you, because some images have to be optimized for those series.
Sorry, I'm just drinking some tea here.
And so there's that B1 series, and you can see in Canadian dollars it's $9.72, which is a pretty good price for me, and you can explore all the costs in Azure, which is really nice.
You don't have to go to a separate marketing website you can just open it up and you can just sort by the lowest cost, which is what I always do, and they have a lot of filters there, so there you go.
Let's quickly talk about Azure Compute Units.
So, Azure Compute Units, also known as ACUs, provides a way of comparing compute, so CPU performance across Azure SKUs.
Remember, we said SKUs is the same thing as sizes or series.
So you'll just see us varying the terms on that.
ACU is currently standardized on a small, so standard A1.
And you saw prior that A1 is a previous series.
So it's not something that you'd generally be launching, but everything's based off of that one.
And those are given a value of 100.
It's just an arbitrary number to give it a point against other machines.
And all other SKUs then represent approximately how much faster that SKU can run a standard benchmark.
I don't fully understand the math behind their stuff here, but I generally get the idea here, and I'll just show you quickly a quick comparison.
So here we have the A1 to A4 series against the D1-D14 series.
A1 is our baseline at 100 ACUs.
And it has a ratio 1 to 1 from vCPUs to core.
And so you can see that for D1 to D14, it says 160 points to 250 points.
And so if I did the math here right, I think I did, it's going to be basically 60% to 150% more performant than choosing an A1 to A4.
So that's how that works.
So there you go.
So here's a neat feature that Azure Virtual Machines allows you to do.
And you can actually do this with a lot of different services with Azure.
And it's the Azure mobile app.
And so what you'll notice is that when you're using virtual machines, they might have this little QR code.
And if you have the app installed, what you can do is scan that code.
But honestly, you don't even need to scan the code.
If you just have the app installed to connect to your account, you can log in on your phone and check out the virtual machine, how it's performing.
And you can take basic actions there.
I believe as well you can access the
Cloud Shell, so it's pretty darn cool, and so I just wanted you to know about that, and if you haven't, just go ahead and install it on your phone.
I think it's available for Android and iOS.
I have an Android phone, so I didn't check iOS, but yeah, go check it out.
So sometimes when you're launching a virtual machine, you'll have the option between generation one versus generation 2 when you're choosing images.
And I want you to know about this stuff here.
And to understand it, we need to know a little bit about Hyper-V.
So Hyper-V is Microsoft's hardware virtualization product, and it lets you create and run a software version of a computer called a virtual machine.
And each virtual machine acts like a complete computer running an operating system and programs.
And so if you're still kind of wondering what Hyper-V is, if you've ever heard of VirtualBox,
which is used for running VMs on Mac and Linux.
This is basically the exact same offering.
It's just Windows offering, okay?
And it already comes pre-installed on Windows 10.
So you might have to toggle something on it.
I can't remember it because it's been a long time since I've had to configure it.
But the point is that you have a Windows machine, you're already ready to start using Hyper-V.
And Hyper-V
has two generations of virtual machines.
So the first one was generation one, and this will support most guest operating systems.
And then generation 2 supports most 64-bit versions of Windows and more current versions of Linux and FreeBSD operating systems.
And there are these two here, but neither one or two is bad.
So they both have their own use case, so it's not like you should always use two.
And there's a big list online, but we're not going to get into that full list.
But anyway, so we see that Hyper-V has generation one and two VMs, but Azure also has them as well.
But they're not one-to-one the same as Hyper-V generation.
So if you look up Hyper-V, like the Hyper-V generation feature set, you might not have that in Azure, so I wouldn't rely on that list.
But what I definitely want you to know between Azure Gen.
1 and Gen.
2, that's a key difference, is that Gen.
1 is BIOS-based architecture, and Gen.
2 is UEFI-based boot architecture.
And if you've ever built a video gaming machine, you definitely know the difference between these two.
If you don't, it's just the way the machine boots up.
It's the first screen you see.
And it's going to change what kind of configuration options you have.
And UEFI has a lot of great features in it.
So for instance, it has secure boot, which verifies the bootloader is signed by a trusty authority.
And you can have larger boot volumes up to 64 terabytes.
And if you want to know more, you'll just have to look up UEFI because I'm not covering it in this course.
I just want you to know that's the key difference there.
And Hyper-V VMs are packaged into a virtual hard disk format, so that's going to be either VHD or VHDX files, OK?
One thing you might want to be able to do is actually get into your virtual machine.
And we have a lot of different options available to us.
In fact, we have three ways to connect to our virtual machines.
We have RDP, SSH, and Bastion.
And so if you don't know these things, we're going to walk through them right now.
The first is Secure Shell.
And this is a protocol to establish a secure connection between a client and server.
This is how you can remotely connect to a Azure virtual machine via a terminal.
SSH happens on port 22 via TCP.
Port 22 is something you should absolutely remember as SSH.
And you will generally use an RSA key pair to gain access.
You can also use username and password, but most people don't do that anymore.
Another way of getting access to your machine is by using RDP, which is Remote Desktop Protocol.
This is a proprietary protocol developed by Microsoft, which provides a user with a graphical interface to connect to another computer over a network connection.
Basically what it means is that it's going to open up a window and you're going to be able to see like another Windows desktop in it and control it remotely.
So this is how you can remotely connect Windows Server to a virtual desktop.
RDP happens on port 3389 via TCP and UDP.
I think there might be some other ports, but this is the port that you need to know.
I just remember from AWS because there was some extra ports I had to configure, but that's a different story.
Then you have your Bastion, which is your third option.
And so Azure Bastion, which is actually an Azure service, is a service that you can deploy, lets you connect to a virtual machine using your browser and Azure portal.
And so the reason why this is so useful is that if you have, let's say, a Chrome desktop,
which doesn't actually, it can't actually use SSH client or can't use the RDB client.
This just gives you another way of using the browser so you don't have to install those clients.
But we'll get into that shortly here, okay?
So let's take a closer look at SSH and the most common way to access your VM or to authenticate yourself so that you're allowed to get into your VM.
SSH is by using SSH key pair.
And so the idea is that you're going to have to generate out two keys.
That's why it's called a key pair.
There's 2 keys.
And so you'd use that command SSH hyphen keygen hyphen TRSA.
And that is something that is definitely extra in my memory.
It's definitely something you want to memorize because it'll be with you throughout your entire career.
And so you're going to have a private key and a public key.
And so the way these keys work is that the private key should remain on your local system and not be
share with others, and the public key is going to be stored on the VM.
And when you go ahead and SSH, you're going to provide your private key as part of the SSH command, and it's going to try to match it against the public key to authenticate you.
And so that is what you normally do.
You do SSH, hyphen, I provide the public key.
See where it says.pub?
That's how you know it's a public key.
And then there's the actual address of the server, and that's how you're going to gain access, okay?
So let's take a look at the process of using RDP.
So the first thing you'll want to do is download the RDP file.
So when you go and try to connect to that virtual machine, you're going to go ahead and download the RDP file.
That's going to download this RDP, this file that has an RDP extension.
You're going to double-click that file, and you're going to be prompted to fill in your username and password.
This username and password is what you specified when you created your virtual machine.
And I just want you to know that if you are on a Mac, you can install the Remote Desktop Client from the Apple Store, but if you're on Windows, you already have RDP Client installed.
There's nothing extra that you have to do.
So let's take a closer look here at Azure Bastion.
And this is an intermediate hardened instance that allows you to connect to your target server via SSH or RDP.
And it will provision a web-based RDP client or SSH terminal.
I'm going to tell you, honestly, I never really thought of this use case for Bastions prior to this.
But the reason, like Bastions are good or have still a utility these days is because some people are using a Google Chromebook.
They're not going to have a terminal, so they can't use SSA.
or if they're on Windows, they can't install the PuTTY client, or if they're on Windows, they won't have the remote desktop client.
And so the only way is through the web, because a Google Chromebook's all a browser.
And so this is one of those utilities for a bastion.
Now, bastions don't necessarily are just for this use case.
They're definitely a very good and secure way to connect to your virtual machines and having a way of auditing who has access to what.
But this is the use case that Azure is putting
forward with Bastion here.
And so the idea is that when you want to create a Bastion, you're going to have to add it to a subnet in your VNet, or you're going to have to make a new subnet.
And it has to be called Azure Bastion Subnet.
And it has to have at least a size of forward slash 27, so 32 addresses.
So that's what you're going to have to do.
So you'll just have to go in and add in that subnet there.
And then once you do, you can go ahead and launch your Bastion.
So let's first take a look at RDP.
And so RDP, we saw how to do it, but let's see what it looks like with Azure Bastion.
So what you do is you say connect with Azure Bastion for your Windows machine.
That's going to assume that you want RDP.
You're going to just put in your username and password as you normally would, and boom, you're in your machine.
That's all it takes.
Let's take a look at how you do it with SSH.
So, you know, if you're using a Linux server, it's going to obviously want to use SSH because you don't have RDP for that.
And so you can actually use either the SSH private key or the username and password.
I'd recommend using always SSH private key.
Let's take a look at that process.
So you'll enter your username in, and then you can switch over to SSH private key.
And then the.pem file, which is downloaded locally to your machine, which is your private key, you can just select it, and then that will upload it and use it in the comparison, and boom, you're in your machine.
So
That's just kind of a cool service that they have there.
Let's just do a quick comparison between Windows and Linux servers.
This is going to be very obvious for people that are used to running Windows workloads, but for those who grew up on Linux, I just want to make sure you understand some of the caveats of Windows that you might not be used to.
So obviously, Azure allows you to run both Windows and Linux instances or VMs.
And so let's just talk about Windows first.
So when you launch a Windows Server, just like your desktop computer, it needs a Windows license to run, whether it's Windows 10 or whatever Windows Server you're using.
But I just want you to know that when you launch your server, you don't necessarily have to have the license on hand.
And so if you launch a server without a license,
All it's going to do is say Windows is unactivated, and you're going to have to take some manual step to activate that license.
And I just want to tell you that so that you're not afraid of launching a Windows machine because you think you're going to get charged a license fee.
It's not going to happen.
You have to take some manual intervention to do that.
So do not worry about launching that Windows machine.
You can bring your own license via a hybrid license.
So some people, like enterprises, already own their licenses, and they just want to
They already made a deal with Microsoft, and so they just want to reuse those instead of using whatever Azure provides, because it can be cheaper.
You're going to set a username and password because you're using RDP to access the machine, so you're not using your SSH key pairs.
Windows machines require larger instances.
Okay, so...
If you're running Windows 10 or whatever, it needs a lot more memory.
And so you're going to have to run it on a B2, which is a lot more expensive than a B1.
And that's because it runs a full desktop environment.
All the Windows servers do this.
And so this is generally why I like running Linux.
So just be aware not to keep your Windows Server running for very long if you don't have a lot of money and you're just learning to pass the certification.
Let's talk about Linux really quickly here.
Most versions of Linux require no type of license.
So I think you can get Red Hat.
You might need a license for that if you want support.
You set either a username, password, or SSH key pair.
You can utilize smaller VM sizes because you're not running a full desktop experience.
Could you run like a full desktop experience?
Possibly.
I haven't ever tried to do it on cloud myself.
Unix and Linux-based systems traditionally are terminal-based environments, right?
So you're going to be SSHing into them
and you're not going to have something visual.
Okay, so there you go.
So let's talk about update management.
At the start of this section for virtual machines, I had said that there was some requirements, ongoing software patches and things that you had to perform on your virtual machines.
And so that is something that you have to take care of, but if you wanted to automate that process, this is where you can use update management.
So that's what it'll do.
It'll install operating system updates and patches for both Windows and Linux.
And not only can it do it for your virtual machines on Azure, but it can do it on-premise and even in other cloud providers.
And the way this is going to work is you're going to go to your operations tab where it says guest plus host updates, and you're going to click on update management.
Now, update management looks like its own service, but it's actually using Azure Automations underneath.
And so that's what is installing the agent.
And the agent is the Microsoft Monitoring Agent MMA.
So that's how it knows what to do.
You have to get that installed on your machine.
So update management will perform a scan for update compliance.
A compliance scan is by default performed every 12 hours on a Windows machine and every three hours on a Linux machine.
It can take between 30 minutes and six hours for the dashboard to display updated data from managed computers.
I just wanted to point out a little bit about Azure Automation, because it does more than just obviously update management, but Azure Automation, you can enable update management, change tracking, inventory, start/stop VMs during off hours, features for your servers and virtual machines.
And these features have a dependency on a log analytics workspace, and therefore require linking the workspace with an automation account.
So there is a little bit of extra that we have to have, but there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're going to be launching our own Bastion using Azure Bastion Services.
So there's two ways to set this up.
We can go to Bastions over here.
and create a bastion this way, or we can create one after we've created a virtual machine.
I prefer the latter, so let's go ahead and do that and launch ourselves a new virtual machine.
And so we could either launch a Windows Server or a Linux Server.
Today I'm going to be launching a Windows Server.
And what we'll do is go down here.
I'll make a new group.
We'll call it the Enterprise.
And as we do that, we'll just name this
Enterprise D, and we'll launch that in Canada central US, that's fine with me.
2019 data center Gen.
2 is totally fine.
If you go here, if you're trying to find it, you go, hit select, and we'll choose Gen.
2 data center.
It is expensive, but we're not going to be using this for very long.
For the username, I'm going to put data.
And for the, I'll just make it Azure user to make our lives a bit easier.
And then we'll put testing, capital T, 123456, testing, 123456.
And we will go down below, we're fine with the settings here, we're going to go next to disk, we're going to leave the disk to premium, that's fine.
We'll let it create a new network, that's totally fine.
Management is okay.
And we'll just actually go hit review and create.
And now we'll just hit Create, so that it will go ahead.
and do that.
It'll tell us that it's in progress.
And we'll just wait a little bit here.
I'll see you back in a moment.
Alright, so our instance is ready.
So let's go ahead and go to this resource here.
And then on the left hand side, you'll have connect.
And so I'm going to show you and you don't, it's not necessary for you to do this step, because you're going to show you how to connect via the bastion.
But I'm going to go ahead and download this file, the RDP file.
This will only work if you're on Windows, by the way.
Well, I guess it'll work on Mac, but you'd have to install
the the RDP service for that users with Windows there.
And so here, this is Azure user, we're going to type in testing with a capital T, just double check that there.
I'm going to log in, make sure that this works.
We'll do that one more time.
Oh, you know, it's testing 123456.
There we go.
We'll say yes.
And we'll just make sure that we can remote desktop into this just before anything else.
And there we go.
So that's all good to me.
I don't need to see any more.
We'll go over to Bastion.
We'll say use Bastion.
And this is going to set up a Bastion service.
In order to use Bastion, you need to have another address space defined for it.
makes it really easy to make it here.
So I'm just going to go 10.0.1.0 forward slash 24.
And we'll go ahead and hit OK.
And so down below, it's going to choose an address space.
We have a security group.
I'm just going to put it for none.
I don't think I want one on that.
And if we scroll on down here, we have the resource group.
So we're going to put it in the same resource group, and we'll go ahead and create that.
So now before this, they didn't have this really nice wizard.
You used to have to go and create all those things individually in your virtual network.
But this is really nice.
It does take a bit of time for this to provision.
So I'll see you back here in a bit.
That took a bit of time for that to create that bastion, but it is ready to go.
And so now that we have it, we can go ahead and utilize this connection here.
And so right away, I think it's setting up for RDP here.
So what we'll do is type in Azure user.
And then capital T, testing 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
We'll go ahead and hit connect.
And so notice that I didn't have to use an external application.
I could just run it in right here.
It's all in the web browser.
So that's pretty much how the Bastion works.
I can't remember the pricing on Bastion.
I think it's a little bit of money, so I don't want to keep this laying around here.
But this is great if you, let's say you're on a Chromebook, which are becoming really popular, where you can't install native applications.
or you're just having issues because you're on like Linux or something like that.
So there you go.
That's all there is to it.
We'll go ahead and clean this up.
And so I'm just going to go here, find the resource group, and we'll go ahead and delete.
I'm just making sure that bastions within there.
So it is good.
And there we go.
So we just launched a virtual machine for Linux.
Now let's go ahead and launch one for Windows.
So I'm going to go to the top here and type in virtual machines.
We'll go to the first link, I'm going to hit add, add virtual machine.
And what we'll do is we'll create a new group.
The last one I had was called Bajor.
I'm going to call this one Cardassia, Cardassia.
And I'm going to name this
machine, also named Cardassia.
And this time, what we want to do is we want to move over to a Windows Server.
I find the easiest one to learn with is the Windows 10 Pro Server, just because I find these ones a little bit daunting.
So I'm going to go Windows 10 Pro.
And then what we're going to do is go choose a larger size.
This is not going to work.
We cannot run a Windows Server on a B1 LS.
So we're going to have to go a little bit larger.
And we don't have to go too much larger here.
But the idea here is that there's going to be a more expensive spend here.
So we're not going to be running to keep this running for long.
But here we have the B2S, that is the appropriate size to run this.
Anything smaller, I don't think is going to work.
And we are going to put in a password here.
So I'm just going to put in Cardassia.
And we'll do Cardassia, one, two, three.
Put a capital on it, I guess.
We'll just do this here.
And I'm just going to go back and lowercase this one.
And we're going to allow the inbound port of 3389, because that is what RDP needs.
I'm going to confirm that I have a Windows license.
I actually don't.
But the thing is, you can still launch one for your test purposes.
It'll just complain saying you're not activated.
So there are some limitations, but it's good enough for us to learn, okay?
And so now that is all great, we'll go next to disks.
We're going to go with standard SSD this time.
We are going to go ahead and hit next and go to networking.
It's going to create us a new VNet, which is a great idea.
We're going to let it create a network security group on the NIC, just like before.
We'll go ahead and hit next.
We'll leave all these options alone.
This all seems fine to me.
And we'll hit next, review and create.
And we'll go ahead and create this server.
All right, and so that's going to go ahead and create it.
So I'll just see you back here in a moment when that's done deploying.
All right, and so after a short little while here, it looks like our Windows Server is now deployed.
So what we can do is go to that resource.
And if you wanted to see what it's deployed, it's the same stuff as always.
You have your network interface card, your virtual network NSG, the IP address.
So let's actually go to that resource now.
And so let's see how we can gain access to this virtual machine.
And so what we can do is use RDP.
Luckily, I am on a Windows machine.
And so I already have the RDB client that I can use.
So all you got to do is download the RDB file.
And then once we have that file, I can just double click it.
And I can open this up.
If you're on a Mac, you can download the app in the App Store.
And so I'll go ahead and type in my password.
So my username was Cardassia.
And then my password was capital CARDASSIA123.
We'll hit OK.
And then it'll give us another warning.
We'll say yes.
And now we are in our virtual machine.
So there you go.
How cool is that?
I'll just give it a moment to load up, but this is a full Windows 10 Pro.
And as I said before, we don't actually have a license.
So if you're afraid of spinning it up, because you're going to get charged a license fee for Windows, you do not have to worry.
That's not going to happen.
You have to do some manual intervention for that to happen.
So we'll just wait a little while here for this to load.
It is not, we're not using the most powerful machine, so it does take a little bit of time.
And so we just hit accept here.
And here we are.
So we are on, we have our nice Windows machine here.
Whoops.
I don't know if it has any games.
Let's go take a look.
Maybe play Minesweeper.
No, maybe maybe you have to download in the store.
I'm not that familiar with Windows machines.
But
So there you go.
So we'll go ahead and close that.
And if we were using the Bastion, it's the same process.
You saw how we used it with SSH, but if we had the Bastion and it's so much work to set one up, we already did that before.
But all you do is enter your credentials in on the page just as we did, and it's just a lot easier that way.
So let's go ahead and just tear down this machine.
We're all done with it.
So I'm just going to hit delete.
And if we find that resource group, we should be able to easily delete them all.
I find the easiest ways to go up here, go to all resources, and then there's the resource group there, and then hit delete resource group.
And then I'll type in the name of it, which is Cardassia, and I'll delete all those resources.
But after that's done, always just take a double check on your all resources tab and just make sure that those resources are gone because sometimes they stick around.
But there you go.
That's as simple as it was to launch a Windows machine.
Hey, this is Angie Brown from Exam Pro.
And let's take a look here at virtual machines, which I consider the backbone of most cloud service providers.
And Azure keeps it really simple by calling it virtual machines.
So we can go up here and type in virtual machine and make our way over here.
But right now I don't have any options because I'm using a tenant that doesn't have a subscription applied to it.
So what I'm going to do is go switch back to my original tenant.
And this one has a subscription applied to it.
And so what I'll do is just click back up here, and now we'll just type in virtual machines.
And I can now see I have options of creating virtual machines.
Let's go ahead and go create a Linux one first, and then we'll go ahead and create a Windows one, and then we'll see how we can connect to it.
All right, so first we'll go to the top here, hit Add, we'll click on Virtual Machine.
And we're going to be presented with a lot of options.
So we'll have to choose a subscription.
And so there is mine.
I want to probably create a new resource group here.
I'm going to call this one Bajour.
And we'll name this Bajour again.
And I'm going to launch this in US East.
I'll just set it to one availability zone for the time being.
Then here we have what we can choose as an image.
I can click on see all images.
and choose from a variety of them.
So if I didn't want to use Ubuntu, I could launch something else like Debian or something like that.
But really, I just want to stick with Ubuntu because I'm fine with that version with 18.
Then here's what really matters is the size because that's going to affect our cost.
So if we click on see all sizes, we have this nifty table where we can sort the cost.
It's just loading the cost here.
It's dynamic.
This is going to be based on what your base subscription is.
So if you're
In Canada, you're going to see Canadian prices, in the US, you're going to see US prices, et cetera, et cetera.
And I care a lot about cost here, so I'm just going to sort this by cost.
And here we have the B1LS, which is very cost-effective.
We have a RAM of 0.5 gigabytes and some other options there.
So we'll go ahead and select that there.
And we have a couple options.
We can use SSH public key, or we can utilize a password.
And so I think what we'll do is use an SSH public key, because that's pretty much the standard there.
We're going to name the username Bajor if it lets us.
Probably won't probably want some additional options there.
No, it's okay.
Oh, great.
And we'll go ahead and generate a new key pair.
And I'm just going to name that one Bajor.
And we have some options here for inbound rules.
So you could set to none.
This is just setting up the NSG for you.
But we're probably going to want to have that port open for SSH because that's how we're going to make our way back in here.
If we're running a like an Apache server, we'd want to have port 80 open.
So we can go ahead and do that.
We'll take a look at now disks.
So here we have options between premium standard and standard HHD.
I just want this to be cost effective.
So I'm just going to go with standard HDD.
But generally you want to have at least standard or premium SSD when you're running real web development workloads.
Then there's encryption here.
And so it's always turned on by default, which is great.
They also have this option of double encryption with the platform managing customer managed key.
We're just going to leave that as default.
Enable alter disk compatibility.
That's not something we need to do here because we are not using ultra disk.
And here you can see that you can attach multiple disks here.
So I can go and do that, but that's not something I need to do today.
And some other advanced options, which we do not care about.
We'll go over to networking.
And so it's going to end up creating us a new vNet for us.
And it will create a new subnet for us and assign it an IP address.
It will also set up a NICS.
network security group.
So the network security group is not going to be applied at the subnet level.
It's going to be applied at the NIC, which is attached to the DC2 there.
And so we'll just leave it to basic.
We're going to allow inbound ports for port 80 and 22.
That was carried over from earlier.
We can put this behind a load balancer, but I don't think we're going to do that right now.
We'll go over to management.
We have some additional options here for monitoring.
This is all okay here.
We can set it to auto shutdown.
Actually, I'll leave that alone.
You can also enable backups here.
We'll go advanced.
And now we have this option here for custom data.
I covered a section on cloud init, and they don't call this user data, but most other providers will call this user data.
So we could provide a bash script or additional information here if we wanted to.
Then down below, there's some host group options.
We're not going to worry about that in proximity placement group.
This is really important if you need to have instances nearby.
I think this is pretty common with, what's it called, high-capacity workloads, HFC.
I can't remember the initialism right now, but we covered it in the core content.
Then we can tag our resource here.
We'll just leave that alone.
I don't care about tagging too much.
But generally, it's good to tag in practice.
And then we will get to review and create our server here.
We'll go ahead and hit create.
And then we'll have to download our private key so we can utilize it later.
And so that's downloaded there.
And now we're just waiting for it to deploy this.
And I'll see you back here in a moment.
So we had to wait a little bit there.
And finally, our deployment is complete.
We can go ahead and just review all the things that it created.
So notice that it created the virtual machine, it created a network interface, a NIC for us, the NSG, the network security group, the virtual network, and also a public IP address.
When I do cleanup, a lot of things I always miss are these IP addresses.
And I know that Azure gave me a warning that said, hey, you're about to spend $700 yearly on IP addresses because you weren't releasing them.
So when we do the cleanup step, I'll definitely emphasize about deleting those IP addresses and how to go about that.
Let's go take a look at the actual resource now.
So here we are, and you can see we have a lot of options on the left-hand side, such as the disk.
So we can see the disk options there, and there's additional security options.
Let's go take a look at how we can go ahead and connect to the server.
And so there's different options here.
So we have RDP, SSH, and Bastion.
Since we are using a Linux machine, we're not going to be using RDP.
That's really for Windows.
But the trick here is that I would need to have a client on my computer to connect like, I think it's called Putty.
If you're on a Linux-based machine, it's a lot easier.
And certainly I have the Linux subsystem installed, so I could probably connect that way.
But I figured let's just go ahead and connect via bastion because I think this is a pretty darn cool feature.
So let's go ahead and create ourselves a bastion.
And this will take a little bit of time here.
But we'll go ahead here and just set up subnets.
So to associate a virtual network to a bastion, it must contain a subnet with the Azure bastion subnet.
So they actually have a special subnet for it.
So what we'll do is we'll just go back to our our server here, which we called Bajor.
And I think we can find a subnet through here.
So on the left-hand side, if we go to networking, we probably could find it that way.
So I'm just looking for that security group in there.
It should be, maybe it's not there.
If it's not there, well, you know, we could just go over, make our way over to subnets.
It's not a big deal.
Because it's called Bajor.
It's pretty darn easy to find to begin with.
And so under subnets here, what we need to do is add a special one here.
And I just got to remember how this works.
So you need to create a subnet called Azure Bastion Subnet with a prefix of at least 27.
So we'll go ahead and add a new subnet.
And we'll call it that.
We'll take out the space there.
And the range is 10, 0, 1, 0, etc.
So we'll just do it on 2, 0.
2.0 forward slash 27.
10 002 is not contained.
Yeah, it overlaps.
So we'll do to not contain the virtual network address space.
Oh, right, so we have to add the address space first.
Oops, we'll just cancel here.
That's okay, we'll discard that we'll make our way over to address space.
And we'll go ahead and add 10.0 dot
2.0 forward slash 24.
They'll give us a pretty darn large range there.
And so now what we'll do is go back to our subnet.
And we'll go ahead and create that there.
And it said only needed 27.
So we'll just give it only 27.
We don't need to go bigger than we need.
And that should be okay, we'll go ahead and hit save.
And it shouldn't take too long.
So now that we have that we can go back here.
And we'll give give this another go here.
It's there, so it shouldn't be complaining.
Maybe what we'll do is just start from the start here again.
Yeah, there you go.
The Azure portal is like that a lot where you'll have something set up and it has the old state of it.
And so you just have to trust yourself that you know what you're doing and you have to go back.
But if you don't have a lot of confidence, a lot of times you'll get stuck and you'll think, okay, I don't have it right.
But always just try again and hit refresh because the Azure portal is very inconsistent.
So we're just going to have to wait for this to create.
This does take a little while to create, so I'll see you back in a moment.
So after waiting 5 minutes, our bastion is now created.
And so what we can do is without even using a PuTTY client or having to use Linux directly, we can just connect via the bastion.
So here we'll see we have some options here.
So we want to do SSH private key from local file.
Okay.
And what we can do is go ahead and select our Bajour key.
And then I'll just scroll down here and hit connect.
Oh, and I think we made the username Bajour.
And we'll go ahead and connect now.
And it's complaining about a pop-up here, so we'll go up here and say, always allow.
And we'll try that again.
And then we'll say allow again.
And so now that we're into our server here, let's go ahead and try to install Apache and see if we can get at least the default page running.
So this is using Ubuntu.
If my memory serves me correctly, it should be apt-get install apache2.
And we'll just hit Y for continue.
And we'll just wait for this to install.
It doesn't take too darn long.
And after a short little wait there, it finally did install.
Also, if you notice this little icon here, we have a little clipboard here.
I don't seem to ever use that there, so that's fine.
Now, when you install Apache, we might have to go ahead and start it up.
So let's just take a look to see if it actually is in the running directory here.
So we'll go to cd var www.
And so that's where the default directory is, right?
But we can just check to see if it's running by doing a ps aux.
I think it's htpd.
Or we can say Apache here.
And so it looks like it's already running, so that's pretty great for us.
And since it's running on port 80 and we've opened up port 80, we should probably be able to access that here.
So let's go back to our actual virtual machine.
So we'll go to virtual machines.
And we have that virtual machine running.
I'm just going to click into it because I just want to find out its public IP address.
So here it is there.
And if we're lucky, this will just work.
Just a copy to clipboard button right there.
And look at that.
We have the default page.
Isn't that cool?
So that's all there really is to it.
And I could even update this page.
You don't have to do it, but I'm just going to update it for fun.
Actually, I probably have to restart the server, so maybe I won't do that.
But yeah, so we connected through the Bastion.
So that was pretty darn easy.
We probably could have also used the Cloud Shell to connect.
But maybe we could give that a go as well.
Since we're all done here, let's go ahead and do some cleanup.
The first thing I want to do is, the easiest way is actually to go to all resources here on the left-hand side.
And this really gives you an idea of everything that's running in your account.
So I actually have other stuff in here that's not relevant.
But the idea is that all of our stuff is running within a resource group.
And so I'm just taking a look there.
I'm not seeing this is all resources here.
Let's see if we see resource group here.
Yeah, they're all there right there.
So I can go ahead and click that.
And so everything more or less should be self-contained within here.
See all that stuff?
You can even see the VNet is part of it as well.
And so if I go ahead and delete this resource group, it should delete all this stuff.
So I'm just going to type Bajor to confirm.
And we'll go ahead and delete.
And that should do a good job of cleaning up all those files.
I'm not sure if it will delete the IP.
It should right there, but if it doesn't, what I recommend is after everything is deleted, just go back here to all resources and just double check to make sure they all vanish.
Because when this is done, they're all going to start to vanish from this list.
And if there's anything remaining, you'll know because it's still here, right?
So just be careful about that.
That's all I want you to know.
And so that's the Linux part.
And so let's go ahead and actually now set up a Windows Server.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and it's really important that we know how to monitor our virtual machines so we can kind of check their performance or do some diagnostics on them.
And so a couple of things we're going to look into, we're going to set up some virtual machines, and we're going to look into automation accounts, log analytics, and metrics and alerts, okay?
So the first thing we'll need to do before we do anything else is make sure that we have particular resource providers enabled.
So go to the top here, and as always, go to your subscriptions.
And we will click into our subscription, go all the way down to the bottom, click on resource providers.
And there's two in particular we're looking for.
One is for alerts, so it's alerts management.
So make sure that is registered.
If it's not, press that button.
And then we want insights.
So make sure insights is enabled as well.
This should be by default, but just in case they're not, you should go ahead and do that.
So we are going to need some virtual machines.
I'm going to set up three.
And the reason I want to do that is just to show you that there's many different ways in Azure to do the exact same thing.
And sometimes when you do something, it just works, and sometimes it just doesn't.
And it can work again and not again.
So I want to give you a few different options available to you.
So the first thing we're going to spin up is a
a virtual machine.
And this one in particular, we'll make a new group.
We're going to call it DAX.
And so we're going to choose for this one an Ubuntu Linux.
I'm going to switch it over.
I'm going to choose a minimal install.
So we'll choose this one over here, which is the Ubuntu server minimal.
And what I'll do is name this.
And there's a bunch of different DAXs in Star Trek.
So we're going to go with curs on DAX here.
And we'll put all this in East US.
So wherever it defaults here.
So if that's where it wants to go, that's where it's going to be.
But let's pay attention to where that is.
Okay.
Let's make sure that we're using a very inexpensive instance.
We'll give it a second to load.
If you do not see the cost, just drag these over until you do.
It just depends on your screen, right?
So once this loads, it will tell us that this is probably the cheapest.
I think that is the cheapest because something's going to go lower than
at 500 megabytes of RAM.
So I think we're already set to it.
I'm not going to wait for it to load.
It'll take forever.
Notice the red line.
There is no error.
That's just what it shows.
And so I'm going to go for password authentication here.
And what I'm going to do for this account is I'm going to type in DAX is the username and then testing with a capital T-E-S-T-I-G, 123456 because it wants an uppercase, a lowercase, some numbers, and a certain length.
And that's what works for me.
So now that I have those filled in, SSH, we're going to keep that open.
We're going to go to disk.
You can leave it on premium if you want.
I'm going to go to standard.
I want to save some money just in case I forget to turn this machine off.
It's going to set up some networking for us, which is totally fine.
We're going to go to management.
And I believe, so there should be guest OS install here.
It is not here.
It's the next step, I believe.
Where is it?
I know you're in here.
Let's go back one step here.
I have a feeling it's on this page, because you can install the guest OS metrics right away.
So I'm just seeing here, I cannot seem to remember where it is.
I might have skipped over it because I'm going so quick here.
Oh, maybe it's not set here.
So when we go to do the other virtual machine, we'll see if it's actually there.
But for this one, we'll just launch it without it.
which is totally fine.
I was going to do one that way anyway.
And so we'll go ahead there and create that virtual machine.
Okay, now while that is going, and by the way, if you think you call that number, that's not me.
So you know, you can call if you want, but it won't go to me.
So that's going to go ahead and deploy that.
What I'm going to do now is go and launch another virtual machine in the same
in the same environment.
So this one this time around is going to be again, it's going to be Linux, we're gonna choose DAX here.
And this one is going to be Jed Zia DAX.
And we this time around, we're going to choose Ubuntu server LTS.
So this one's a minimal install.
And this one here has a bit more to it, we're going to choose Gen.
two.
This is now $4.86, which is strange.
It looks like it was the same one before.
I don't know why the other one was still more expensive.
Because I swore it said $40, but maybe I was mistaken.
The red means nothing as per usual.
It's just Azure tricking us.
We're going to call the username here DAX testing with a capital TESTING.
You know what I'm trying to say here.
And I'm going to do testing 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
And we will go next to disks.
We'll stick with premium for this time.
It doesn't really matter.
If we go to advanced here, there's no interesting options there.
This is all fine.
This looks good.
We go to management.
So now notice here, so we didn't have it for the minimal install, but for this one, we do.
We can actually put in the guest OS.
diagnostics, and what it will do is it will have to create itself a storage account, so that will be in Azure Storage to store our diagnostic data.
And so that seems like a good idea to me.
So what we'll do is we're going to go to next, but notice we didn't have it for the minimal install, probably because it doesn't have the agent, what's called the WAG agent installed.
for it to do that by default.
So just notice that it varies on some machines.
We're going to go to Next, we're going to hit Review and Create.
And we're not done yet.
We're going to create one more virtual machine.
And this time it's going to be a Windows.
Once I hit the Create button here, we're going to go back to virtual machines.
And this time I'm going to launch a Windows machine.
And I'm going to use, we're going to put in the same group here, I'm going to call this one
Tobin or let's call it Lila DAX here.
And this time I'm going to choose a Windows Server.
So I'm going to go to Windows Server here.
We have a lot of options.
I'm not that great with Windows servers.
I'm going to choose a Gen.
2 Windows Server here.
It's not going to let us get away with this B1L.
It's not big enough.
You need a lot more compute and memory.
I think it's like 2 and 4, but I just remember to always choose DS2V2.
which is pretty hefty.
It's pretty expensive.
Maybe I could choose something cheaper, like the DS1.
No, I need to, I need to CPUs.
So DS2v3, that's when you're launching a Windows Server.
If you don't do that, they'll complain.
And that'll probably be pretty darn expensive, but we got to make sure that we just shut this off and get through this as quick as possible.
I'm going to choose the same thing as always.
So I'm going to put in DAX.
And then for the password, I'm going to do testing, 123, capital on that T, 456, testing, 123456, because it wants 12 characters.
We're going to let it do on the RDP.
That's totally fine.
Sure, premium SSD.
We're not going to keep this around for very long.
We're going to scroll on down, go to management.
And notice that you can enable OS diagnostics here.
I'm not going to do that here.
Just so I can show you show you it in the other variation.
We're going to go to next, we're going to go hit review and create.
And we're going to go ahead and create this instance whenever it lets us do it.
There we go.
Okay, we'll hit create.
And now it's deploying.
So we have these three virtual machines we're creating.
And so what I'm going to do is make my way back to virtual machines here.
And so I have the two there.
I'm going to give it a refresh, make sure I can see the third one creating.
We don't see it just yet, but these ones are running.
So what I'm going to do is open up Curzon.
I'm going to open up Jedzia.
And one has the guest, the guest or the.
what's it called?
Diagnostic settings.
It's the guest metrics installed, and the other one does not.
So if I scroll down here, so I just want to show you, there's a lot of variation, and sometimes, you know, you do it one way, it works, another way, it doesn't.
So for Jedzia, it was installed on default.
So that's the one that is using Ubuntu standard.
And then this is the minimal install, where it's saying, hey, do you want to install the metrics?
And you have to pick a storage account.
If you didn't, then you would have the option to create one.
Here it's called DAX.
DIAG.
So I just want to show you, we're going to go ahead and enable those guest level monitoring metrics.
Okay.
So we have a storage account and that's where the data is going to go.
And this will probably fail because I don't think it has the necessary things installed.
I just wanted to show you could do it that way.
But what the other thing we're going to need is we're going to need a log analytics workspace.
So all a log analytics workspace is a place to store your logs.
It is essentially a data lake for a lot of different resources.
So you can put all sorts of resources under here.
And that way you can search across them, see how this failed.
If you ever have a failure like this, the way you'd investigate this as you go in here, and even though it says a SAS token for the storage account couldn't generate, it's kind of a misleading thing here.
Because if I actually click in up into my notifications, we go to our activity log.
we can see kind of what something has happened here.
So I know this failed.
It might not show up here yet.
Sometimes it takes time to show up.
So we'll revisit this later, but it would show red errors here.
And if we looked into there, it would tell us that Python's not installed on that machine because it's a minimal Linux install.
So if you run into those problems, that's the reason why.
Some VMs are a bit easier to work with than others.
But we're looking at log analytics.
And again, it's just a place to collect your logs.
But I want to see
because I think JetZ is the one that actually is the one that is working properly.
But if we go down to metrics or logs, it's going to say, hey, if you want to use logs, you're going to have to go ahead and create, you have to enable it.
But what it's really doing is it's creating a log analytics workspace.
So if I click this here, what it's going to tell me is say, hey, you don't have one.
We'll create a default one for you.
I don't want to do it that way.
What I want to do is create one myself.
and then link it through there.
Or what I could do is make it through automation.
So what I'm going to do is, I think what I'm going to do is I'm going to do through automation.
So there's another service called automation accounts.
And this particular service is for configuration management, update management.
And it's a way for us to keep our VMs up to date.
And so this one's going to be called DAX.
Oh, it's too short, doesn't like that DAX automation.
And I'm going to choose the resource group DAX, it's ES,
East US, and here it's going to say Azure run as account.
So this is going to give it more permission so that it can run as a contributor role, and that way it will have access to resources to do what it wants to do.
So we'll go ahead and deploy that.
And then once this is deployed, we'll create our workspace through this, because I found an issue where if I made this and tried to link it, just didn't link, and I don't want to have those problems.
So I'm just going to make my life a little bit easier by making it through here.
So under here, if we go to update management, it's going to say, hey, you need a workspace in order to use update management, if you want to update management is it keeps your VMs up to date by applying patches.
So if we drop down here, we're just going to go ahead and create a new workspace.
And I'm going to do it that way, because it'll be automatically associated with that workspace on creation.
And we'll let that go there for a bit.
But while that's setting up a new workspace for us, if you go over to runbooks, this is the power of, well, I'm not, I'm not, it wants to make that thing there.
So I'm just going to click OK there.
Don't worry about that discard.
But the whole power of this is that it can apply patches.
It can manage the state of your VMs.
But if you need to do something,
like run something, like a series of run commands.
They have a bunch of different runbooks here.
So there's a variety of different kinds, and I think we can click into them.
There was something about SQL that sounded kind of how to use an SQL command on an automation runbook.
So yeah, it's just a runbook.
So runbook just means like a series of run commands, something that you're automating on your server, and you do it through here.
So update management looks like it is now working.
We didn't press that enable button.
initially, but it worked there.
But if we wanted to have VMs under here, we'd have to go ahead and add them manually.
And so we're just going to wait for those to show up.
Alternatively, if we go back to our server, or sorry, one of our VMs, we should be able to add it this way, or it'll just tell us to go that way anyway.
So there should be like update management or something in here.
Could be configuration management.
that still would be through something, right?
So it'd probably be still through automation.
But I could have swore there was, maybe it's guest and host updates.
Yeah, so here it's just saying go to Azure Automation.
So you don't really set it through here.
You have to associate it through Azure Automation.
And so these are ready to enable.
So I'm going to say go ahead and enable those.
I don't know where our Windows server is.
We definitely spun one up.
It's not a big deal if we don't have it.
It's not really crucial to this tutorial, but it would have been nice to show
the Windows 10.
There, I'm gonna go see what happened to our Windows Server.
Oh, it is there.
Okay, Lila's there.
So we'll take a look at that in a second.
But we're just adding those there, we're not going to really apply any passes, I just want to show you how to associate them there.
And just to highlight the fact that there are runbooks, which are pretty cool.
And you can also do other things like if you need to, like install Python packages or stuff like that, to do stuff, you could do that as well.
So there's a bunch of interesting things in there, but it's kind of like a side dish to the follow along here.
So this would have created our workspace.
So now let's go over to our workspaces.
And we have one here.
And if you're just curious what it looks like if we go here, there's nothing super exciting.
You just put the name and region in and it has the default pay as you go.
So you're not really missing out on creating one by hand there.
But underneath here,
What we can do is see if our virtual machines are actually associated with this here.
So if we go under virtual machine, you're going to see that these ones are connecting, which is interesting because I didn't do anything to connect them.
I'm not sure why that's happening, but I'm going to hit connect here.
And that will connect that.
A lot of times I'll come in here, I have to manually connect them.
I don't know if it's because we put them in the, what do you call it, within the automation there.
If we go back to automation, which ones did I choose?
I already forgot.
Update management.
They're not showing up here now, but I know they're there.
Maybe we triggered it when we were doing there.
But anyway, the point is that you have to make sure that those are configured so that it's actually sending data over to the workspaces so that we can then use the logs and things like that.
So if we go back to our virtual machines over here, you can see they're connecting.
This takes forever.
While this is going, let's go take a look at storage accounts.
And actually a better way would just be to go look at the virtual machine individually here.
So we'll just go back to my virtual machines and I go to the resource group.
We scroll on down here, we should see a storage account within here.
Let's just type in storage.
There it is.
Whoops.
And the thing is, that we can actually view some of the data in here.
So if you go to Open Explorer, you'd have to install this.
It's for Windows.
I don't, I think it's for Mac as well.
But once you have the Storage Explorer open, you can just click Open here.
And it'll open up once it's installed on your computer, of course.
And what I can do, if we have any data, it might not be collecting any data yet, but if we go down to our storage accounts here, oh, here it is down below.
and expand it under tables.
So he has this WAD, that is the name of the agent that is collecting data.
And here you can see that it's already collecting stuff.
All right.
And it's collecting for Jetzia DAX.
And so I'm just kind of looking at the data that it's collecting, nothing super interesting.
But the thing is, is that we're going to make our way over to logs because by default,
Azure collects host metrics, so things about the instance like CPU usage, but there's things that it doesn't collect, like memory and other things like that.
So that's why we need to turn on this setting here, the diagnostic settings, so we can collect those metrics.
These are called guest metrics.
So we have memory, network, file disk, disk, and storage.
So if you wanted to know
how much storage was left on the actual disk with the virtual machine or how much memory was being used, you'd need that set up here.
Once this is enabled, you can send data over into Azure Monitor and other places.
It's not showing app analytics, I think that's for, or log insight, whatever the name of the service is, it's for
That one, I think, is for the Windows one, so we'll see that when we go over there.
But syncs just means we're going to send data from here to Azure Monitor, right?
But we'd have to have preview to see that.
Nothing that interesting here.
But if we go over to logs now, this should not be showing up here anymore.
So if this is still showing an enable screen, then we've got to go back to
our log analytics, we'll click into here, we'll go down to virtual machines, and we'll see if it's connected yet.
So it still says it's connecting, right?
This one's ready, though.
And I haven't even done anything with that one yet.
So what we'll do while we're waiting for these Linux ones to spin up, we'll go back over here to our virtual machines, and we'll go find that Windows machine, which I don't know why it's not showing up here.
There it is.
And what we'll do is we'll go ahead and connect to it.
So I am on a...
Windows machine.
So I'm going to shape here, and I'm going to click on RDP.
And I'm going to download that file.
I'm going to double click this file on my Windows machine.
And I'll be able to open this up instantly.
It was called DAX testing 123, whoops, testing 123456.
Looks good to me.
We'll hit OK.
We'll say yes.
Because if you want to collect
particular metrics, the guest metrics, you have to enable, like when you're on Windows Server, you have to enable it to send performance counters.
So I'll give it a moment here.
It doesn't take too long.
While that's going, we should look to see if we actually have the settings set up here, the diagnostic settings.
And so this is what I'm talking about, the enable guest level monitoring.
So we want CPU utilization, disk, and network.
So we'll go ahead and click that there.
And while that's going to go back here, and so this has now started up.
I don't know much about Windows servers, but I do know how to turn on, at least the last time I did, I know how to turn on the performance counter.
So see here it says online performance counters are not started.
So I can right click this and then just say start performance counters.
And that will have it start sending data over to our storage accounts.
assuming that this is enabled here.
So this is going to go ahead and install WAG into the Windows Server so it can send back metrics.
And so we've got a lot of things going on here, but let's go back to JetZia.
And I want to see now if I have any, if I can use logs now.
There we go.
So it's now connected to the workspace, so it knows where to send that data.
And you can pull up, when you go to logs, it'll show different types of default queries.
If you're in the actual group here, you'll have the same screen, but it'll show you across all possible resources.
So it's a little bit easier to figure out like useful queries for virtual machines when you do it through here.
And there's some ones, there's some that we can run right away.
So if we go over to the diagnostics,
We could or actually availability is a good example.
So heartbeats will tell you if the server is live.
So a server will have heartbeats.
So every whatever second or minute, it's going to say, hey, I'm still alive.
That's what a heartbeat is.
So we'll go ahead and run that.
And we'll give it a moment here.
I'm not sure why it's crying.
That doesn't work.
I'll just click off and try that again.
So go back to availability.
We'll hit run.
And it has the right scope.
If you're wondering how it knows what to check, that's all based on scope there.
And for whatever reason, it just decides that it doesn't really want to run right now.
That's a bit frustrating.
But if it's not working for this one, we can always check our other one, which is curzon.
And we can go see if this one works.
That's why I made multiple servers, because I knew one of these might not work right away.
So we'll go ahead and run this one here.
It says no logs are configured.
So that makes me think that our workspace here, if we go back over to here and we go down to virtual machines, that they're actually not linked.
Oh, they still are connecting.
There you go.
So it's a bit misleading.
It looked like we could query, but we still can't.
Let's go take a look at this virtual machine here, our Lila one still.
Now let's see if we can do anything with it yet.
So if we go down to
Diagnostic settings.
It looks like it's installed.
And so if we go to performance counters, these are the counters that it should be collecting data on.
You could do custom if you want and change those values, but we're just going to leave it basic for the time being.
Go ahead and save that.
And I believe we can do logs over here on this one.
So we'll go over to availability.
I'm going to load that into the editor this time instead of hitting run.
I can hit run.
And it will return and says that it has a count of seven.
So 7 heartbeats, that's good.
If you want to create rules, you could easily do that.
There's actually some nice ones here.
If we go into here, this won't work unless our metrics are working, our guess metrics.
But there's a bunch down below here.
I'm just trying to see one that might be interesting for us to set.
So you might go here and
I don't think I like that one.
Say this one here, I'm just gonna clear this all the way out.
Oops.
So here, they even say to create this alert, just hit the plus new button here.
So we go here.
And sometimes it does this, it doesn't actually bring it over, which is weird.
So you have to go back.
I told you like this, the UI for Azure is super, super buggy.
So if you don't have any confidence, don't worry, it happens to all of us.
So we'll go back to our alerts, and I'm going to load that into the editor.
And what I'm going to do is just copy it.
And we're going to go ahead and hit run.
And so here we're getting some data back.
I think it's going to complain about the time generated.
But if we go and create a new alert, oh, man, it just does not want to copy anything over.
And so it's like I can't even paste.
We'll go back to here.
I'm going to copy this.
I noticed it was because I had it double clicked.
Maybe it just creates one that you have selected.
And so it should complain about this, but it's not.
So that's great.
And so we can go here and we can put a threshold to five.
Just put in any value here and that gives you a monthly cost for that alert.
So you hit review and create.
Please correct the following details.
Where?
Oh, the alert name.
Okay, my alert.
And we will hit review and create.
We'll hit create.
And so there we can create an alert.
So we can create an alert like our memory is running out of stuff, and those are kind of useful things to do.
So talking about metrics, we're going to make our way over here.
And notice we have host metrics and guest metrics.
So host metrics are general ones that are available to us, and guest metrics are memory and stuff like that.
So if we have that,
You're going to notice now we have disk and memory and things like that.
If we didn't have that installed, we wouldn't be able to access this information.
So what I can do is go ahead here and try disk time.
I don't know if it'll show us anything right now because it might have not collected enough information.
Go over to a virtual host.
We'll have different metrics here.
So a standard one would be like CPU usage.
Okay, so that one is displaying there.
The poor performance metrics always take a little bit more time to collect.
So I'm not sure if I'll stick around to show you that.
But if we go over to availability, sometimes when you need to go debug performance, like you can hit run.
And this will tell you if it's actually collecting information.
So see right now, it shows me nothing.
So it hasn't collected anything for process, memory, or processor.
But if it did, then we could go and use these other ones down below here.
So we have free disk space.
So that's a really useful one to have, which we can't get metrics on that right now.
But that's what we've been trying to do is collect that information.
So let's go back to our workspace.
And what I'm going to do is take a look at our virtual machines that are connected.
And this one has an error.
And that's Kurzon.
And I'm not surprised because, again, it's a minimal Windows Linux instance, so probably couldn't install the agent.
So that's expected.
But I just wanted to show you that edge case.
If we go into the JetZero one, which is the one we were waiting for this entire time, we should hopefully be able to see some metrics.
So if we go down here and we choose guess metrics, I want something with memory here, like percentage.
Okay, so it's still not showing me anything, and that's fine.
If we're not getting any metrics, what we can do is we can go log into this instance and give it some data so that it does something, all right?
So what I'll do is go all the way up to the top here into my overview.
I'm going to copy this public IP address.
We're going to open up our cloud shell and make sure that it's in Bash, all right?
And we're going to type in SSH, DAX,
And then we're going to paste the IP address in.
We'll hit enter.
We'll say yes.
And the password is testing123456 with a capital T.
And what we can do here is we can install a tool called StressNG.
What that tool does is it will help us do stress testing.
And so that allows us to make some metrics.
So we'll go ahead and install that via Snap.
Snap is the new package manager for Ubuntu.
It used to be apt-get or apt.
And it doesn't take too long to install.
And while it's installing, I actually have a pre-made line here to check the memory or to fill up the memory.
I'm just going to go ahead and paste this line in.
So this is stress-ng VM bytes and it uses awk and it's going to do memory availability and it's going to fill it up to 90%.
So we want to have 90% memory usage.
I'm going to go hit enter.
I'm just going to let that run.
Now it's not outputting anything, but it definitely is running.
There we go.
And so we're just going to leave it there.
And so soon enough we should have some information.
And I think if I go there, yeah, it's still there.
So it's fine.
So now if we go over to down to our logs and we go back to
performance, and we just choose this one here.
We might see something now.
Again, it takes time.
See, now it looks in the 15-minute window here.
But I just want to see that it's collecting anything.
For me, it doesn't matter what it collects, just collects something for me, you know?
So I think it'll just take a little bit of time.
While we're doing that, we should make our way back over to our workspace because there's some other settings that are kind of interesting that I noticed.
If you go over to agent configuration, you can collect additional information over here.
So we have performance counters for Windows and Linux.
I think we have to set the memory one here if we want it to actually appear here.
So I don't know if there's a way to set all of them, but I'm going to just choose some here.
So I'm going to do memory used.
We'll do logical use space here.
We'll go here and do free space.
I think that might be the reason why it's not showing up for us.
Maybe process time here.
We did use memory, percentage of use space.
We will do reads and writes.
So here we have some for our Linux.
So I think if we set that, then we should be able to see some information.
Syslogs is just a type of logs that you can collect.
We're not going to look into those today.
But yeah, that's the management there.
We could also try setting some here, maybe one for memory.
I can't remember what the one for memory is called here because they do all of this kind of stuff.
Like Windows has so much stuff, I can't make sense of it.
I think we might want paged owls.
And page.
So when called there, bytes.
We'll give that a go.
And we'll see if that starts collecting information.
I'm going to go back over to here.
And oh, this is Kurzon.
That's the Windows machine.
We're going to go to the Linux machine here.
And we'll give it another go.
So we get anything this time around.
So we'll go back to performance.
We'll say what is being collected run.
Okay.
And so I think we're just going to have to wait a little bit.
So I'm just going to stop the video here and I'll see you back in maybe 1520 minutes.
Okay.
All right, so I'm still waiting here and I don't seem to be seeing any data, but that's okay because there's another way we can kind of approximate this and we don't have to wait forever, especially if you don't have a lot of time like me.
The thing is that Azure has a log analytics tutorial and within here, they have a demo environment that I'm very familiar with.
And so this can approximate exactly what I'm trying to show you here.
If you notice at the top here, it says Microsoft Azure Monitoring Logs Demo Log Blade.
So if we go to queries and we go down to virtual machines and we look at what data is being collected, we can hit run here.
And this is the kind of information we are trying to see, right?
This is what we want to see what it's actually collecting.
And that's okay.
We're not doing remote desktop anymore here.
And if we go to virtual memory available, we'll just clear that out there and run that.
This is kind of the information we're trying to find.
All right.
So I just wanted to show you that when you collect those metrics that you can run these queries.
And this is that language up there with Kusto.
And that's pretty much it.
That's all I really wanted to show you.
So let's go ahead and tear down all our stuff.
It's all self-contained within a resource group.
So what we can do is go to all resources in the top left corner there.
And we called it DAX.
So we can search for DAX here.
Whoops.
Actually, it's all over the place, we just click here into the name.
And we'll hit Delete resource group.
Type in DAX, have a lot of resources created for this one.
And there you go.
So yeah, hopefully that helps you understand those relationships between automation accounts where we can run runbooks, do patching, you know, stuff like that, install Python stuff.
You know, the fact that
Log analytics is basically a data lake for all your data, that you can create alerts, that you have metrics, you have guest OS metrics which collect those three values, the memory, the network, and the additional CPU information or disk space, and just the variance there so you don't get stuck.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are looking at virtual machines for Azure Cheat Sheets.
So let's jump into it.
So Azure Virtual Machines allows you to create Linux and Windows virtual machines.
The size of the virtual machine is determined by the image.
The image defines the combination of VPCUs, memory, storage capacity.
The current limit on a prescription is 20 VMs per region.
VMs are billed at an hourly rate.
A single instance VM has an availability of 99.9% when all storage disks are premium.
Two instances deployed into availability set will give you 99.9%
availability.
You can attach multiple managed disks to an Azure VM.
When you launch an Azure Virtual Machine, other networking components will be either created or associated to your virtual machine, such as NSGs, interface cards, IPs, and VNet.
You can bring your own Linux by creating your own virtual hard disk.
Azure VM comes with a variety of sizes that are also optimized for specific use cases, and there's a lot of different ones here, so it's not super important, but I mean you should know the broad categories here.
Azure Compute Unit (ACU) provides a way of comparing CPU performance across Azure SKUs, and the standard one they're all benchmarked against is Standard A1.
All other SKUs.
then represent approximately how fast, faster the SKU can run on the standard benchmark.
You can install the Azure mobile app so you can monitor your VMs on the go.
Hyper-V is Microsoft's hardware virtualization product.
It lets you create and run software versions of a computer called virtual machines.
That's how it all works.
There are two types, or two generations of Hyper-VM.
You got generation one, which works with most operating systems, and generation 2 that supports most 64-bit versions of Windows and current.
Versions of Linux and FreeBSC operating systems, Hyper-V VMs are packaged into virtual hard disk formats such as VHD, VHDX files, not on the exam, but just understand that Hyper-VM generations are different from the Azure Hyper-VM generation, so it doesn't have all the features of Hyper-VM.
Okay, there are three ways to connect to virtual machines.
versus via secure shell.
It's not sure shell, it's secure shell.
But yeah, so that'll have to get fixed at some point.
SSH happens on port 22, and RSA key pairs are commonly used for authorized access.
Then you have RDP, which is a graphical interface to connect to another computer over the network connection.
This is how you can remotely connect to the Windows Server via virtual desktop.
This happens on port 3389 on TCP and UDP.
Now, I mark these
red because I want you to remember these two, so make sure them, okay?
Azure Bastions, and we'll clear that because now it's getting a bit of a mess here.
There we go.
So Azure Bastion, a service you can deploy, lets you connect to a virtual machine using your browser and Azure portal, supports both SSH and RDP, useful when you only have a browser like a Chromebook or do not have permission to configure or install software.
Then you have update management.
This allows you to manage and install operating system updates and patches for both Windows and Linux
Virtual machines that are deployed in Azure on-premise or in other cloud providers.
Update management will perform a scan or update compliance.
A compliance scan by default is performed every 12 hours on a Windows and three hours on a Linux machine that can take between 30 minutes and six hours for the dashboard to display updated data from the managed computer.
So there you go, that is the Virtual Machines Cheat Sheet.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from ExamPro, and welcome to Azure Disks, a virtual hard drive in the cloud.
So, it's block-level storage volumes for SSD or HDD.
So, Azure Managed Disks, also known as just Azure Disks, are block-level storage volumes that are managed by Azure and used.
By Azure VMs, and these disks are just like physical disks, but they're virtualized, and all you have to do is choose the size, type, and configuration, and you don't have to worry about any of the underlying hardware.
So, managed disks are designed for 99.999% availability.
Azure creates 3 replicas of your data, allowing for high durability.
You can create up to 50 VM disks in a single subscription per region, allowing you to create up to 1,000 virtual machines in a scale set using the marketplace image.
And honestly, the max amount that you can have in a scale set is 1,000 image, so I think that's a good number.
Managed disks are integrated with availability sets.
Managed disks support availability zones.
Azure Backup can be used to create backup jobs with time-based backups and backup retention policies.
And you can use RBAC to assign specific permissions for a managed disk for one or more users.
You can directly import your VHDs into Azure disks.
And you can use the Azure private links to ensure traffic between your disks and your VMs stay within the Microsoft network.
Now taking a look at encryption for our disks, we have two types of encryptions.
We have server-side encryption and Azure Disk Encryption.
And so for server-side encryption, SSE, this provides encryption at rest and safeguards your data to meet your organizational security compliance commitments and enabled by default for all managed disk snapshots and images.
But just so you know, temporary disks are not encrypted by server-side encryption unless you enable encryption at the host
Layer keys can be managed in two ways: so you have platform-managed keys, these are managed by Azure, or customer-managed keys, where you are managing the keys.
So now, for the second type of encryption, we have Azure Disk Encryption (ADE), and this allows you to encrypt the OS and data disks used by IaaS virtual machines.
It's weird than they do that in the documentation.
They just mean virtual machines that are running on Azure.
They have it prefixed with IaaS there.
For Windows encryption, it's done with BitLocker.
For Linux encryption, it's done with DMcrypt.
So let's take a look at disk roles, and there are three types for Azure.
We have data disk, OS disk, and temporary disk, and it's possible to see all these roles if you were to spin up a Windows 10 Pro server, went into remote access, and looked at the disk management, and so that is our drives that are attached to this.
Virtual machine, and we have the OS disk, the temporary disk, and the data disk.
If you're wondering what those three things are, that's what we're going to talk about now.
So, the data disk is a managed disk that's attached to the virtual machine to store application data and other data you need to keep.
It's registered as an SCSI drive.
I think that's pronounced SCSI, and are labeled with a letter that you choose, has a maximum capacity of 32 gigabytes, and the size of the VM determines how many data disks you can attach and the type of storage you can use.
Moving on to OS disk, every virtual machine has one attached operating system disk.
The OS disk has pre-installed OS, which was selected with the VM that was created.
The disk contains the boot volume.
The disk has a maximum capacity of 4 gigabytes.
Then onto our temporary disk.
This is the most VMs contain a temporary disk, which is not a
Managed disk provides short-term storage for applications and processing, and is intended to store data such as page or swap files.
Data on the temporary disk may be lost during a maintenance event or when redeployed to a VM.
During successful standard reboot of the VM, data on the temporary disk will persist.
The temporary disk is typically mounted on dev SBD on Linux, and on Windows, the temporary disk is generally
Assigned to the D drive, and for these disks, they're not encrypted with SE, unless you enable encryption at the host level.
Let's take a look at managed disk snapshots and manage custom images, which are very similar.
So a managed disk snapshot is a read-only, crash-consistent full copy of a managed disk that is stored as a standard disk by default.
Snapshots are point-in-time recovery.
Snapshots exist independent of the source disk and can be used to create a managed disk.
Snapshots are billed based on the used size.
So if you have 24 gigabytes and you only use 10, you're only going to be billed for those 10 gigabytes.
You can see the used size of your snapshot by looking in the Azure user report.
ports.
And then we have managed custom images, which seem very similar, but have a very distinct difference.
They allow you to create an image of your disk from your VM.
And this image contains all the managed disks associated with a VM, including the OS and disk data disks.
So just comparing it to a snapshot, it isn't aware of any disk except the one it contains.
And this makes it problematic in the use
or the scenario that requires coordination of multiple disks such as striping.
So snapshots would need to be able to coordinate with each other, and this is currently not supported.
So that's where you want to use a managed custom image.
So if you're looking to just make a copy of one of your disks, like let's say your data disk, then go ahead with snapshots.
If you need to have all of them, then you're going to be using a managed custom image.
So when you create an Azure disk, you're going to actually have to choose from one of the four tiers of your disk.
And depending on what you choose, one's going to be more expensive or one's going to be faster.
So let's go take a look at the four tiers.
So the first being Ultra Disk.
So these deliver high throughput, high IOPS, and consistently low latency disk storage for Azure VMs.
They dynamically change the performance of the disk without the need to restart your VM.
A really great feature suited for data intensive workloads such as SAP HANA, top tier databases, and transaction heavy workloads.
Can only be used as data disks.
So generally when you're using Ultra Disk, it's recommended that you use a premium SSD as the OS disk, only supported with very specific VM series.
So you're going to have to look at your virtual machine to see if you're allowed to use that disk.
For premium SSDs, they're high performance, low latency disk support for Azure VMs, for input output intensive workloads, suitable for mission critical workload applications, only to be used with the VM series that are premium storage compatible, guaranteed IOPS,
And throughput of that disk, so the standard tiers don't have a guarantee of IOPS.
If you need a guarantee of IOPS, you're using premium SSD designed to provide low single-digit millisecond latency and target IOPS throughput described in the preceding table, and so I have a diagram coming up on that, but the point is that premium SSD is generally what...
Azure is going to recommend to you, but in practice, you're probably going to be using standard SSD.
So cost-effective storage option optimized for workloads that need consistent performance and lower IOPS levels compared to standard HDDs and standard SSDs delivers better availability, consistency, reliability, and latency.
Suitable for web servers, low IOPS application servers, lightly used enterprise applications, dev test workloads, designed to provide single-digit millisecond latencies and the IOPS and throughputs up to the limits described in the preceding table.
That table
coming up.
IOPS and throughput may vary sometimes depending on the traffic patterns available for all Azure VMs.
Then you have standard HDD.
This is the lowest cost tier here, and it's still reliable, but it's for running latency insensitive workloads available for all VMs.
So latency IOPS throughput of standard HDD is going to vary, and that's the whole point we're trading costs for.
variability here.
Designed to deliver write latency under 10 milliseconds and read latency is under 20 seconds for most IOP operations.
Available in all Azure regions and can be used with all Azure VMs.
And so here is that diagram.
And just taking a look here, you can notice, look at the IOPS.
So here it's 2,000, 6,000, 20,000, 160,000.
This is the one I generally want you to remember.
If you're going to remember any IOPS, just remember premium SSD starts at 20K.
And then the maximum throughput, we got 500 megabytes per second, 750, 900, and 2000, which is pretty darn fast.
Notice the K here, that stands for thousands.
So you can have a max disk size of 32,700 something gigabytes, and it's across the board the same.
This one's at 65,000.
And then just from a feature standard here, we have backup, non-critical, infrequent access, light use, dev and test. If you're a small startup, this is what you're going to be using. Heavy use, production, guarantee, IOPS. If you're a very well-established company, this is what you're going to be using. IO intensive, top-tier databases, heavy workloads. This is for very special use cases. So there you go. Let's talk about bursting. And this is a concept for both virtual machines and storage.
And so it all has to do with performance. Okay? So disk bursting is going to boost the disk storage for IOPS and megabytes per second for a period of time for your disks. And then bursting for VMs are going to boost the performance of CPU utilization and what have you there. Bursting allows you to handle unexpected disk traffic. This allows you to get more out of your disk and avoid permanently upgrading to a more performant disk. Okay? And bursting on disks and VMs are independent from one another. So if you have a bursting disk, you don't necessarily need
a bursting VM, but you might want to pair them together based on what your use case is. For burstable VMs, you have to use particular types of VMs that support it, so the VSV2 series, the DS3 series, and the ESV3 series. And just so you know, if you do spin up a virtual machine that has bursting, it's enabled by default, and it's what you want. Then for burstable disks,
For premium SSDs, for disk sizes of P20 and smaller, it's for all regions. And bursting is enabled by default for disks that support it. So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from ExamPrev. And in this follow along, we're going to learn a bit more about Azure disks. So I think it'd be a good idea for us to actually go manually attach one and do a few things with the disk there. So what I want you to do is make your way all the way over the top here. And we're going to launch ourselves a new virtual machine. So go ahead and add a virtual machine here. And for this one, I'm going to name the resource group. If I don't have one, we'll say, I'll call it, not fax, we'll call it DAX. And I'll name the machine DAX as well.
And down below, we're going to want to launch an Ubuntu server. So make sure you choose the 18 LTS generation 2. And then for sizes, let's make sure we have B1 LS, because that will be cost effective at $5.83 if you forget to turn off that machine. For the username, we'll do Azure user. And for the password, we'll do capital T testing 123456, capital T testing 123456. And we don't need any ports open except for
22 because we will be SSH into this machine today. Now we can attach a disk here, but I want to attach one after the fact. And we're going to stick with premium SSD because that seems okay to me. And we'll go ahead and go to review and create and we'll go and create this virtual machine. And we'll give it a second here. So we hit the Create button. And I'll see you back here once this is finished creating. So I'll see you back here in a bit. Okay.
So now that our deploy has succeeded here, I'm going to go ahead and go to that resource. And on the left-hand side, we'll go to disks. And we'll go attach ourselves a new disk. I want just some kind of additional disk here. So my second disk. And here, I'm going to just use a standard SSD. We don't need premium there. It's not a big deal. And when we're happy with that, we're going to go ahead and hit save. I'm going to wait for that disk to create. And once that's done, we'll go ahead and SSH into
This here looks like it actually is already done. It's updating the virtual machine, so what I'm going to do is make my way back to it. I'm going to go, oops, we don't want to discard any changes there, but we'll go and hit. I don't think it will, but I'll go make a new tab here just because I don't trust it, and we will go back to DAX to the virtual machine here.
And we will need to go ahead and grab that public IP address and then get into this machine. So I'll go ahead and open up my cloud shell. It might ask you to create storage depending on, you know, if it's the first time you've done this before. But now that we're in here, I'm going to type in SSH and we're going to type in Azure user at sign and we will paste in that IP address, the public IP address there. And we'll go ahead and hit enter. We'll say yes. And then capital T testing 123456. And then we should get into our machine here. And we are in.
typing clear to clear my screen. And so what we'll want to do is partition that disk. Just because the disk is there doesn't mean we necessarily can use it until it's partitioned. So what we're going to do is use the parted command. So there's man parted. That's one command we're going to be using today. That's going to be for partitioning. And the other one will be man mount. That will be actually mounting it so we can use it. And if you go into man, you type that, just hit Q to get out. I guess I didn't tell you that.
But in order to partition it, we're going to be typing sudo parted and then the name of the disk we want, so SDC. So if you're wondering what this is, so the thing is that this is a standard naming convention for the mount point or the mounting name or whatever we call this thing here. But dev stands for device, and then SD stands for, it used to stand for SCSI, but now it's just, that's what you always put when you're naming it. And then this is followed by a letter, so it could be A, B, C, D, and that is the order of it.
It will have a number afterwards sometimes, so like one, two, three for partitions, I believe. So what we'll do is go ahead here and then type in hyphen, hyphen script, MK label. And this is not important for you to remember. It's just that we need to go through these motions here because honestly, every time I do this, I look it up. And actually off screen, I have this here. So don't think I have this memorized because I definitely don't. But what it's going to say is partition this entire, like allocate the entire drive for partitioning.
And so I'm just going to double check to make sure I spelled this all right. So I don't feel embarrassed if I hit enter and it doesn't work here. So just double checking. And it looks all pretty good to me. And we can't use B because B is reserved. Something's already using it. So we'll go ahead and hit enter. And so now that's been parted there. And we'll have to run a couple more commands here to be able to write to the file system. So we'll type in sudo mkfs xfs dev forward slash sdc1. Okay.
And we'll hit Enter. And so that is all now good. And we'll do the same thing. I'm hitting up, and then we're gonna have to do a part probe on it. Again, not a big deal to know these things off the top of your head. But if you're curious, I think you could type in man on that as part probe. And so it'll tell you what the info informed the OS partition, the tables have changed. So there's that. And then for the other one, which is MKFS.
right? Build a Linux file system. So we've made a partition, we built a Linux file system, and then we informed the OS of the change table updates. Okay. So once that is done, now we need to mount it. So we're going to type in sudo make directory, MKDIR, which means make directory. We can type... This is a very basic Linux command. It's making a folder basically. And we can name this whatever we want. So since this is DAX, I'm going to go forward slash DAX for fun.
And then I'm going to do ampersand ampersand. Now we could use, and I know I typed facts by accident, we could do semicolon, but it's better to use double ampersand because it means that both of these commands need to succeed to proceed. Or sorry, the second command will not proceed unless the first one happens, where if you use a semicolon, it won't do that in Linux, if you didn't know that. So we're going to type in sudo dev. I'm going to type in forward slash dev here, sdc1.
And then we'll type in DAX, and so that should mount it. Whoops, so there was a bug there. This is supposed to be pseudo. That should mount it to there, and so if we go to our next command here...
So, we want to use df just to do some reading here, so report a file system disk usage space. This is a great way to see if our disk is there, so we'll do -h grep, and we're going to look for sd, right, because that's what they're all basically named, okay?
And so there we can see our drive and we can see how much is actually being used. So that is a good way there. And I think if we just type in DAX, we can actually just start writing stuff here. So I can say touch. That just means make an empty file. So touch hello.txt, right? We don't have permission. So if I type maybe sudo.
we do PWD, and then maybe LS. So I've just written to that disk there. Now, just because we've created a mount disk, if we restarted the machine doesn't mean it would mount again. So there's a little bit of work, we need to do that. So what we can do is use, I think we have to add something to etc. F stab. And so we're gonna have to get a bit of information about the disk, like such as the UID. So what I want you to do is type in sudo hyphen I. Okay. And
I will type in, I stands for interactive, by the way. If we type in ML, again, I keep on showing you man if you ever want to find out what these things are. But if you type, this is locate print block device attributes. And you can read this if you want to see more information. I'm hitting up and down. I want to leave this at Q. But what we can do is enter interactive mode for you via pseudo. That's the I stands for BLKID. And so we're looking for the output of our SDC1. OK, so
For SDC1, it's down here. So what I'm going to do is copy the whole line. We probably don't need the whole thing. I'm going to copy it. And I have off-screen Visual Studio Code, so I'm just pasting that in there. So you just have to paste it somewhere in a text editor so we do not lose that. And what we'll do is proceed to update the fstab file. I'm going to type in sudo, etc. fstab here.
And I haven't had one of these in a long time, so hopefully I get this right. Oh, sorry. So we want a VI in between there. You can use Nano. I really don't like Nano. I prefer VI. But if with VI you have to, or Vim, you have to be very careful. So with Vim, the idea is H, J, K, L, or map to your movements. But if we just hit I, then the keyboard works normal, okay? And see, it says insert down below. And so notice that we have these other values. Whoops, I got to be really careful here.
But notice, I wasn't using the arrows, but notice we have some other things here. So what we want to do is go ahead and add our own here. So we'll hit, oops, I want to go below here, hit enter. And so we want the UUID of the one we have. So I'm going to do UUID equals. And what I'm going to do, hold on just a moment. File, new. I just want to show you the actual thing I copied out here.
Okay, just a moment. So here's mine, right? So I'm just going to have to copy that on over. So I'm just going to maybe park it halfway on the screen here so we can see what we're doing. And so I need this value here. I'm just looking at what's already there, right, to match it. And we'll go copy. And I should be able to do paste here. And then just double check to make sure nothing's cut off. So 4, 4, good, 00. So that looks good to me.
So there's that. And then we need to put the, I think, the mount point. So yeah, because it says, yeah, I'm pretty sure that's what it is. So we'll type in forward slash, we called ours DAX, and then we're going to put XFS, oops, XFS. And then we need a space, and we're going to type defaults, comma,
no fail one and two. All right. And so now that we have that all set up, I think we're all good to go. So I'm just going to go and save this. So see how it says insert, I'm going to hit Escape key, that brings me back into normal mode. And then I type the I'm going to type a colon, notice it comes down here into the command, I'm gonna type W and Q and quit. All right. So
that's pretty much it. So now our drive is mounted and we can write to it however we like. And so, that's good here. So what we'll do is just go ahead and close Cloud Shell and maybe what we'll do is, I don't know, maybe like back up this disk here. Okay, yeah, so let's go ahead and actually do a backup. So on the left-hand side, we'll go to disks. And if you're just confused where we are, what we can do is even go to disks, I think, ourselves, and we'll see our disks. And I can go to my second one here.
And then from in here, I can go ahead and create myself a snapshot. So we'll go ahead and hit a snapshot. And we'll just say my disk backup. And we have two options here. We can create a full, a read-only copy of the selected disk, or we can do incremental, which will save us space. I don't think we need to do incremental today. We can do a full disk for fun. And we'll hit review. Oh, we missed some basic information here.
Storage type, we will put it into standard HHD, and we'll go ahead and go back and hit review and go create, and that's going into our DAX there, and so we'll just wait until that's done.
Great. So now that we learned how to create a snapshot, how about we go ahead and actually attach a disk to a Windows machine? Because the process is slightly different. It doesn't hurt to go through the process twice here, so you can experience the differences. So we'll go ahead and create a new virtual machine here, put it in our DAX. We'll call this DAX Windows. And we'll choose a different image here. And probably a Windows server is probably ideal. So we'll go drop this down.
I think I will go with the 2019 generation 2. B1LS is not sufficient, I believe. I can't remember. I think that we need a B2S because 2 and 4. I think that will be enough. If it doesn't like it, will tell us. And so we need to create administrator users. I'm going to type in Azure user. And then for the password, capital T, testing123456. Capital T, testing123456.
And we won't allow RDP there. We'll go next to disks. We're not going to attach one right off the bat. We're going to stick with premium and we'll hit review and create. And so we'll go ahead and create this Windows machine. And I know it's a bit more expensive than Linux machine, but do not worry, we will not keep it around for too long. And we'll just wait here for just a moment to make sure that it's in progress. And I'll see you back here in a moment.
All right, so now that our Windows Server has been created, let's go to that resource, make our way over to disks, and we're going to be doing the same story here, so I think that we can kind of attach any kind of drive we want here. I don't think it matters, so I'm going to say, My Windows Disk, and...
Yeah, I'll have a premium this time. Who cares? Why not? And so we'll just wait for that to create. And then it shouldn't take too long. It's going to update the virtual machine. And then what we'll want to do is RDP into this instance. So on the left-hand side, I never trusted if I cancel that. I feel like it's going to mess up my settings there, but I don't think so. We'll go to data, DAX Windows, and on the left-hand side, go to Connect, and we will do RDP, download the file. If you
don't have the client, you'll have to install it for Mac. On Windows, it generally is, I think, pre-installed, unless you need Windows Professional. I'm not sure. But we'll type in Azure User, capital T, testing, 123456. Okay. Oops, I actually don't know if I typed that right. Let's reveal that if we can. It's not showing me the icon now, so I'll have to type it all over again. Capital T, 123456. We'll hit OK. And we'll say yes.
And so we'll just wait a moment here for this to start up, and I'll see you back here in a second. All right, so now that our Windows machine is ready here, what we'll do is make our way over to PowerShell. So just type in PowerShell, and we'll go here. I don't know if it matters. It's x68. Let's just go to the first one here. I don't use PowerShell too much, but I can make our way through it here no problem. And so what we're going to do is go ahead and partition it.
And luckily, I have the command off screen here, so you'll just have to follow along with me as soon as this ever decides to load, unless I can start typing. There we go. Okay, just give it a moment. There we go. And so we'll type in get-disk. I made the poor choice of hitting Tab. Don't hit Tab when you're in RDP. It just makes your life a lot harder. See, because then it autocompletes today.
So I was trying to autocomplete it to say disk so I don't make any spelling mistakes. And then we'll put, we'll make a pipe. We'll say partition style. And then we'll say if it equals, again, you don't have to have this memorized. It's just important that you go through the motions here with me. So you can say, yeah, I did this one time. And then we want initialize disk. I'm so tempted to hit hyphen to autocomplete, but I just do not trust it here. So I'm going to type it all each individually by hand. Then we need, we have partition.
partition style, so MBR, and we're going to say pass through. Okay, and then we'll put pipe again. We'll say new partition. I was hoping that it would wrap there. Okay, and we'll say assign drive letter, because we want it to have a letter, right? And then we'll say use maximum size, pipe format,
volume. We'll say file system, we probably could have done this in multiple commands. But I'm just making it easy and just following what we got here that I know works because I ran it earlier. And then we'll name it whatever we want. So you know, my new disk. And then we'll put in hyphen, confirm, false. Okay, so there's a lot there. And I already see a mistake. I think that's a mistake.
for initialize disk because it should be that. There we go. At least it colors it so we know. And so I think that looks all okay, I'm gonna go hit hit enter. And we will just wait here a little bit. Cannot be found that matches the file system label, there's clearly a spelling mistake. So we'll go here, label.
I'll probably give you the code, so you can just copy and paste it. And we're still having a bit of problems here. So I think what I'll do, I'm going to see if I can just copy and paste it in here. Oh, there we go. Okay. Yeah, so that's what I recommend you do as well. And so we'll verify if that disk is actually ready there. So I think we can write if we type in dot VM storage.
profile.data disks. Hit enter. We didn't get any output. So we should have got output there, and we didn't. So just give me a moment here, okay? All right, so I'm not sure why VM's not working. Normally, if you type in even dollar sign VM, it would give you an output, but there's another way that we could check. There's another way we could check if the drive's there. We just go up to the folder here. I just, it was a smart idea I had here.
And under the PC, it should just show up, right? So here we have a disk. I guess the disk is still not.
formatted.
So I guess we'll just format it this way.
Like this is just another way to format it, right?
So we'll go here.
We'll say quick format.
Okay.
Great.
And oops, yep, there we go.
So that's all done.
You know, but you know, sometimes I just find it easier to just use
This stuff we could have also done it through if we went to disk here, right?
We could have done it through here.
We could have we could have also partitioned it this way.
But I mean, this worked just as easily.
But you know, sometimes it's helpful to practice some PowerShell there.
So yeah, I think we're pretty much done here because now we've formatted both.
But yeah, let me just decide here if I want to try and doing a backup.
You know what, I decided maybe the backup should be a separate follow along here.
So we're all done here.
So we'll go ahead and close that RDP, and then make your way over to your resource groups here.
And what we'll do is make sure actually, it's easier if we just go to, I went to all resources, but we'll go here, and just go ahead and delete whatever you need to delete.
So if we go to DAX, and we say delete resource group, they'll delete all that stuff.
And I think that's good enough for disks, so there we go.
Hey, this is Angie Brown from Exam Pro, and we're looking at Azure Disks Cheat Sheet, and this one's a long one.
We've got 3 pages, so let's jump into it.
Azure Managed Disks are block-level storage volumes that are managed by Azure and used within Azure VMs.
Managed Disks are designed for ninety-nine.
999 availability, that's three nines.
Azure creates 3 replicas of your data, allowing for high durability.
You can create up to 50,000 VM disks of a type of subscription per region, allowing you to create up to 1,000 VMs in a virtual machine set using the marketplace image.
Managed disks are integrated with availability sets, and it also supports availability zones.
Azure Backup can be used to create a backup job with time-based backups and backup retention policies.
You can use role-based access controls to assign.
specific permissions for a managed disk to one or more users.
You can directly import your virtual hard disk drives into Azure disks.
You can use Azure Private Links to ensure traffic between Azure disks.
and VMs stay within the Microsoft network.
Azure managed disks support two types of encryption.
You got SSE by default and temporary disks are not encrypted by server-side encryption unless you enable encryption host.
So remember that exception, there are two types of keys that you can be managed, platform managed keys and customer managed keys.
Then you have Azure disk encryption, allows you to encrypt both the OS and data disks using an Azure virtual machine.
For Windows, you're going to be using BitLocker.
For Linux encryption, you're going to be using DMcrypt.
to our second slide here.
There are three main disks roles in Azure, the data disk, the OS disk, the temporary disks.
The data disk is a managed disk as attached to a virtual machine to store application data or other data you need to keep.
Registered SCSI drives are labeled with a letter that you choose, has a maximum of 32 gigabytes.
The size of the VM determines how many data disks you can attach and the type of storage you can use.
For the OS disk, every virtual machine has one attached operating system disk.
The OS disk has a pre-installed OS with
which was selected when the VM was created.
The disk contains the boot volume.
The disk has a maximum capacity of 4 gigabytes.
For temporary disks, most VMs contain a temporary disk, which is not a managed disk.
Provide short-term storage of applications and processes and intended to only store data such as page or swap files.
Data on the temporary disk may be lost during a maintenance event or when you deploy a VM.
During a successful standard reboot of the VM, data on the temporary disk will persist.
The temporary disk is typically forward slash dev forward slash
SDB on Linux.
And you know what?
I tried fixing this, and this is my second go on it, but I still got a spelling mistake.
We'll have to fix that, okay?
Just erase that off the board there.
And Windows VMs.
Windows VMs, the temporary disk is D by default.
Not encrypted by SSC unless you enable encryption at the host.
Going on to managed disk snapshots is a read-only, crash-consistent full copy of a managed disk that is stored as a standard managed disk by default.
Snapshots are point-in-time recovery.
Snapshots exist independent of the source disk and can be used to create new managed disks.
Snapshots are billed based on used size.
If you have a 64 GB drive and only 10 gigabytes, you're only billed to 10 gigabytes.
You can use size of your snapshot by looking you can see the size of your snapshot by looking within the Azure Usage Report.
Onto the last page here, for Azure Disks, a managed custom image can create an image of your disk from your VM, contains all managed disks associated with the VM, OS, and data disk.
Does all three, okay?
And so, oops, a snapshot doesn't have awareness of any disk except the one it contains.
For a single disk, and you definitely need to know this, for a single disk, managed disk snapshots.
For multiple disks, it's going to be managed custom disks.
Know the difference for your exam, okay?
Azure offers 4 tiers of disk.
We got ultra, premium SSD, standard SSD, and standard HDD.
For ultra disks, delivers high throughput, high IOPS, consistent low latency and disk storage in Azure VMs.
We have a bunch of details in between.
Read if you like.
Premium SSD, high performance and low latency disk support for Azure VMs with input output intensive workloads.
Again, some additional information there.
Standard SSD, cost-effective storage, optimized, option optimized for workloads that needs consistent performance at lower IOPS levels.
levels, and then that has a bit of details there.
And then we have standard HHD, reliable low-cost disk support for VMs running a latency insensitive workload, so available all VMs, et cetera, et cetera.
And there you go.
But just know the key concepts here that you want to know what these disks are for, okay?
So the main line there, all right?
So we're at the end there, and yeah, there you go.
So, Azure has a few different kinds of load balancers, and one in particular is the Application Gateway, and this is for application-level routing and load balancing service.
So, Application Gateway operates at the OSI Layer 7, which is also known as the Application Layer, and the idea here is that when you're working about applications, you're working with http://requests.
That's what it is.
And so the idea is that it can look at the contents of the HP request and do some interesting things.
So maybe it's looking at the path and saying, okay, if you have a path and it's payments, go to the VM that has our payment system.
And then if it's forward slash admin, go to the VM that does that.
Maybe it has to do something with cookies or maybe you want to apply a WAF policy to it.
And so you can look at those.
HTTP requests and determine if it is malicious traffic and filter it out.
So yeah, it's all about the application, which has to do with HTTP requests.
To configure this thing, you need to set up a front end, routing rules, and back end pools.
And there are two configurations for the front end.
You can either have it with a private IP, which makes it now an internal load balancer, or a public IP, which makes it either we would call a public or external load balancer.
And there's both.
I've never used that option before.
But I mean, you just really need to know the public and private.
For the backends, you create backend pools.
And A backend pool is just a collection of resources to which your application gateway sends traffic.
And so a backend pool can contain virtual machines, virtual machine scale sets, IP addresses, domain names, app service.
And I think you can also send it to like on-prem.
So let's just talk about routing rules, which connects the frontend and the backend together.
And so here is a more complex example.
It gives you a better idea of the service at full.
And so the idea is that you have your application gateway.
It's going to send traffic, or sorry, like your DNS is going to send it to application gateway.
And then you have these listeners, and they listen for incoming traffic.
And then what it will do, it will pass on that to a rule.
And a rule just really says, who should we pass the data to?
And then, if you are defining A back-end pool, then you need to have an HTTP setting that says, How do we handle the HTTP requests?
Okay, and so now we'll just look at more granular detail about requests or routing rules.
Let's take a closer look at routing rules.
This is where all the magic happens.
So A listener listens on a specified port and IP address for traffic that uses a specified protocol.
If the listener criteria are met, the application gateway will apply the routing rule.
And these come in two flavors.
We got basic, which forwards all requests for any domain to backend pools, and multi-site forward requests to different backend pools based on host header and host name.
So the thing is that you can have multiple listeners and you can have an order of them.
And the idea is that you really want the basic to be a
on the last in priority because if it's a first, it's going to capture everything because that's its job.
It's like a catch-all.
So just make sure that if you're using multiple listeners, you put basic last.
So that's just something you need to know.
Then for those back-end targets, this is where we either define a back-end pool or redirection.
Redirection is just an HTTP redirection like 403 or whatever.
You have their temporary or permanent, very simple.
But for back-end pools, you have to create HTTP settings.
And this tells us a little bit more about how we want to handle HTTP, cookies, connection training, port requests, et cetera.
Let's talk about it a little bit more.
So here are the actual options that we can configure for HTTP settings.
So you have your backend port.
So generally, it's either port 80 or 443.
It just depends on where you're doing your SSL termination.
But generally, if you need end-to-end encryption, it'll be 443 or...
And then if you're doing SSL termination at the load balancer, then it's 80.
Then you have cookie-based affinity.
This allows you to keep a user session on the same server.
So if you need to persist cookies and use them for authentication, you'll want to enable that.
You've got connection draining.
This gracefully removes back-end pool members during planned service updates.
So the idea is that when there is an update, it's not just going to abruptly cut over.
It's going to wait until a connection disconnects from a server before
no longer sending more requests there, because you don't want a connection dropping in the middle of an update.
It's not great for a user.
Then you have request timeouts.
This is the number of seconds the application gateway will wait to receive a response from the backend pool before it returns a connection timeout error message.
And last, oh, sorry, we still have override backend path.
These allow you to override the path in the URL, so the request for a specific path can be routed to another path.
The idea is, imagine you want to send it to bananas,
And you want bananas to actually internally route to oranges?
I don't know why you want to do that, or maybe to plantains that would make a lot more sense.
So, something you can do, and the last one is the override the host name.
So, Application Gateway normally leaves the host name alone, but if you're using multi-tenant services like apps.
Like App Service or API Management, it needs very specific host header set, so this is where you can override them and change them for those services.
So, hopefully, that really gives you a good picture of Application Gateway, but I feel that that's all you really need to know.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're looking at the Azure Application Gateway Cheat Sheet.
So Azure Application Gateway is an application-level routing and load balancing service, and it operates on the OSI Layer 7, also known as the application layer.
You can attach a WAF, and so that will give you additional security.
An application gateway is composed of a front-end, routing rules, and back-ends.
So front-ends, you'll choose an address type.
So you either want it to be a private IP or a public IP.
For backends, you'll create backend pools, and a backend pool can be a variety of different things, but a backend pool is a collection of resources to which your application gateway can send traffic, and there's that list.
You can make it a VM, VM scale set, IP address, domain name, or app service.
For routing rules, they're composed of listeners, back-end targets, and HTTP settings.
So A listener listens on a specific port and IP address for traffic that uses a specific protocol.
If the listener criteria is met, the application gateway will apply the routing rule.
There are two types of listeners, basic and multi-site.
Probably mostly likely going to be using basic, but if you do use multi-site, that's cool.
Requests are matched according to the order of the rules and the types of listeners.
Add your basic listeners last, otherwise it will capture all requests.
For back-end targets, choose where a route should either go to a back-end pool or a redirection.
To create a rule for back-end pool, you need to create the HTTP setting or settings.
The S is missing on there.
To find how we want to handle cookies, connections, draining, port requests, timeout, and more.
That's for the HTTP settings.
So there you go.
So let's take a look here at Azure scale sets.
And these are used to automatically increase or decrease your virtual machine capacity.
So imagine you have a web application behind an application load balancer, and you have an increase in traffic.
You want to be able to quickly add more capacity by adding another identical virtual machine.
Or when there's a decrease in traffic, remove it to save costs.
And that is what Azure scale sets do.
So you're creating scale policies to automatically add or remove based on host metrics.
Host metrics could be like CPU utilization or network in.
You're going to create health checks.
And you can also set a repair policy to replace unhealthy instances.
You can associate a load balancer to distribute virtual machines across availability zones.
And you can scale to 100 or even 1,000 VMs using scale sets.
So one thing you're going to probably want to do with your scale set is associate with a load balancer.
And in honesty, I don't run any kind of application workload unless it is in a scale set and behind a load balancer because it's just good practice to do that.
And the reason why you're going to want a load balancer is that it's going to help you evenly distribute your VMs across multiple availability zones.
And that's going to give you high availability because you definitely want to try to run
3 VMs across 3 AZs to get that high availability.
You can also use a load balancer probe checks, and these are more robust health checks than what skill set provides you.
So that is just an added benefit there.
And when we're talking about load balancers, we have two different choices here.
We have the application gateway, and so this is for HTTP, HTTPS, web traffic load balancer.
And then you also have Azure Load Balancer, and this is going to support TCP and UDP network traffic and things like that.
So, depending on what OSI layer you need to operate on, it's going to determine what kind of load balancer you need to use.
So, let's take a look at scaling policies, and these determine when a virtual machine should be added or removed to meet the current requirements, and you have this.
little wizard here, this is what the wizard you see or form you see when you're creating a scale set initially with very simple features.
But let's just focus on two things, scaling out and scaling in.
So scaling out is when an instance should be added to a scale set to increase capacity.
So you choose your metric, which is hard coded in this case, to CPU threshold.
So you choose your metric, the duration, how many VMs you want to add.
And then the scale in is the opposite.
That's when you're removing.
something from the scale set to decrease your capacity.
And again, that interface is very simple.
When you actually go ahead and create a scale set, after you go and update it, you're going to end up with a lot more options.
And here are the options.
You can see they're extremely robust.
And so you have the option to choose one of the built-in host metrics that are already being collected on your virtual machine.
So the most popular here, and there's more than this, but
The most popular here is CPU, network in, network out, disk read, and write.
Then you have your aggregates, so you can decide how you want to group or collect that data before you apply your final operations on it.
Then you have your operators, so you can say greater than or greater than or equal to.
Then you have your actions.
You can say increase the count, so add X amount of servers, or you can say increase by percentage.
So imagine you had
10 servers and you want to increase the load by 30%, that would add three additional servers.
If you want more metrics than just the built-in host metrics, you can absolutely get more, but you're going to have to install a couple things.
For app, if you want more app-specific metrics like page performance or page load performance and session scout, you would install a small instrumentation package for App Insights, and if you want to have more detailed host metrics, so you might have host metrics, but you want them in more detail or more available host metrics, you'd install the Azure Diagnostic Extension within your VM.
There are a few other scaling policy options that are, well, they're not exactly in that form, but they are around or are associated with them.
One is the scale-in policy, not to be confused with the scale-in option.
And this determines what virtual machine should be removed when you decrease capacity.
So it's just a simple drop-down, and you have a few different options.
So there's the default option.
This is where it deletes the VM with the highest instance ID, and it's going to do that, taking consideration the balancing across AZs and ADs.
Or it can delete the newest virtual machine, so delete the newest VM.
Again, this one's only across availability zones, or delete the oldest VM.
This is going to delete the oldest VM and balance across availability zones.
Then you have an update policy.
And this determines how VM instances are brought up to date with the latest scale set model.
So again, it's another drop down and you have a few options here.
So you have automatic, so increasing the start upgrade immediately in random over order or manual.
So existing instances must be manually upgraded or rolling.
And so this update upgrades roll out in.
in batches with optional pause.
And just one other note here is that if you want to do automatic OS upgrades, you can enable this to help ease update management by safely and automatically upgrading the OS disk for all instances.
So there you go.
Health monitoring is a feature with skill sets you're absolutely going to want to turn on.
And what it does is it determines whether your instance, your virtual machine instance, is healthy or unhealthy.
So you have that option to disable or enable it.
comes in two different modes.
We're going to have the application health extension, which is what we're seeing on the right-hand side here.
And this is where you ping an HTTP or HTTPS request with a specific path.
and expect back a specific status.
So the status here would be 200.
So the idea is that you could say ping the home page, and if the home page appears, then therefore the server must be healthy.
Or you can make it your own custom page.
That's what I like to do.
I have like a health check page.
The other mode is load balancer probe.
This is only going to work if you have an associated load balancer.
And here you can check based on TCP, UDP, HTTP requests.
So this is a little bit more robust.
So I generally would recommend using this mode over the first mode, because generally when you have a scale set, you're going to also want to have a load balancer.
Now, if you want to replace unhealthy instances, they have an automatic repair policy.
So this isn't automatic.
I mean, like it's not turned on by default, so you have to explicitly say you want to turn it on.
And what that will do is that if it finds an instance that is unhealthy, it's just going to terminate it and then launch a new instance.
All right, and so there you go.
So here we just have a few remaining features I want to talk about with scale sets.
And these are more advanced features, but they're good to know.
So let's talk about an allocation policy.
And by default, your scaling sets are limited to 100 instances, but they can go beyond 100 up to 1000 instances.
And this is where an allocation policy comes into play.
So if you turn that on, now you have to worry about placement, which is not a big deal.
But I mean, that's how you're going to go beyond that 100.
And then there's the option of proximity placement groups.
And this allows you to group Azure resources physically closer together in the same region.
This is definitely something you want to do if performance like latency and performance of physical distance of virtual machines is very important.
When you're running like HPC workloads, this is something people have to think about as literally the physical placement of your VMs.
By default, a scale set has a single placement that can hold up to 100 VMs.
And if you set the scale set property to single placement group to false, then the scale set can be composed of multiple placement groups and have a range of 0 to 1000 VMs, so that's it.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are on to the scale set cheat sheet, so let's jump into it.
Azure scale sets allow you to automatically increase or decrease your VM capacity.
A load balancer can be associated with a scale set evenly, and the purpose of that would be to evenly distribute your VMs across multiple AZs to make your application highly available.
Use load balancers to probe checks for robust health checks.
You have two options here.
You can use an application gateway with your scale set, or you can use an Azure load balancer.
A scaling policy
The policy determines when a VM should be added or removed to meet the current requirements.
You have your scale out operation and your scale in operation.
Remember, scale out means to add and scale in means to remove.
Then for scale in policies, this is going to help you determine what the VM, like how it's going to remove VMs, all right?
And you have default, newest VM, oldest VM.
For the update policy, determines your VM instances are brought up to date with the latest scale set model.
We have automatic and manual and rolling.
For health monitoring, this can be enabled to determine if your server is healthy or unhealthy.
There are two modes of health monitoring.
So we have application health extension.
This is where it pings an HTTP request to a specific path and expects.
So it's accept, but it should say expects.
We'll just mark that there quickly there.
Expects a status of 200.
Load balancer probe allows you to check based on the TCP, UDP, HTTP requests.
And the last thing here I just want to mention is automatic repair policy.
If an instance is found to be unhealthy, then it should delete and launch a new instance.
I'll go correct those two things for you, but there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're looking at Azure App Services, which allows you to quickly deploy and manage web apps on Azure without worrying about the underlying infrastructure, and specifically, this is known as a Platform as a Service.
So Azure App Service is an HTTP-based service for hosting web applications, REST APIs, and mobile backends.
And you can choose your programming language, and it can either be Windows or Linux environment.
And it's a platform as a service.
So if you've ever used Heroku, it is basically the Heroku of Azure.
And so Azure App Service takes care of a lot of the underlying infrastructure for you.
So it can do security patches of the OS and languages, load balancing, auto scaling.
Automated Manager, and then there's a lot of things that you can implement, and so for integrations such as Azure DevOps, GitHub Integrations, Docker Hub.
package management, easy to set up staging environments, custom domains, attaching SSL certificates.
So you can see that it just basically takes care of everything for you if it's really hard for you or time consuming for you to do all this on your own in Azure.
And the way it works is you pay based on an Azure app service plan.
Honestly, I find these really confusing.
I really like how AWS does Elastic Beanstalk because you're just paying for the underlying services.
But Azure has all these crazy
tiers here, but you have shared tier, which is free and shared, doesn't support Linux.
You have the dedicated tier, which is basic standard premium, premium version two and three, and the isolated tier.
And so another thing I need to note is that Azure App Service is not just for traditional VMs for monoliths.
You can also run Docker, single or multi containers.
And when you set up a project, you're going to choose your domain name on the azurewebsites.net.
Obviously, you can override that with your custom domain name.
But there you go.
Let's talk about Azure App Services runtimes.
And so let's define what a runtime is.
A runtime is software instructions that are executed while your program is running.
And so runtime generally means what programming language, libraries, and frameworks you're going to be using.
And so runtimes for Azure app services are predefined containers that has your programming languages and probably some commonly used libraries for those languages installed and probably commonly used languages for web frameworks.
And so the idea is that you're going to choose your runtime.
It could be.NET,.NET Core, Java, Ruby, which I'm very disappointed in Azure because as of shooting this video, they do not support
Ruby for Application Insights, but yet they have it here in Azure App Services, Node.js, PHP, Python, and there's all the logos, if you like seeing the logos.
And so Azure App Services generally has multiple versions.
So they have like Ruby 2.6, 2.7.
For PHP, they have a lot of versions.
For Node.js, they have a lot of versions.
But I just want to point out that it's pretty common for cloud providers to stop or to retire the old ones at some point to stop supporting them.
just because they want to keep things modern.
And the other thing is it also helps you keep with your best security practices, because really you should always be trying to upgrade to the latest version for those security patches and things like that.
So there you go.
Now let's say you wanted to use a language that wasn't supported on Azure App Services, like you wanted to use a
Elixir.
What you could do is create your own custom container, either for Windows or Linux.
And so you just go ahead and create your own Docker container in your local environment.
You can push it to an Azure Container Registry.
And then the idea is you can deploy your container image to your app service.
So I just wanted you to know that you could do that if there's some languages or other things, or maybe you're using a language, but you need some bundle or packages that are just baked into the container.
So there you go.
Let's talk about deployment slots.
So deployment slots allow you to create different environments for your web application and associate a different host name.
This is useful when you need a staging or a quality assurance environment, or maybe you need just like a developer environment, any kind of environment you want.
So think of it as a way to quickly clone your production environment for other uses.
And so down below here, you'd have your deployment slots, and there's your slots.
So maybe you have app staging beta, so that's the different host names there.
And so the idea is that not only do you have other environments, but there's also this thing called swapping.
And the idea is like, imagine you decide, like you make a clone of your production environment, and then you deploy the latest version to it, and then when you decide that it's good, it's in good shape, then what you can do is swap it out with your current production environment, and then just retire your old one.
This is called blue-green deployment.
And so that is a great way to do deployments, and I just wanted you to be aware of that.
So I wanted to talk about App Service Environment because I just wanted to show you how Azure App Service is not just for little toy apps or your small startup, but they can be really useful for larger enterprises.
So App Service Environment is an Azure App Service feature that provides a fully isolated and dedicated environment for securely running App Service at high scale.
And so this is going to allow you to host web or Windows web apps, Linux web apps, Docker containers, mobile apps, and
Functions and app service environments are appropriate for application workloads that require very high scale isolation and secure network access, high memory utilization, and again, when you think of platform as a service, you don't think at this kind of scale, so it's really impressive that Azure does this.
Customers can create multiple ASEs within a single Azure region or across multiple Azure regions, making ASEs ideal for horizontal scaling stateless application tiers in support of high request per second RPS workloads.
An ASE comes with its own pricing tier, and that's the isolated tier.
An ASE can be used to configure security architecture.
Apps running ASE can have their access gated by upstream devices, such as a web application firewall, also known as a WAF.
ASEs can be deployed into availability zones using zone pinning.
I don't know what that is, a zone pinning, but that sounds good to me.
And there are two deployment types for ASE.
We have external ASE and ILB ASE.
Let's go take a quick look at what those look like.
So here's a big diagram.
And look in the middle there, that's where our Azure service environment is.
It's in our own VNet and a subnet.
And the idea is that the reason it's called an external ASE is because it exposes the ASE hosted app on an internet.
accessible IP address.
And then down below, if you wanted to connect this, this is generally what people are probably using it for, but what you want to do is you can connect it to your on-premise via a site-to-site or express route VPN.
So that's something you can do with it.
And the other part is like you can, because the ESC is within the same VNet, it also has access to resources within the VNet without any additional configuration.
So that's really nice.
And then the second
a second one here, it looks, it's exactly identical, but there's one key difference, and it has this ILB there.
And an ILB stands for Internal Load Balancer, and that is basically the only difference.
So there you go.
All right, let's take a look here at deployment for Azure App Services, and let's just first define deployment.
So that's the action of pushing changes or updates from a local environment or repository into a remote environment, and Azure App Services has a lot of options for us, and that, to me, is the most powerful thing about Azure App Services, because it's easy to deploy a web app to a virtual machine backed by a database, but...
Figuring out deployment is a very time-consuming and tricky thing, and Azure App Services gives us so many options, unbelievable amount of options.
It is so great of them to do that for us.
So we can run from a package, deploy Zip or a RAR, deploy via FTP, deploy via Cloud Sync, deploy continuously from like GitHub, or use Azure Pipelines, deploy using custom containers, using Docker Hub, Azure Container Registry, deploy from a local Git repo.
deploy using GitHub Actions, deploy using GitHub Action containers, or deploy with an ARM template.
So we're not going to look at all of these, how they work, but let's look at a few of them so we just have an idea how robust of these options are.
The first one we're going to look at is running from a package.
And this is when files in the package are not copied to the www.root directory.
Instead, the zip package itself gets mounted directly as a read-only
www.route.directory.
So basically all other deployment methods in App Service have to deploy to the following directory.
If you're on a Windows machine, it's going to be home site www.root.
If you're on Linux, it's going to be home site www.root.
And so since the same directory is used by your app at runtime, it's possible for deployment to fail because of file lock conflicts.
And for that reason, the app might behave unpredictably because some of the files are not yet updated.
So this is the reason why you might
Want to create a package?
It's just because it circumvents the issue of just replacing files in the folder.
Another method is the zip and RAR deployment.
This uses the Kudu service that powers continuous integration-based deployments, and Kudu is used for a lot of things, but it's an engine behind Git deployments and Azure App Services, and it's an open-source project that can also run outside of Azure.
And so, CUDA supports the following functionality for zip file deployments, and it supports a lot more than just zips, but it does deletion of files leftover from a previous deployment, option to turn on the default build process, which includes package restore, deployment customization, including run deployment scripts, deployment logs, a file size of...
What is it?
Two gigs?
Two gigs.
And you can use it with the CLI, the API, via REST with curl, or the Azure portal.
So, by the way, that's you uploading a zip, but you're essentially using Kudu underneath, okay?
And so let's go take a look at another deployment method, which is File Transfer Protocol.
FTP has been around for forever, and this is pretty much how people thought you were supposed to deploy your apps in the late 90s and early 2000s.
I don't think it's a really great way to deploy, but the point is that if you want to do it this way or you have a use case that makes sense, you can do it.
So the idea is that in the deployment center, you would say, I want to use FTP, and you get an FTP endpoint, your username and password, and that's your credentials, and you use your FTP client to connect.
Very old school, but it's an option for you, which is really nice.
Another way, which to me is a bit bizarre, but it's cool that you can do it, is you can use Dropbox or OneDrive to deploy using Cloud Sync.
So the idea is that you have Dropbox.
It's a third-party cloud storage service.
OneDrive is the same thing.
It's just Microsoft's thing.
And so you go to the deployment center, configure Dropbox or OneDrive, and when you turn it on, it will just sync
or you'll just create a folder in your Dropbox drive, and that will get synced.
So that's the one for OneDrive, that's the one for Dropbox, and this is going to sync to that www.root there.
I would have loved to take in some screenshots, but I couldn't find how to turn the service on, but I know it exists, and I thought it was so bizarre.
But yeah, there you go.
That is the deployment methods there.
So the way you pay when you use Azure App Service is you need an Azure App Service plan, and that's going to determine how much you pay and what's going to be available to you.
You got 3 tiers, which we're going to go through here shortly, and we did mention them earlier.
I honestly do not like this whatsoever.
This tells you this is a Microsoft product because it has these wonky pricing tiers.
I hope in the future they'll change it, but that's just what it is.
And so let's go learn it.
So basically what you do is you have like this big wizard.
that tells you all the stuff that you can have.
It tells you what's included and stuff like that.
But let's work our way through it.
So the first thing is the shared tier.
And there's two types here.
We got free and shared.
And so there's the free tier, that red one there.
It's called F1.
It gives you 1 GB of disk space, up to 10 apps on a single shared instance, no SLA for availability.
And each app has a compute quota of 60 minutes per day.
So there you go.
You get some free tier there.
Then there's the shared tier.
This provides up to 100 apps on a single shared instance, no SLA availability.
Each app has a compute quota of 240 minutes per day.
And the thing is, that I didn't know where the button is for that.
So like the next thing right beside it is the dedicated tier.
And I thought that's what it would be because it says 100 total ACUs.
So is it?
I'm not sure.
But anyway, the point is there is a shared tier.
Where it is, I don't know.
And you can't use the shared tier on Linux-based systems.
So you're using Windows.
If you're using Windows, you've got to use bigger instances anyway, which I don't know.
I don't like that too much.
But that's what it is.
Moving on over, we're now into the dedicated tiers.
And look, it's right beside the free tier.
That's the green one.
It says B1.
And if you expand it, actually has a couple other tiers there.
So I just wanted to show you that there was three there.
And so for dedicated tiers, we've got basic, standard, premium, premium version 2, premium version 3.
And we're looking at basic.
That's what that is.
More disk space, unlimited apps, 3 levels in this tier that offer varying amount of compute power, memory, disk usage.
It must be B1, B2, B3.
And then the next thing over is the standard.
And we had to switch tabs there onto the production tab.
Notice the terminologies don't really match the tiers.
And so with standard, you can scale out to three dedicated instances, has an SLA of 99.95% availability, and three levels in this tier that are offering varying amounts of compute, power, memory, and storage disk.
And so then
So that's that tier there.
And we're on to our last tier, which is the premium tier.
And this scales to 10 dedicated instances.
It has availability of SLA of 99.95% and multiple levels of hardware.
So that's the dedicated tiers.
Then we're on to the last thing, which is isolated.
And this is really only going to be used, I think, for ASC.
So the isolated tier has dedicated Azure virtual networks, full network compute isolation, scales out to 100 instances, availability SLA of 99.95%.
And again, I think it's just for those ASEs.
But there you go.
That is all the tiers.
And hopefully it makes sense to you.
But it is a little bit tricky to figure out what to choose, but you don't really get to pick at a granular level.
That's what I don't like.
But it is a really great service, Azure App Service.
It does figure everything out for you, so maybe it's okay for you.
So let's say you're using Azure App Services to host...
one of your applications and you need to run a random script.
How are you going to do that?
That's where WebJobs comes into play.
So it comes at no additional cost.
And WebJobs is not yet supported for Linux, which is of no surprise here because Microsoft is all about Windows.
But I hope one day they will support it.
The following types they support as of today are command files, bat files, executables.
We've got PowerShell files, bash files, PHP files, Python files, JavaScript files, and Java files.
When you go ahead and create your job, you're going to
to have between two types.
So you got continuous and triggered.
Continuous means that it's going to run continually until stopped, which is pretty clear.
And this particular mode supports debugging.
So if you need debugging, that's the mode you're going to be using.
For triggered, this only runs when a trigger occurs.
And you have different kinds of triggered here.
So you notice we have scheduled and we can enter a cron job in.
And this will also expose a webhook that can be called to enable scenarios like scheduling.
I think that would be like manual triggers.
It doesn't support debugging though.
So looking at web job scales, and this is for continuous only, we have multi instance and single instance.
So multi will scale your web jobs across all instances for your app service plan.
And single instance will only keep a single copy of your web job running regardless of the Azure app plan instance count.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are going to be learning about Azure App Services in this follow-along.
And it's a service that's supposed to make it easy for you to deploy web applications, I say supposed to, because it really depends on your stack.
Azure has more synergies with other stacks than others.
So like if you're like me and you like Ruby on Rails, you're going to find a lot of friction with Rails and Linux.
But if you're using something like Windows servers or Python or.NET, you're going to have a much easier time.
Still really great service, just wish they'd make it a bit more broad there.
there.
But let's hop into it.
So before we can go use that service, let's make sure that it's activated.
And so we'll go over here.
And we'll go to Azure subscription.
And then down below, we're going to go to resource provider.
Now you'd think what you could do is just type in app services.
And you'd be wrong because the service is under a particular provider.
So if you want to figure out what provider it is, we can go Azure resource providers.
And they have a page on documentation here that lists them all.
So if I search for Azure App Services, it's under web and domain registration.
So we're going to make sure this is registered.
If we're using a custom domain, which we are not today, we need this one activated.
So going back here, I will type in web and you can see it's registered.
So if yours is not registered, go ahead and hit that.
I believe this by default is generally registered with new Azure accounts.
So I don't think that is an issue for you.
But we'll go back up here, close these additional tabs, and we will type in Azure App Services.
And we will look for that service.
So here it is.
And we'll go ahead and hit Add.
And so I'm going to give it a new name.
I just made it a moment ago, but I'm going to try again and try to use the same name.
So we're going to call this Voyager.
Great.
And then I'm going to go ahead and name this Voyager.
And I already know that is taken, so I'm going to type in Delta Flyer.
And these are fully qualified domains, so they are unique.
With Azure App Services, you can run a Docker container.
We're doing code this time around.
And what I like to use is Ruby.
But again, if I want to use the CICD, I'm not going to be able to use the deployment center with Ruby, so that is not possible.
And so we're going to go with Python and run either a Flask or a Django app.
I haven't decided yet.
I am in Canada, so let's go to Canada East.
And down below here, we have the plans.
Generally, the plans will tell you the cost underneath.
You'll notice that it's loading, but I just want to show you that there are some discrepancies in terms of pricing.
So if I was to go to Azure App Services pricing, and we were to pull this up here, we can kind of see the pricing here.
Okay.
And if we scroll on down, right now we're looking at a premium V2.
And oh no, I don't need help.
I'm okay.
You'll notice that it's 20 cents per hour.
So if I go here and do that times 730, because there's 730 hours in a year, that's $146.
I believe this is showing me in USD dollars.
Yeah.
And here it's showing me 103 Canadian, which is lower.
So it could be that because I'm running in a Canada East region, it's the
the price is different.
But you could imagine that if I had this at this cost at, what did we say here, at 146 USD to CAD, I'd actually be paying $182.
So you got to watch out for that kind of stuff.
But I'm pretty sure this is what the cost is.
So just be aware that if you look stuff up in here, it's not necessarily reflective.
So you got to do a little bit more work to figure that out.
If we wanted to go here, we cannot choose the free tier when we're using Linux.
If we're using Windows, I believe we can use it.
We're working with Linux today, so that's just how it's going to be.
For the B1, this is totally fine, but we want to utilize deployment slots.
Deployment slots is an advanced feature of the production version, and that's the only way we're going to be able to use it here.
This is $0.20 per hour again, so I don't want to be doing this for too long, but I think what we'll do is before we do that, we can just do an upgrade to dev to prod so we can experience
I'm going to go and just choose B1.
Okay, so go next.
We do not need any application insights for the time being, and it will not let us, so it's okay.
We'll go next, review and create, and we'll go ahead and create this resource here, and I will see you back when this is done.
So our resource is now set up.
We'll go to resource.
And now that we're in here, you'll notice if we hit browse, we're not going to see anything because we do not have anything deployed, which makes sense, right?
So we're going to actually have to go ahead and deploy something.
So we are going to make our way over to the deployment center.
And it's just going to tell us that we have yet to configure anything, and that's totally fine.
We're going to go to settings.
It'll give it a moment.
And so the thing is that we're going to need something to deploy.
I did not create an app, but the great thing is in the Azure documentation, they have a bunch of quick starts here.
All right, and apparently they have one for Ruby as well, but today we are looking at Python.
And so they actually have an example repository for us here, which is GitHub.
.com/azuresamples/python/docs/helloworld.
And I mean, I could go make a repo for you, but we might as well just use the one that is already provided to us.
So I'm just going to pull this up to show you what's in it.
It's a very, very simple application.
Even if you don't know anything about building web apps, I'm going to walk you through it really easily here, okay?
So we're going to open up app.py.
So we are using Flask.
If you've never heard of Flask, it is a very minimal Python framework for creating web apps.
very uninspiring homepage here, but it gets the job done.
It's going to create a default route for us, which we have there.
We're going to call hello here.
And we're going to have hello world.
So that's all that's going on here.
Very, very simple.
And we have a requirements.
This is our package manager.
I don't know why Python uses txt files.
It's very outdated to me, but that's what they use.
And here we have flask.
All right.
So we're going to use that repo.
It's a public repo, so it should be very easy for us to connect.
So we'll drop down, go to GitHub, and the next thing we need to do is authorize GitHub.
All right, so I ran into a bit of trouble there because I could not authenticate my GitHub account, but you know what?
I just made another GitHub account, so that made it a lot easier.
I'm going to go ahead here, hit GitHub, and we're going to try to authorize it.
And so now I'm logged into this new one called ExamProDev.
And we'll go ahead and authorize this application, and we're now in good shape.
This repository doesn't have anything in it, so if I want to clone something, I guess I'll probably have to fork that repo, so we'll give it a moment to authorize, and while that's going, I think that's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to go and fork the example repo.
If I can find the link again here myself, I believe it...
It is.
That's still authorizing over there.
I'm still looking for it.
So it was like examples or something.
Samples or examples.
All right, so I found a way around the problem.
I just made a new GitHub account.
So that's all I had to do.
And I just won't be using my primary account until I get my phone back.
So what we'll do is go hit connect.
I'll hit authorize.
And it didn't prompt me because it already connected to this new one called Exam Pro Dev.
You might have to put your credentials in here.
And it's going to ask me to select some things.
It's a new account, so there are no organizations, there are no repositories, there are no branches, totally brand new.
So what I'm going to need to do is get a repo in there.
So we'll just go ahead and fork the Azure samples one.
So that is Azure samples, Python, docs, hello world.
And if I type that right, we're in good shape.
I'm going to go ahead and fork this repository.
I'll say got it.
And then I'll move this off screen here.
This is now cloned.
You should see it cloned here.
And we'll go back here.
And this probably isn't live.
So there's no refresh button here.
So we'll have to hit discard.
And we will give this another go here.
And we will select our organization, which is our name.
There's the repository.
should be main branch.
It's kind of outdated.
I'm sorry, but it's called master.
That's what it is.
Not my fault.
That's Azure's fault.
Okay.
And I think that's it.
I don't know if we need a workflow configuration file.
I don't think so.
I'm just going to double check here.
No, I don't think so.
And what we'll do is we'll just go ahead and save that.
And so now we are set up for deployment.
All right, so now that that's all hooked up, if we were to go to browse, we're actually still seeing the default page.
A deployment hasn't been triggered just yet, so the way it works is it's using GitHub Actions.
So if we click into our, I'm going to call it main branch, I know they got the wrong name, but...
We're going to click into our GitHub workflows.
And then below here, we can see we have a YAML file.
And this is for GitHub Actions integration here.
And so what it's doing is it's specifying the branch, how it's going to build.
It's going to run on Ubuntu latest.
The steps it's going to do, it's going to check it out.
It's going to set up the Python version.
It's going to build it.
It's going to do that stuff.
And so in order for this to take action, we'd actually have to go ahead and make some kind of manual change.
we have yet to do so.
So what we'll do is we'll go back to our main here.
And it should be as simple as just changing something here.
So it's not, I'm not sure how it's supposed to know that it's supposed to be doing the hello.
Oh, I guess, yeah, sorry.
So this means it's going to route over to here.
So I'm just going to make any kind of change here.
Doesn't matter what it is, just one space.
We'll go ahead and give it a commit.
And it
If I go back to my latest commits, we should see that I made that change.
There it is.
We'll go back over here.
And this should be deploying.
So if we go over to logs, here, you can see one's in progress right now.
Okay.
And so that's what we're waiting, we're just going to see that finished there, we probably open the logs and get some more information there.
And so it just brings you back over to GitHub Actions.
And so here's GitHub Actions, and it's performing the stuff here.
So we're just going to give it time here, and I'll see you back in a moment.
So we didn't have to wait too long.
It only took one minute and 29 seconds.
If we go back over here.
we might need to do a refresh.
And so we can see this is reflected over here.
And so if we go back to, it doesn't really matter if we go to settings or logs here, but I'm going to hit browse and see if my page is deployed.
It still is not.
So we do have a small little problem here, and it's really going to just have to do with how the app is served, so that's what we need to figure out next.
All right, so our app is not currently working, and there's a few approaches we can take.
And the thing I can think right away is we should go and SSH into that instance.
If you scroll on down here from developer tools, you can go to SSH and click this button, and that's going to SSH you right into that machine right away.
You can also access SSH via the CLI command.
So I believe it's like, it's like AZ web app.
SSH.
It'll do the exact same thing.
You do that from the Cloud Shell, but that's not what we're doing today.
If I give this an LS in here, and we're in Linux, we can see we have our app here.
And what I would do is I would see what's running.
So I would do a Puma, or sorry, not Puma, PS aux grep Python.
And you can notice that we have GUnicorn that's running.
So that is where our Python instances are running.
So you're not looking for Flask, you're looking for Python here.
And if we wanted to make sure that was working, we just type in curl local host.
And so that is going to return a port 80.
So that tells me that, because like curl just means like, let's go look at that page.
It should return some HTML, like print out the HTML to us.
So that means the app is not running.
So what you could do is run Flask run, and it's going to start on port 5000.
Right?
So what I can do.
is I can go up back to my deployment center here.
And I'm going to go get that link here.
And just ignore the fact that it's working.
It's not working right now.
I know for certain it's not.
But if we do 5,000, that won't resolve because port 5,000 isn't open.
So we can't really just put 5,000 in there.
And the default server here would be 5,000.
So if I stop this and I specify port 80,
Then this will start up the app on port 80.
And so now when you go here, okay, it will work.
This is not a great way because, of course, as soon as you kill it here, technically the site should stop running.
And so you'll run into that step.
So what we need to do is provide a configuration to Gunicorn, which is a Python thing.
Again, it's not so important that you know what these things are, but the idea is that you understand as an administrator, you want to make sure you have an app that runs after you do a deploy.
And so in this particular one, we need a startup.txt.
And interestingly enough, there is a example code by the same author of the other one we were looking at here.
I believe it's the same person.
or it might not be, but they have a startup.txt, right?
And so in here, you can see that it binds on port 000, it starts up for workers, starts up the app.
All right.
And so that's something that we can go ahead and do.
So what I will do is I will go back to my GitHub repository that we have here.
And I can just go ahead and add a new file.
So I'm going to say
Add a file, create a new file here.
We'll call it startup.txt.
I'm going to copy this command here and paste it in there.
So GUnicorn will bind the workers and start up on the app.
Startup app is being ran by something here.
So if I go back here, I think they have a startup pie here.
And that's all that it is doing.
I think I want to...
I could do it this way, I suppose.
Let me just see here.
There's just a slightly different name.
So they actually have like a full app going on here.
And I just want a very simple Flask app.
So I think what I can do is put Flask run here.
Port 80.
And that should start up the app there.
I'm going to go ahead and commit that file.
Okay.
And as soon as I commit that, if I go back to my actions, it created that startup file there.
So it should trigger a build.
It's queued up.
And I'll just put this tab up here.
So we'll be back here in two seconds.
And if I give this a nice refresh, yeah, you can see it deploys in progress.
So this doesn't take too long.
We'll just wait, close that there.
We'll just wait a few minutes.
We click logs, it just opens it back up here and we'll see how that goes.
All right, so your deploy may have finished there, but the thing is that we're not going to really know if a change has taken effect unless we actually go ahead and update our code.
So what I want you to do is go to your code tab, go to your app.py, we'll hit edit, and I'm going to go ahead and change this to Vulkan.
And then we'll scroll on down, hit commit changes.
And we'll make our way back over to our deployment center.
And we'll give it a refresh here.
And we're just going to wait until this one is complete.
And we will double check to make sure that is changed.
If it is not, we will take action to fix that.
Okay.
All right.
So we just waited a little while there for that deploy to happen.
And if we go to our website here, it is taking effect.
So that's all we had to do to get it working.
So that's pretty good.
So that is deployment.
So let's talk about deployment slots.
In order to utilize this feature, we're going to actually have to upgrade our account because we cannot utilize them at the basic plan here.
We've got to go to standard or premium.
So let's go ahead and give that an upgrade.
So here's the B1.
We're going to go to production here.
And I think, yeah, we're going to have to choose this one here.
Very expensive.
So the thing is we're going to just upgrade it temporarily, unless there's more options down below.
that are cheaper.
Yeah, these are the standard tiers.
Let's go with this one here because it's only $80.
Again, we're not going to be doing this for long, but I want to show you how to do staging slots and auto scaling, okay?
So we'll go ahead and apply that there.
And now it says that it's applied.
So if I go back to our app here and we click on deployment slots, sometimes it doesn't show up right away.
If it doesn't, that's not a big deal.
You just wait a bit, but today it's super fast.
So we're going to go ahead and add a new slot, we're going to call it staging, we're going to deploy from our production branch here, and I'm going to go ahead and create that there.
And we'll just wait until that's done.
Okay.
Great.
So we waited a little bit there, and our slot is created.
So I'm going to just hit close there.
And so now let's go take a look and see if we can actually see the application here.
So I just clicked into it, I clicked Browse, and we're getting the default page.
So nothing is actually really deployed to it.
So how are we going to do that?
That's the main question here.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to make my way over to the deployment center.
And you can see that it's not configured for the slot.
So we're
We are going to have to set it up all over again, even though it copied over configuration settings.
It didn't copy over the code.
So we go to GitHub.
We'll choose our organization again.
I'm going to choose the repository.
We're going to choose that main branch again there.
We're going to let it add a workflow.
And notice that this time it's going to call it staging.yaml, so there'll be a separate workflow that gets created.
We're going to go ahead and save that there.
And what we can do is, again, click onto our branch name there.
And if we click into our workflows, we'll now notice that we have a staging example.
It's the same thing, but it should be able to now deploy.
So the whole purpose of these deployment branches is that it helps us, we can deploy different versions of our apps, but it also, it's just a place where we can view things before we actually roll them out.
So we want to make sure 100% that they are working correctly.
I don't think this will automatically push out.
Let me just go to my actions to see if this is deploying.
Notice that we have two workflows now.
We have staging here.
And yeah, it looks like it's going to deploy here, so we'll just wait a little bit.
But maybe what we can do is try to have a slightly different version for each one here, okay?
But we'll just let that finish, and I'll see you back in a moment.
All right, so our deploy finished there.
So now if we go back to our website here, we go browse.
we should see that application.
It says, Hello, Vulcan.
And if we go and take out this, we still have Hello, Vulcan.
So how can we have a variant of this so that we can push out to that?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go back to my application here.
I'm going to go to code, and I'm just going to make a minor change.
I don't say I also...
Does that spell right?
Startup?
Doesn't look correct to me.
So maybe I'll go ahead and adjust.
that file, but it doesn't seem to be affecting anything, which is I'm a bit surprised there.
So what I'll do is I'm going to go and edit that file and give it the proper name.
Can I rename this file?
Yes, I can.
So we'll call that startup file.
I thought we need that for deploying.
I guess it just works without it, which is nice.
If we go back here, I'm going to go and I actually just want to edit my app here again.
And I'm going to go and edit this.
And we'll say, Hello, Andoria.
Or Hello, Andorians maybe.
And so if I go back to my actions, the question, what is it deploying?
Is it going to deploy the production or the staging?
And it looks like it's going to do both.
Looks like it's doing both here.
But one way we could tell is we can go to our logs here.
And we can see that, so we did 2 deploys.
So there's one change here.
If we go back to our main application and our deployment center here, and we go over to our logs, you can see that they're both deploying.
So it doesn't seem like it's a great thing that that's how it works.
So the question is then how would we facilitate that deploy, right?
How could we do that?
I suppose what we could do is just make a separate staging branch.
So if I go over to code here, I don't think we can just make branches through here.
So what I'm going to have to do is go ahead and oh, I can create a branch right here.
So we'll just type in staging and we'll go create ourselves a new branch.
And now we are in this branch.
And what I'm going to do is go ahead and modify this and we're just going to call this Hello Klingons.
Okay, we'll go ahead and update that.
And so this should be a separate branch.
So you'd think what we could do is go in and just change our settings so that it deploys from that one.
We'll go back to our deployment slots.
We'll click into staging here.
And we need to change our configuration settings.
I think we could just do it from here.
Hold on here.
I could have swore it specified the branch.
If we go to deployment center here,
I think it's set up on that other branch there.
I think we just adjusted here.
So yeah, I think we could just adjust the settings.
We can't discard them.
But maybe what we can do is just go in and modify that file.
So we will go into our code here.
And we will go ahead and click into here.
go into staging and we'll just change what the branch is called.
So we'll just say staging.
And we'll hit start commit and we will save that.
And we'll see if it actually reflects those changes there.
So we will go here and hit refresh.
We'll see if it picks up staging now if we go to settings.
It's not picking it up.
So
I'm not sure, I don't think, from a redeploy operation, we don't want to redeploy.
So maybe what we'll do is just, we'll have to do a disconnect here because it has the wrong one here.
So save workflow file.
Okay, we'll just go ahead and delete it.
It's not a big deal.
We'll just have to make a new one here.
We'll go to GitHub.
We'll choose our organization again, our repository, our staging branch this time around.
We'll let it add one.
See, it says we could use an available workflow, so we could have kept it there and added it there.
And we'll go ahead and save that.
So now we'll have two separate branches there, and we'll give that some time to deploy, because that will now trigger a deploy off the bat.
And so I'll see you back here in a moment.
Alright, so after a short little wait here, it looks like our app is done deploying.
So we'll go over here, we'll make sure that this is our staging server is good.
And we want to see that our production is different.
Perfect.
So we now have a way to deploy to each one.
But imagine that we want to swap our traffic.
So we're happy with our staging server, and we want to roll that out to production.
And that's where we can do some swapping.
So what we'll do is click the swap button.
And we're going to say the source is the staging, and this is our target production.
And we're going to perform that swap
right now, we can't do a preview because we don't have a particular setting set.
That's okay.
And it's kind of showing if there are any changes.
So set of configuration changes, we don't have any.
So that's totally fine as well.
We'll go ahead and hit swap.
And that's going to swap those two, I believe it's has has zero downtime.
So we'll be in good shape if that happens there.
And we'll just give it a moment to do that.
Great.
And so after a short little wait there, the swap is complete.
And so if we remember clearly, this was our production, right?
And so if I was to hit refresh, it should now say Klingons.
And if I go to my staging server, it should be the other way around, right?
Good.
So now imagine that I want to just split the traffic.
That's something else that we can do.
So notice over here we have these percentages here.
I'm not sure why it won't let me change those.
So maybe I'll have to look into that.
So I'll be back into...
So I'm not sure why it's not showing us that traffic slot there, but what I'm going to do is just maybe try to trigger a deploy back into our staging, and maybe that's what it wants to see.
So what I'm going to do is go back to my code here.
We'll be in our staging branch here.
I'm going to go ahead and edit this file here.
And we will just change this to Bajorans.
And we will hit update.
And we will let that go ahead and deploy.
So if we go to actions here, we can see that it is deploying.
And we'll just give it some time.
Okay.
So we'll see you back here in a bit.
I mean, the other reason could be that we're just not at the main level.
Hold on here.
If we go back here to deployment slots.
You know what?
I think it's just because I was clicked into here and then I was clicked into deployment slots that they're both grayed out.
Yeah, it is.
So we can actually do it that top level there.
It doesn't hurt to do another deploy, though.
So we'll just wait for I'll wait for that deploy to finish.
And then we'll come here and adjust that there.
Okay.
All right.
So let's take a look at doing some traffic switching here.
So right now, if we were to go to our production, we have Klingons.
And if we were to go to our staging,
We have Bajoran.
So imagine that we only want 50% of that traffic to show up.
So what we can do is put in 50%.
And what I'm going to do is, do I hit enter here or, oh, sorry, save up here.
There we go.
And so what's going to happen is this should take effect, I think, right away.
Yep.
And so now we have a 50% chance of getting something else here.
So I'm just going to keep on hitting enter here.
If that doesn't work, we can try an incognito tab.
And there we go, we got the opposite there.
And so this is serving up staging, right?
And this is serving up production, but they're both on the production URL.
So that's a way you can split the traffic.
So that's pretty much all I wanted to show you for deployment slots.
Let's now talk about scaling.
All right, so let's take a look into how we can do some scaling with our app service.
This is only available if you have Beyond Standard and Beyond, so Standard and Premium and et cetera.
So if we just search for scale, we have two options here.
We have scale up and scale out.
So scale up is pretty straightforward.
That just means to make our instance larger.
And so we already did that when we upgraded from our standard, our...
our B1 over to our S1 here, right?
So if I was to go here, I'm not going to do that, but if I was to do that and upgrade, that would be scaling up, right?
And notice that we're talking about scaling.
So right now we're limited to 10 instances, which is totally fine.
But now let's take a look at scaling out.
So if we go to scale out here and go to custom auto scale, what we can do is we can scale based on a metric.
So
We can add or remove servers based on the demand of the current web applications traffic, so we're only paying for servers when we need them, and so we have a minimum of 1, a maximum of two.
That seems fine to me, but we're going to add a rule here, and I want to scale this on the maximum time we're going to do on CPU percentage.
I just want to have a very easy way to trigger this so we can see a scaling event in action.
Here it has a maximum of 16%.
I might just lower that down even further.
Well, let me type in there.
New.
So 16% is what it's going to have to be.
It's not a big deal.
But I am going to reduce it down to, actually, I think, sorry, I don't know why I was going here.
The metric threshold to scale an action, I'm going to put it at 10%.
Sorry.
Okay.
So here's that line.
And so we have a, and I like how you can drag it, but you kind of have an idea that we have a high chance of having this triggered.
I just want to do this so that we have a good chance.
So if I was to put it here, you can notice that it's very easy for us to spike our traffic and cause a scaling event.
Now I'm going to set the duration to one minute, so we have a much higher chance of triggering that there.
Okay.
Set A duration less than 5 minutes may generate transient spikes.
Yeah, that's fair.
But I mean, I just want to show you a trigger happen.
And we need a cool down time probably.
And it's set to 5 minutes.
That's totally fine.
We're going to add one.
And that looks fine to me.
I'm going to set this to maximum.
Okay.
And so now we're very likely to trigger that there.
We'll go ahead and hit add that instance there.
And so now that we have that, we're going to go ahead and save that.
And so now that that's there, what we want to do is actually trigger a scaling event.
And so where we're going to see that is under the monitoring tab.
So if we go to monitoring, and what we're going to do is go over to, it should be in
Sorry, I forgot.
The place where we need to go take a look here is actually in the run history here.
So if we go here and check one hour, we can see how many instances are running.
And I think if I dial it back here, it should show me over time as it changes.
We do have a scale up event that has happened, which happened, I guess, 4 minutes ago.
So I guess it gives you kind of an idea of how many instances are running, which right now are two.
So maybe our...
Maybe our scaling event is not in the best use case there because it's happening too frequently.
So what I'm going to do is go ahead and modify that scaling rule.
And so I'm just going to go back and click here.
And maybe we'll just make it so it is less aggressive.
So what I'm going to do is just change it so it's over the duration of 5 minutes.
And I'm going to just put it right above here so that it goes back to one.
Okay.
And we'll go ahead and save that.
And so now if we go back to our run history here, it still shows that it has two, as you can see here, but I want to see this drop back down to one.
So it's going to check every 5 minutes or within the span of 5 minutes.
So what I'm going to do is just wait here and I'll see you back in a bit until we see a scaling action happens here, okay?
Yeah, I'm just sitting here waiting for it to scale down and I don't see it going.
So it makes me think that I need to go ahead and set a scale scale down action.
Let's take a look at the one that we currently have.
So this one is set.
Oh, you can see it's still spiked.
We don't even have anything going on here.
But what I'm going to do is just be really aggressive here.
I'm going to say when it's 50%.
OK.
And so here.
We'll go back here and I'll save that.
And I just wanted to see if it scales down.
I shouldn't have to set a scale down action.
It should just go.
And what I'm actually going to do is be a little bit more aggressive.
I know I'm setting a lot of stuff here, but I'm going to just set it to duration of 1 minutes so we can see this a lot sooner.
And we will go back to our run history here and we'll see if we observe a scale down.
Alright, so it's not scaling down here, but I think it's probably because I need a scale out action.
So what we'll do is go ahead and add a new rule.
This thing, if we go here, and we just look at it, it's not going to decrease it unless we have a scale out action.
So I don't think it's necessary for us to set one here, I think you get the idea.
But that's for scaling.
So we're all done here with Azure App Services.
All we got to do is go ahead and go ahead and delete it.
So let's go ahead and delete our app here.
Okay.
So there's a few different ways we can do it.
I'm going to do it via resource groups.
I believe we called it Voyager here.
So click into that.
And I'm going to go ahead and delete the resource group.
And here is all the related services.
And so I will type in Voyager.
And there we go.
Great.
And so, there we go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're looking at Azure App Services Cheat Sheet.
This is a two-pager, so let's jump into it.
Azure App Services is an HTTP-based service for hosting web applications, REST APIs, and mobile backends.
You can choose a programming language in either a Windows or Linux environment.
It's platform as a service, so it's the Heroku or AWS Elastic Beanstalk equivalent of Azure if that helps you remember what it is.
Azure App Services makes it easy to implement common features.
So for integrations and features such as Azure DevOps, GitHub integrations, Docker Hub integrations, package management, easy to set up staging environments, custom domains, attaching TLS and SSL certificates.
You pay based on the Azure app service plan.
So you've got a standard tier, a dedicated tier, and an isolated tier.
Notice that this tier does not support Linux, okay?
Azure App Services supports the following runtime, so.NET,.NET Core, Java, Ruby, Node.js, PHP, and Python.
Azure App Services can also run Docker as a single Docker container or multi-containers.
You can also upload your own custom container, so you'd upload it, or I guess deploy it.
So you'd create it, upload it to Azure Container Registry, and then deploy.
You have deployment slots.
This allows you to create different environments for your web application.
You can swap environments.
This could be how you perform a blue-green deployment onto the second
Slide here: App Service Environment (ASE) is an Azure App Service feature that provides a fully isolated and dedicated environment for securing or securely running.
service apps at high scale.
Customers can create multiple ASCs within a single Azure region or across multiple Azure regions, making ASC ideal for horizontal scaling, stateless application tiers, or high request per second RPS workloads.
ASC comes with some pricing tier, which is isolated tier.
ASC can be used to configure security architecture.
Apps running on ASC can have their access
this should say granted, not graded by upstream devices such as a web application firewall, a WAF.
And app service ASCs can be deployed into an AZ using a zone pinning.
There are two deployment types for ASC.
You have external ASC and ILB ASC.
ILB would be internal load balancer, okay?
Azure App Services provides many ways to deploy your applications, and there's so many I'm not going to list it here, but I probably would recommend that you go review the actual content for that, because it would have made a whole cheat sheet here.
Then, last thing here, WebJobs is a feature of Azure App Services that enables you to run a program or script in the same instance as the web app API mobile app.
There's no additional cost to WebJobs, so there you go.
Hey, this is Andy Brown from ExamPro.
And in this follow-along, we're going to learn all about imaging or managed images in the shared image gallery.
This is kind of a precursor for our availability follow-along because we need an image for that follow-along.
So I figured we'll just spend some time here learning about images.
So what I want you to do is go all the way to the top and type in virtual machines.
And we are going to launch ourselves a new Linux instance running Apache 2, just a default page, so that we can
to see some kind of website there.
I'm naming my resource group and the virtual machine as Wolf and Wolf.
We'll drop this down for images here and make sure that we choose Ubuntu LTS 18.04.
I'm choosing generation 2.
For our size, just expand that there and choose B1 LS because that's the most cost effective one.
So it's $5.83.
We'll go over to password, choose Azure user.
And we'll do testing 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, capital on the T, testing 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, capital on that T.
For ports, we're going to want port 80 and port 22.
We'll go next.
We'll skip all the way over to advance.
And here we're going to put in some custom data.
Now I wanted to install Apache by default.
So we'll make a shebang.
That is the exclamation with the hash together.
And we'll type in, oops, bin forward slash SH.
Make sure I spell that all right there.
We'll type in sudo apt install Apache.
two hyphen y.
So this is a bash script.
And the way cloud and it works is that you can give it a YAML file, you can give it a bash script, it's just going to look at the first line to determine what it is that you're passing in.
And then then it will work appropriately.
This is the easiest way to get Apache installed.
So we'll go ahead and go review and create.
And we'll wait for our review screen to populate here, and it does our calculation.
We'll scroll all the way down, hit create, and I will see you back here in a bit once this is done deploying, okay?
All right, so after a short wait there, it looks like our server is ready.
So we'll go to resources and make sure that it works.
Now it is complaining, so I'm going to go all the way top to virtual machines here.
It's because I had a virtual, I had a resource group earlier called Wolf, and so it's getting confused.
But I'm going to click in here into Wolf, and what we'll do is grab the public IP address and just make sure that works, and we're all in good shape.
So now that we have that, we want to make a snapshot of this page, and so that's the goal here.
Okay, so
here, when it's open, we're going to click on capture.
And we're going to create a new image.
So we'll have it in wolf here.
And so we have the option to have it in the shared image gallery, or neither.
And so what I want to do is make it not in the shared image gallery and also in the shared image gallery.
So we can see the difference.
Okay, so say no.
And we will have it in that, that there, it's going to give it a name.
Notice here says zone resilience.
So if you want to be able to launch this in any availability zone, you're gonna have to turn this on.
which we absolutely want to do.
We do not want to automatically delete our virtual machine because we're going to take more than one snapshot of it, okay?
So we'll hit here, we'll hit create.
And so that's going to stop the virtual machine, and we're going to get an image here soon, okay?
So I guess we'll just wait until this is done.
So after a short little wait here, we now actually have our managed image.
So what I'm going to do is open a new tab here, and I want to make my way back over to virtual machines.
Just because I want to show you the state of the virtual machine.
So, in order to create that image, it had to stop our virtual machine, which is pretty normal because you don't want your virtual machine to be in a strange state when you're creating an image.
But what we'll do is we'll make our way over now to images.
So, if we type in images here and...
And now you can create images directly here, but I always find this part a little bit hard because you kind of run out of options, then you have to add data disk.
It gets too complicated.
So a better way is just to always launch the VM and create it that way.
And do they have a backup button?
There it is.
Okay.
So here is our image.
And if we wanted to create a VM from it, we just hit create VM.
And what it's going to do is just pre-populate it here.
Okay, so it's as simple as that.
It's really not that complicated.
And so what we'll do is we'll go back to our virtual machine.
So I'm going to click here and just go type in virtual machine.
And now let's go create an image the other way, which is via the shared gallery.
So I'll hit capture again.
And this time I'm going to let it create in the gallery and automatically do the virtual machine after creating this image.
Absolutely.
We don't really need it after we do this here.
And so we have the option between general and specialized.
So general is for VMs created with its image, requires a host name, et cetera.
Specialized does not contain all that data there.
For an image definition, we'll have to create a new one.
So we'll say my definition.
And here we'll have to have a version number.
So I'm going to go 0.0.1.
And we have some information about replication.
That's all fine.
We'll hit review, create.
this sometimes is faster, or it can be very, very slow.
So I'm not sure how fast it will be here.
But I'll see you back here a moment when this is all done.
Okay, so I've been waiting here quite a long time.
But I think that it's actually already created, which is confusing, because it still says in progress, but I just want to go through the motions and show you what's here.
So if we go all the way to the or sorry, if we were just open my gallery here.
And by the way, if we want to get to shared galleries, we just type in shared gallery.
Right?
Here underneath, we have our definition.
And within that, we have our versioning.
And from here, we can create our VM.
So if we were to create our VM from here, you're going to notice the same box.
But now it's here.
And so the thing is, that shared image gallery is the preferred way of creating virtual machines just because of all the versioning and additional layers that you have in place.
But it's really up to you on which one you want to use.
But I believe that this is the preferred method.
But now that we have two images, that's pretty much all there really is to this, I'm going to keep the resources around here, probably not the virtual machine, if I make my way over to the VM, if it still has not been deleted, I'll just go delete that myself.
Okay, that might be the reason why it still says in progress is trying to delete the VM.
And so now we can proceed on to our next section or next following, which will be all about
Availability.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are on to our availability follow-alongs.
And one thing we should understand is availability sets.
Now, this is basic knowledge.
I share this in the AZ-900, but if you're doing something like the administrator or a lot of the other exams, you need to know how to utilize this, so we're just going to cover it again.
and mostly in the context of also scale sets.
So I just want to pull up one page for you.
This is a very important page that you should know for SLAs for virtual machines because it describes the different kinds of combinations of things to meet certain requirements.
And especially on the administrator, you're definitely going to see questions saying, you know, if you have X, Y, Z, how do you achieve 99.5% availability?
And you need to know whether you can use a scale set or availability set.
Combination of things, okay?
So that is something that is really important, but just to do a review of availability sets, what I'm going to do is pull up the documentation, because they have a nice graphic here, and the idea is that you have fault domains and updated domains, so this is like a stack of computers, a rack of computers, and...
And the idea is that there are some machines that are going to be scheduled for updates, and then some have a potential of failure, right?
So if everything is in this fault domain, then if all this fails, then the server, the redundant server over here will remain running.
And then within the rack, if an update occurs on just this one, then these other ones will remain fine.
So that is something we can specify when we create our virtual machine.
So I'm going to go through the motions here.
We're not going to go and actually launch the virtual machine because there's not a lot to look at here, but I want you
you to know about these settings.
So under availability options, notice here it says availability zones.
So physically separate your resources within an Azure region.
And then down below, they have automatically distribute your VMs across multiple fault domains.
So it's a bit odd that they don't have scale set here.
It's in preview, because it's definitely something you can use.
but I guess they're just going to add it as convenience, but these are your availability settings.
So if I go to availability set, you'd have to create a new one, and here you're just specifying the amount of fault domains and update domains, all right?
And so I believe when you create a scale set, it has five and five by default, and then here when you're creating availability set, there's a bit of flexibility, but the difference between scale sets and...
Availability sets is an availability set.
The VM, they're all the same, so you're not going to have a variety of different kinds.
It also has automatic scaling, and it's defaulted to five to five.
So I just want to be sure that you know how to create an availability set, and you just launch the instance so it'll all look like normal.
So there we go.
So carrying on learning more about availability, let's take a look at scale sets.
So we could make our way over to virtual scale sets and create them here.
But I find it a lot easier to actually launch them when you have an existing image.
So what I'm going to do is actually make my way over to our shared image gallery here.
And I'm going to go into our name, into our version, I'm going to go ahead and create a virtual machine scale set.
And that'll just automatically select it here so we don't have to go through images and try to find it that way.
And so we'll name it Wolf Scale Set.
And we will choose three availability zones because that's the general rule is that you always want to have three.
And like especially for enterprise, it's always going to be 3, okay?
Then if we scroll on down here, I'm going to set it as password and we'll say Azure User.
And we'll do testing, capital T, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, testing, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, capital on the T.
We'll go to next.
Oh, I don't know if it'd like that.
Make sure that is correct.
There we go.
And we'll go to next to this.
We'll leave with premium SSD.
We'll go to next for networking.
And everything looks fine here.
We'll go to next.
Now notice we could create a load balancer here, but I'm going to want to create that separately because I just want to show you all the options where here it's going to set up a bunch of stuff for us by default.
I don't want you to lose that experience.
And so we can see the initial count.
I'm going to set it to three because I have 3 availability zones.
We can set up a scaling policy.
I'm going to go manual for the time being right now.
We can set also a scale in policy.
So we'll go next to management.
And actually, you know what, for scaling, I'm going to set it to one, just because I want to probably set up a scaling policy instance, see it scale up.
This is all okay, we'll go to next for health.
We're not going to monitor health right now.
And this all looks okay, as well.
We'll go hit review and create.
And we will launch this scale set.
Okay.
All right, so after waiting a little while here, it looks like our skill set is ready.
So I'm going to go to resource here.
Actually, probably an easier way, just if you get lost, you can type scale set in the top here.
And we'll click into our scale set here.
And we can see how many instances we have.
We have a single one running right now.
But let's say we wanted to launch three there.
We go to scaling.
And we could scale up to go a bit crazy there, scale up to three.
But we could also set a custom auto scaling group.
So if we were to go here, what we could do is scale based on a metric.
And then we would add a rule.
And we could choose a bunch of different options like average percentage of CPU, and when it exceeds a certain amount, then it will cap and here you can adjust the values here.
Now, I do this in the app Azure services section, we spent a lot of time
There with that, and there's not a lot to learn here it's pretty straightforward.
So, what I'm going to do is actually do a manual scaling.
So, I'm going to go over here, and we're just going to increase this up to three here, and then we'll just go ahead and hit save.
And so, what that will do is increase the amount of instances, okay?
Another thing we should take a look here is actually health and repair.
So this way we can say whether we're going to have a health monitoring here.
And we are running on port 80, and we do have a website there.
So that's something we can definitely turn on.
But notice down below we have automatic repairs.
And so it's saying that if an instance is unhealthy, it will replace that instance.
So we'll turn that on for a grace period, we could say of 10 minutes.
So I'll go ahead and
and save that.
And yeah, we'll just wait until that's done.
Alright, so it looks like our health check is turned on here now.
So some other things I might want to point out here is like the upgrade policy, you could change this to change when it should or how it should update.
If instances are replaced under configuration, notice that over provisioning is turned on.
So we do not have unexpected billing, say, let's say someone tried launching 100.
You can
change instance termination.
I'm not sure how that would affect it if you had the replacement for unhealthy instances.
I'd hope that it would replace an unhealthy instance or terminate it, but I'm not sure about that case there.
If we go to sizes, we can resize our VMs.
You know, it's not super exciting here, but we can see we have 3 instances running.
We have a healthy health check.
It will show a green box
over here.
But now that we have a scale set, we're going to make our way back to our homepage and we'll start on to the next section, which is setting up a load balancer.
All right, so now that we have our scale set, we're going to continue on learning more about availability by creating an application gateway.
So this is actually a type of load balancer, even though it has gateway in the name.
Then there's Azure load balancers, and the difference between these two is this one's layer 7 for the applications, and this is layer 4.
So TCP, UDP, like at a lower layer.
So
since we have a web application, which is a simple Apache page, we're going to want to serve it up via the Application Gateway.
All right, so make your way over to the top here and we'll click on Application Gateway or just type that in and we'll go ahead and add ourselves a new Application Gateway.
We'll choose Wolf here.
I'm going to name this Wolf Application AGW.
And then we do not, we don't need any auto scaling right now.
So we'll just leave that alone.
I'm going to set that to one.
We're going to choose two, one, and three, because the rule of three counts here.
We always want three.
And then down below, make sure you choose the correct virtual network.
If you're not confident, make sure you go over to your skill set and just double check to make sure where it resides.
So if I go over here into my skill set and check, it's in WolfVNet 499.
I ended up with more than one.
I don't know.
I just had a tutorial.
I've done this a few revisions, so I've ended up with an additional one there.
Notice it's complaining because it's trying to put this in the default, but it needs its own subnet.
So here under subnets, we're going to create one just for the VGW, so VGW.
And we're going to need a range first.
So go over to address space ranges, and we'll pick out the next number.
So 10.0.2.0 forward slash 24.
We'll hit save.
And once that has created, we'll make our way over to the subnet.
And when we hit subnet, it will automatically select the next one for us.
I'm going to put VGW in here.
We'll hit save.
And then once that's saved, we'll make our way back to the wizard.
Notice up here, the breadcrumbs.
If we click one back, we can make our way back to where we are and then choose that VGW subnet.
We'll go to the front to the front end section here.
We got public, private, or both.
We want public today, and we will need a new IP address.
So I'm going to call this Wolf.
VGW.
We'll go ahead and hit OK.
We'll go to backends here, add a backend pool.
I'm just going to call this backend, and we'll drop down and choose a virtual machine scale set.
If you do not see it here, it's because they're not in the same VNet.
Make sure that's the case.
And then we'll go to configuration.
So we've got a frontend, a backend.
Now we've got to glue them together with routing rules.
We'll just say my rules.
We have listeners and backend targets.
So we'll name our listener name my listener.
If you can spell it, that's a hard one for me.
So I'm just going to copy paste that in, take out the space there.
The front end IP is going to be public.
We're going to have HTTP on port 80.
We'll have basic if we had multi-site.
So if you have more than one destination, but we do not.
We'll go to backend targets, and we will choose the backend pool that we created.
And then we have to choose or add HTTP settings.
This is all kind of crammed together.
It doesn't really line up very well.
So I get a bit confused here.
So I think what we want to do is hit add new here.
And then we'll say my HTTP settings.
Port 80 is good.
We do not have cookies.
We do not care about connection draining.
All these options are not important to us for our very simple application.
But if you were creating a real web application that
that has a session, you probably would want to turn these both on, okay?
We'll go ahead and hit add.
And we do have path-based routing, but this is not something we need to worry about right now.
This is where you could say, you could have multiple targets.
So you could say, okay, anytime it is a cookie, then go to this virtual machine.
And then if it's another one, you could say go somewhere else or even do a redirect.
That's a great way of attaching things to your virtual machine there.
We'll go ahead and hit add.
And so now we have all of our information.
We'll hit tags, and we will go hit create, and I'll see you back here when this is done deploying, okay?
All right, so I've been waiting a while here for this to complete, but it looks like that we're still having a bit of trouble.
So what I'm going to do is make my way over to the actual load balancer here, because I just remembered, and this happens, because I don't normally make a scale set separately.
I usually make it with the load balancer.
But if we make our way over to the backend pool and we're to click into here, it actually has a thing that says down here, virtual
machine skill set was added to this backend pool, upgrade all instances of wolf skill set for this change to work.
So the scale set needs to get updated is the problem here.
So what I'm going to do is make my way over to the scale set.
And we'll see if we can do an upgrade here.
So if we just checkbox I'm all on there, I'm going to go hit upgrade.
And then this will perform an upgrade on the instances.
And we'll just give that some time and I'll see you back here in a moment.
Okay, so that didn't take too long for the upgrade.
And if you just hit the refresh here, you're going to wait for the status quos running.
And now they're all healthy.
So if we make our way back to our load balancer tab here, if you still have something open, just go to backend pools.
You should see three targets.
If we go up to our overview over here, we'll go grab, whoops, our IP address.
Now why they copy the text there?
I have no idea.
But if we go paste that up into here and take that out, we get our page.
So there you go.
That's all it took to get the availability
for the actual server running.
If we go on the left-hand side and we go over to health probes, this is interesting to look at.
We're not going to set it up, but I just want to show you that you'd write in your health check here, and then you could specify a different path.
So if you had like a page called, and this is pretty common for a lot of places, they'll have a page called health check.
And so that's just kind of like a way to configure a custom health check for your instances, but this is all I really wanted to accomplish here today.
I don't think there's really much of anything else that I'd like to do here.
So what we'll do is we'll go and make our way back to all of our resources.
And we'll try to find our original resource group here, if we can find, it's probably easier if we just go to resource groups.
Great, I'll just go ahead and delete this one here.
There we go, it's gonna delete a whole lot of stuff.
But yeah, there we go.
So Azure Monitor is quite a beefy service.
There's a lot going on in it.
And so it's a comprehensive solution for collecting, analyzing, acting on telemetry data from your cloud and on-premise environments.
So here's an example of one of the things it can do, which is provide you a visual dashboard.
But it can create smart alerts, automate actions, log monitoring, and a lot of different things.
And many Azure services by default are already sending their data to Azure Monitor, so you can use it.
It right away.
Now, I just want to introduce you to the concept of the pillars of observability.
This isn't a thing specific to Azure, but it's something that in DevOps that you need to understand, and it's just going to help you contextualize the offerings of Azure Monitor and other cloud service providers.
So, what is observability?
That is the ability to measure and understand how internal systems work in order to answer questions regarding performance, tolerance, security, and faults with a system and application, and in order to...
obtain observability, you need three things.
You need metrics, logs, and traces, and you have to use them together.
Using them in isolate does not gain you observability.
So let's go define those three things.
The first thing is metrics.
And that is a number that is measured over a period of time.
If we measure the CPU usage and aggregated it over a period of time, then we would have the average CPU metric.
Then you have logs.
These are text files where each line contains event data about what happened at a certain time.
And then you have traces.
And this is a history of requests that
is that travels through multiple apps and services, so we can pinpoint performance or failures.
And I like to make the joke that it looks kind of like the Triforce observability once you've constructed it there at the end.
Let's look at the anatomy of Azure Monitor, which is a little bit complex, but I'm sure we can work our way through it.
So the first thing is that we need sources of data.
So this is what data can be sent into Azure.
So you probably want application data, operating system data, data from Azure resources at your subscription level, your tenant level, which is going to be associated with Active Directory and custom sources.
And once you get those into Azure Monitor, you have to store them somewhere.
And you're going to put them in logs and monitors.
And these are just data stores that are within Azure Monitor that you're going to be able to work with.
And once you have that data in there, you're going to be able to leverage different services to do different things.
And so we will call these functions.
So you can perform insights, visualizations, analysis, response, and integration.
So we'd look at insights.
We're getting insights into our virtual machines, our containers, our applications.
For visualization, you might be making dashboards, you could be using Power BI or creating workbooks.
For analysis, you might be using the log analysis or the metric analysis tools.
For responses, you might want to create alerts or start auto-scaling.
And for integrations, you might want to use logic apps or export APIs to connect things up.
So there you go.
So now let's take a closer look at all the different sources, because this is going to really help us understand the utility at each level.
And I think that makes everything very crystal clear.
So remember that list of sources where we went to application to custom sources?
We're going to start at the top of that list and look at application code, which is all about performance and functionality of your application and code.
So that's like collecting traces, application logs, and user telemetry.
And so here is the visual representation.
And so on the left-hand side, we have our sources.
In the middle, we have our storage.
On the right-hand side, we have our services that we're going to be doing things with that data.
So looking on the left, in your application, you'll probably want to go ahead and install the instrumentation package.
This is going to allow us to collect data into Application Insights.
And Application Insights is an application for getting rich data about our applications.
Then you have availability tests.
This tests the responsiveness of your application from different locations on the public internet.
And that's really useful if you're saying, like, if you have your application, you're running it in the east of Canada and the west of the US, and you want to make sure that the response times are the same or lower, that's going to help you get there.
For your metrics, this is going to be describing performance and operations
and custom metrics of your application.
For your logs, you're going to be storing operational data about your application, such as page views, application requests, exceptions, and traces.
And then the things you're going to be putting in storage is you're going to send the application data to your Azure storage for archiving.
Or what you'll do is you'll store your availability tests if you need to go and analyze them further.
Or you could create a debug snapshot of your data so that you can then go debug that at a later point.
OK.
So let's take a look at how we're going to monitor our operating systems.
And this is for the guest operating system, not the host operating system.
So when you're dealing with virtualization, the VM has its own OS, but the actual underlying hardware has its own OS, and that's the host one.
And that's not what we're looking at.
You don't need to monitor that one.
That's up to Azure to do or your cloud provider.
We're looking at the guest one, the one we actually can control.
So the operating system is going to need a couple of tools installed, so our agents.
So we'll want to install the log analytics agent so we can use that with log analytics.
We'll probably want to install the dependency agent.
That allows us to monitor processes on the machine.
So those are the programs that are running.
So like, you know, let's say MySQL, Redis, maybe you have a Rails app, whatever.
And so that's that.
And I just want you to know that these agents can be installed anywhere.
So it can be installed on Azure, on-premise, or even on other cloud providers like AWS.
If you want performance counters, you're going to have to install the diagnostic extension, which is, I think, a good thing to do.
And just to make note, the log analytics agent is going to store that data into logs, then you can use that log analytics later.
If you want to have the, or store the health state information, then you're going to be using the Azure diagnostic extension, and then they're going to put that in Azure storage.
And if you want to use Azure Event Hub, so Event Hub is a way of connecting your app to other destinations.
You're going to stream it, but you're going to need the diagnostic extension for that.
All right.
Let's take a look at Azure resources and how we're going to monitor those.
So you're going to have resource logs, and these provide insights to internal operations for Azure resources.
And these logs are automatically created for you, but you will have to set diagnostic settings to specify destination for them to be collected for each resource.
For metrics, you're going to get those automatically.
You don't have to do any additional work to configure them.
And you're going to be able to analyze those in Metrics Explorer.
For your log data, you're going to use log analytics to look for trends and other analyses.
You can also copy your platform metrics to logs for analysis.
And your resource logs are going to be archived
It's Azure Storage for long-term backup.
If you want to use or trigger or send your data to other destinations, you can use Event Hubs.
That's generally what Event Hubs is for.
So there you go.
Taking a very quick look at how we monitor our Azure subscription.
This is going to be for the service health of different resources that you're using, like are they okay, are they running, and things about Azure Active Directory.
So that's about it.
Take a look at our Azure tenant and how we would monitor that.
And if you remember our Azure AD section, that's where we define tenant because tenant is
highly coupled to Active Directory.
And so this is going to be for tenant-wide services, such as Active Directory, so reporting that contains history of sign-in activity, audit trails of changes made within a particular tenant, things like that.
So there you go.
So last on our list here is custom sources.
And basically, if none of the other previous categories fit where you want to collect data, this is where you can just collect data using the Azure Monitor API.
And so basically, you're using a REST client, and then it's going to store it in analytics at log analytics or Azure Monitor.
So it's just really custom data, custom storage.
So there's two fundamental types of data that we care about when working with Azure Monitor, and that is logs and metrics.
And so Azure has two services to deal with that.
One is called Azure Monitor Logs.
And so this service collects and organizes log performance data for monitored resources.
Data logs are consolidated from different sources into workspaces, which we'll talk about.
Platform logs from Azure services is something it'll collect.
It'll collect also log performance data from VM agents.
The usage and performance data from applications also can be consolidated, and these workspaces can be analyzed together using a query language, which we definitely cover in this course.
And you work with these log queries and the results interactively using a sub-service called Log Analytics, which is something we'll definitely be covering.
Then there's Azure Monitor Metrics.
So this is for the metric side.
So collect numeric data from monitor resources into time series database.
Metrics are numerical values collected at regular intervals and describe some aspects of a system at a particular time.
Lightweight and capable of supporting near real-time scenarios, useful for alerting and fast detection of issues.
And you can analyze them interactively using Metrics Explorer.
And we cover that as well.
So really, these two services are like the data stores or the databases for the respected types of data.
And then each of them have the sub-services, which is for exploring and some other additional services, but let's get into that more detail now.
So, when you use Log Analytics, you're going to probably want a workspace, and this is a unique environment for Azure Monitor Log Data.
Each workspace has its own data repository and configuration and data sources and solutions that are configured to store their data in a particular workspace.
So, it's really interesting because if you go over to Azure Monitor, you can use Log Analytics without creating a workspace, but I believe that if you want to isolate a lot of your data and...
install maybe collect data outside of Azure services for other things, you're going to need a workspace.
And it's going to also have a lot more robust options.
So that's something you're going to end up doing is creating workspaces, and it's a good habit to do.
But there's not a lot to talk about there.
But let's move on to actual the query language, which is really the meat of log analytics.
I want to quickly touch on log analytics.
And so this is a tool used to edit and run queries within Azure Monitor logs.
And so the idea is it kind of looks like something you would use to connect to a database because it really is structured like a database with tables and columns and things like that.
And it has its own query language called KQL.
And the idea is that you input your queries and it's going to output results for you.
And that's something we're going to look at in greater detail is that
KQL language so that we know how to use that panel.
Let's go talk about workspaces.
Let's take a closer look at Kusto and its query language.
So Azure Mono Logs is based off of the Azure Data Explorer, and along came with it is the Kusto Query Language, also known as KQL, and this is the way we're going to filter and sort and do things with our logs.
So Kusto is based on a relational database management system, and it supports entities such as database, tables, and columns.
It also has this thing called clusters.
And KQL actually has a lot of utility in Azure because it's not just in Monitor logs and Data Explorer.
You can use it in log analytics, log alert rules, workbooks, dashboards, logic apps, PowerShell, Azure Monitor log APIs.
So it's definitely something you're going to be using across the board in Azure.
And so they have some basic operators.
They have lots of operators that you can use.
So you can do calculated columns, searching and filtering on rows, group by aggregates, join functions.
And we're going to be looking at a lot of the operators in more detail after this slide here.
But anyway, the queries execute in the context of a Kusto database that is attached to a Kusto cluster.
And we will talk about clusters, database tables, and columns up next.
Let's take a look at what makes up something for Kusto.
And so we have a bunch of entities here, clusters, database, tables, columns, and functions.
And so I have this nice visual to help us kind of see how they all work together.
So at the top we have clusters, and these are entities that hold multiple databases.
You can also have multiple clusters, but it's not just not being shown there in that graphic.
Then you have the databases themselves.
These are named entities that hold tables and store functions.
You have tables, these are named entities that hold data, and a table has an ordered set of columns and zero or more rows of data, each row holding one data value for each of the columns of the table.
Then there are the columns themselves, and these are named identities that have a scalar data type.
Columns are referenced in the query relative to the tabular data stream, and that is the context of the specific operator referencing them.
Then we have stored functions, and these are named entities that allow reuse of Kusto queries or query parts.
And then you've got these external tables, and these are tables that live outside of your cluster.
I think that you're referencing them from storage accounts and they're in BLOB storage, so I think they could be like CSV files and stuff like that.
But these external tables are used for exporting data from Kusto to external storage, so storage accounts, as for querying external data without ingesting it actually into Kusto.
So hopefully that gives you an idea of the lay of the land there.
Let's take a look at the type of data types that we can use in Kusto, but let's just define what scalar and data types are.
So scalars are quantities that are fully described by a magnitude or numerical value alone.
So the idea is that it just means like a single value.
Then you have data types, and a data type defines how a piece of data is interpreted.
So an integer number could be a data type.
If you've ever used programming languages like data types and stuff like that, or an SQL database, you should be familiar with those.
So in Kusto, data types are used for various things, so they can be for columns or function parameters that expect specific data types that they want them to be.
And so let's just go through the quick list of data types, because there are quite a few here, and I've summarized them quickly.
So the first is Boolean, and this represents a true or false value.
Then you've got date times or date, and this represents a date.
These are stored in UTC time zones.
You've got decimals.
These are numbers that like are 12.88, or something with a decimal in them.
You have integers, which is like a whole number.
Then you have longs, which are also integers, but with a greater range.
You have your GUIDs or UUIDs, and these are unique values.
So it's like a random hash there that you have.
And the idea is just so that you have unique values, but they're not like one, two, three, 4, 5, so people can't guess the size of your tables.
Then you have reals.
These are double precision floating point numbers.
So these are really, really big numbers, something you'd probably use if you're doing things with finance or numbers.
Then you have strings.
And these are unicode strings, and they're limited by default to 1 MB.
And the way you do them is you have them wrapped in quotations.
We have that hello world.
You have time spans.
These are interesting.
These are little time intervals represented.
So like 2D would equal 2 days, 30M would equal 30 minutes, 1 tick would equal 100 nanoseconds.
And they have a variety of those.
Then you have dynamic, and this is a special type that can do a bunch of things.
So it can accept primitive scalar data types.
So the idea is it's kind of like a
a data type that can accept any value, or it can accept an array of any value, or it can accept a property bag, which, if you're from the JavaScript world, looks like a JSON object, so you have a key and value, and it can even be nested.
And then last, which is a data type, but you're not setting these as your columns, which is the null, and that's a special value that represents a missing value.
And any of these data types can be a null value.
So like you look at Boolean, it can be true, false, or null, and datetime can be a datetime or date or null, and that goes for all.
all of them.
Let's talk about Kusto control commands.
This is really part of the KQL language, but it's a way of kind of working with the databases and tables and stuff like that.
If you ever use Postgres, maybe you've done like forward slash du, or you have these commands that didn't really have to do with necessarily querying, but like managing the databases.
and tables and stuff, that's what control commands are.
So I'll give you an example.
So here we have a control command to create a Kusto table.
So they always start with a period.
So period create table logs and then it makes 2 columns and that.
When you're using the query like log analytics and stuff like that, you can just type period and then start typing it.
It'll show you all the list of control commands.
It was really hard to find the documentation a full list, otherwise I would have picked some out for you.
But generally you can just kind of explore that way.
Or the most common ones you're going to come across is all going to be in the documentation, even though there's a very long list of control commands.
A very common one you're going to be using a lot is show.
So for example, you can do.show tables and then count the number of tables there are.
And so I just want to show you that if you type.show, it'll show you what it can take as a second parameter.
And there's a huge list there.
So just an idea like how you can work with control commands.
Take a look here at Kusto functions, and these are reusable queries or query parts, and Kusto supports several kinds of functions, the first being stored functions, which are user-defined functions, and these are stored and managed as one kind of database schema entity.
Then, just to define user-defined functions one step further, they come in two categories.
We have scalar functions, so these have
have input scalar data types and output scalar data types, and then tabular functions.
So these take input tabular data and they output tabular data.
Tabular data is just when you're working with multiple rows in a table.
Then you have query-defined functions, which are also user-defined functions that are defined and used within the scope of a single query.
So very similar to stored functions, but it's all based on scope.
Okay?
Then the last on our list here is built-in functions, which are hard-coded, and these are defined by Kusto and cannot be modified users, and they just give you a lot of utility.
Let's take a look at some of these built-in functions, starting with special functions.
So select Kusto entities.
So you might want to say, I want to select a cluster, and then I want to select a database, and then that table.
Then you have aggregate functions, which perform calculations on a set of values and return a single value.
So maybe you want to do a count.
So you see where it says count and parentheses.
Then you have Windows functions, and these operate on multiple rows and records in a row.
And so one really popular one is row number.
And so this could count the number of rows.
Maybe you have to figure out the row numbers in relation to your query.
And so that's something you could do there.
Let's take a look at some scalar operators.
And there's quite a few here.
And these are for working with scalar data types to do comparisons.
And there's a bunch of different categories, so let's just quickly go through them here.
The first one is byte-wise operators.
That's where you're working with zeros and ones and flipping them around to do different things.
So you've got the binary end, the not, the or, the shift left, the shift right.
The XOR, and these make a lot of sense if you know how to work with binary math.
If you don't, don't worry about them, but I just want you to know if you do, they're there for you use.
Next are logical operators.
So this is what you're going to be more familiar with, like equality.
So equals, inequal, and or.
So those are pretty darn simple.
Then you have date, time, and time span arithmetic.
And so we have add or subtract date times.
You can do that.
You can add, subtract, divide, or multiple time spans.
So add one day plus two day makes 3 days.
Then you have numerical operators.
These work on ints, longs, and reels.
So you can add, subtract, multiply, and divide.
You can do module where it's determining whether it's a whole number or not, or divisible by a whole number.
So like let's say you have 17 and you put it through there.
You say module 17 by like modulus 2.
If it's not divisible by two, like perfectly resolves into zero, it will return either zero or one.
Then you have less, greater, equal, not equal, less or equal than.
greater or equal.
So you got the idea there.
Equals to one of the elements.
So that's in.
So you do the in.
It's very familiar if you're used to using SQL.
Then you have the opposite where you put an exclamation in front of it.
Actually, there's a lot of extra operators that just have the same thing with an explanation to mean the opposite, especially with string operators.
So here's a bunch of string operators and they almost all have exclamations, a variant with exclamation in front of them.
Then you have your between operators.
This matches the input that is inside an inclusive range.
So you can say between 1 and 10 or between these date times.
So there you go.
Let's take a look at Kusto tabular operators.
And I really want you to pay attention to this one because this is where all the power of KQL happens.
So these perform comparisons against a bunch of rows.
That's why it's called tabular operators.
And there's a lot of them, and we're going to look at the most common ones, because it would take me forever to go through all of them, and you're not going to remember them all, so let's just look at the ones we actually care about working with.
So, the first is count, this returns the count of rows in the table.
Then you have take, this returns up to a specified number of rows of data.
You have sort, this...
will take the rows of the input into the order by one or more columns.
So you see by damage property descending, so it's just sort.
Then you have project, returns a specific set of columns, and where filter a table to subset of rows that satisfy A predicate.
Before we move on to the next slide, I just want to point out, like if you've worked with SQL, these are very familiar, right?
Like take is like limit, sort is like order by, project is like select, okay?
Moving on to the next one here, we have top returns the first N records sorted by specified columns.
This is kind of like a shorthand.
I think it makes take and sort and just abbreviates it to one line.
You have extend creates a new column by computing a value.
So notice that it says duration equals end time minus start time, and then we're using duration somewhere else.
Then you have summarize, aggregate groups of rows, that's kind of like group by in regular SQL.
And then renders, so renders results as a graphical output.
And to me, that's a really cool one.
Moving on to metrics, we're going to be looking at Metrics Explorer.
So, Metrics Explorer is a subservice of Azure Monitor that allows you to plot charts, visualize correlating trends, and investigate spikes and dips in metric values.
So, the idea is you can create a really cool graph like that, and you can make a variety of different ones based on how you want to chart it out.
Let's talk about how we define one of these metric visualizations in Metric Explorer.
So you've got this cool bar, and the idea is you've got to fill it all the way to the end, and then that will visualize it for us.
The first is the scope.
So you're going to open this up, and it's going to allow you to select resources.
So it'll show you like subscription and stuff like that and resource groups, but it always makes you select a resource at the end.
And some services you can select multiple resources, and some you can only select a single instance.
So, with storage account there, it's only going to be a single one there, so I had one called Dastrum Institute I made, and then there you're going to choose a namespace.
So, this is a specific group of metric data within a resource.
So, notice, like it makes sense for a storage account that it would show account, BLOB, file, queue, table.
It's going to vary based on your service.
Then, you actually have the metric you care about, so we have availability at...
aggress, ingress, et cetera, and a bunch of other things.
You're going to choose one of those.
And then you're going to choose how you want to aggregate it.
So average, min, max, et cetera.
And again, this is going to be totally different based on what resources you choose, but that's generally how it works.
Let's take a look here at Azure Alerts.
And this helps us be notified when there are issues found within the infrastructure or application.
And this allows us to identify and address issues before the users of your system notice them.
And so they come in three flavors.
We've got metric alerts, log alerts, and activity log alerts.
And when an alert is triggered, you can be notified or have it take action.
So here is kind of the anatomy of an alert.
And we have the alert rule.
This defines who we should monitor the service and the definition of when it is triggered, which is going to be the next part here.
So a resource such as a virtual machine, designated as the target resource, will emit signal.
So it's going to be emitting a data payload.
And it could be of the following types.
It could be a metric, a log, activity log, application insights.
You can kind of see how that ties to the types of alerts.
Then you have the criteria or logical tests.
This gets evaluated and determines, are we in a triggered state?
It could be like percentage CPU greater than 70%.
Then you have your action group, which contains actions.
And those actions will be performed when it is triggered.
And actions could be things like run an automation runbook.
Use Azure Functions, ITSM, Logic App, Webhooks, or Secure Webhook.
On the other side there, we have this box over here, and this is all about the state of your alert.
And so we have monitor condition, alert state.
So monitor condition is set by the system, and alert state is set by the user, but the idea that is there is so you can define where it is, because you might want to have a history of saying, okay, I've resolved this issue, so I'm marking this as closed, and that'd be like an alert state there.
And so there you go.
This is probably not going to be on your exam, but it's super cool to show, and it's only one slide away.
So let's talk about it, which are Azure dashboards.
These are virtual workspaces to quickly launch tasks for day-to-day operations and monitor resources and build custom dashboards based on projects, tasks, or user roles.
So the idea is you can go in here and you have like this little tile.
Editor, and you can drag stuff over, so you can see I can put a video in and a link to the help support and put a clock and some metrics I care about and some markdown, so it's a really good way of building out these customized dashboards based on a user role to really help you focus on what you have to deal with within your infrastructure on Azure.
Let's take a look at Azure Workbooks.
Just because this is in the scope of Azure Monitor, so we should cover it.
So Workbooks provide a flexible canvas for data analysis and the creation of rich visual reports within the Azure portal.
They allow you to tap into multiple data sources from Azure and combine them into a unified interactive experience.
And so the key word here is story.
It tells a story about the performance and availability about your applications and services.
So this thing kind of looks like a dashboard, but it isn't.
And it's highly customizable, but it's not very clear in here.
But really what it is, it's like the form of a document.
And the idea is that imagine that you have a document and then you can embed analytics in it that are real-time analytics so that you can visualize and kind of investigate and discuss performance and availability and stuff like that.
You can kind of think of it like if you have ever worked with Jupyter Notebooks, but it's really for performance and monitoring.
It's kind of like that, okay?
And these things are highly customizable and really useful.
And if you ever use Datadog, Datadog has its own thing.
I think they call them notebooks as well.
They instead of workbooks, they're called notebooks.
It's the same thing, but it's a really great tool for really understanding your performance.
Let's take a look here at Application Insights, and this is an Application Performance Management Service.
So, it's an APM and it's a sub-service of Azure Monitor.
Let's talk about what APMs are.
So, these are monitoring and they do monitoring and management of performance and availability for software apps.
APM strives to detect, diagnose complex application performance problems.
to maintain an expected level of performance.
So why use Application Insights?
Well, it automatically detects performance anomalies and includes powerful analytics tools to help you diagnose issues and to understand what users do with your app.
Designed to help you continuously improve performance and usability.
Works for apps for.NET, Node.js, Java, Python, hosted on on-premise, hybrid, or any public cloud.
And I know that it works for other ones that are not part of the supported languages.
So there's one for Ruby, but that's
This is like Azure's only providing official support for a bunch of languages, but you might still have libraries out there for them.
And it integrates with your DevOps processes and can monitor, analyze telemetry from mobile apps by integrating with Visual Studio App Center.
And if you're running an app, you definitely want to have an APM installed.
If you ever use Datadog or Skylight or New Relic, that's what APMs are or what those providers offer.
But let's take a closer look here.
And this is kind of an example of an application.
And what you're going to see is that we have a front end, a back end, and workers just to kind of represent how you can instrument your applications.
And when we say instrument, it just means install like this piece of code that runs on it to send data back to Application Insights.
And the idea is that when you instrument it, you're just installing the instrument package SDK.
Or in some cases, you can just turn it on where it's supported.
So you don't necessarily have to install it in an app.
You might just press a button.
and it will install it within Azure services.
And there's many ways that you can view your telemetry data.
So the idea is that the agents send that information to Application Insights, and then you're going to be able to leverage that in alerts, Power BI, Visual Studio, REST API, continuous exports.
A lot of services can ingest Application Insights.
Apps can be instrumented from anywhere, so if you're running on AWS, you can install it on your servers there.
When you set up application sites monitoring for your web apps, you create an application site resource in Microsoft Azure, so it's a physical resource.
And you open this resource in the Azure portal in order to see and analyze telemetry collected from your app.
And the resource is identified by the instrumentation key, also known as the IKEY.
And I just got a big old list here just to tell you all the things you can do with it.
So, what does Application Insight monitor?
Well, request rates, response time, failure rates, dependency rates, response times, failure rates, exceptions, page views, load performance, AJAX calls, user and sessions count, performance counters, host diagnostics, diagnostic trace logs, custom events metrics.
So there you go.
That's a big old list.
And on the right-hand side is where can I see my telemetry?
And we saw a little list, but let's go through the big list.
And that's smart detection and manual alerts, application map, profiler, usage analysis, diagnostic search for instance data, metrics explorer for aggregated data, dashboards, live metric streams, analytics, Visual Studio, Snapshot Debugger, Power BI, REST API, continuous export, and there you go.
So you can see that it can collect
and you can use it in a lot of places.
Definitely, install if you're using or you're running a web application.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're looking at Azure Monitor Cheat Sheet.
This one's a three-parter, so let's jump into it.
Azure Monitor's a comprehensive solution for collecting, analyzing, and acting as telemetry for your cloud on-premise environments.
And even though I don't have it in the slide here, it is an umbrella service.
I mean, there's a lot of things underneath this, and that's why we have 3 pages of information.
It can create visual dashboards, smart alerts, automated actions, log monitoring.
To obtain observability, you need to know metrics, logs, and traces.
You can use them all together using them in isolate, but that does not give you observability.
Metrics is a number that is measured over a period of time.
Logs is a text file that contains event data, which was happening.
And traces is a history of requests that travels through multiple apps and services, so we can pinpoint performance or failures.
Azure Monitor collects 2 fundamental types of data, some sources, logs and metrics, which kind of matches up with our theoretical information here, right?
So Azure Monitor logs collects and organizes log and performance data for monitoring resources.
Data logs are consolidated from different sources into workspaces, platform logs and Azure services, logs and performance data and virtual machine agents.
Usage and performance data for applications can be consolidated in a workspace.
You can be analyzed.
They can be analyzed together using a sophisticated query language, which we'll talk about here in a moment, or review, I suppose.
Work with log queries and their results interactively using log analytics.
Azure Monitor Metrics collects, and that's the second part here, right?
So the two fundamentals.
Azure Monitor Metrics collects numeric data from monitored resources in a time series database.
Measures are numerical values collected at regular intervals and describe some aspects of a system.
Them at a particular time, lightweight and capable of supporting near real-time scenarios, useful for learning and fast detection of issues.
You can analyze them interactively via the Metrics Explorer.
On to page two, Log Analytics is a tool in the Azure portal used to edit and run log queries with data in the Azure Monitor logs.
Log Analytics is used a language called KQL.
Log Analytics.
I think that's Kusto, right?
So Log Analytics workspace is a unique environment for the monitor logs data.
Each workspace has its own data repository and configuration.
Data sources and solutions are configured to store in their workplace.
And I really wish I put the word data lake in here.
It's not important for the associate, but for other exams, it helps you understand if you think of it as a data lake.
Azure Monitor Logs is based on the Azure Data Explorer, and log queries are written using the Kusto query language.
KQL can be used in a log analytics, log alert rules, workbooks, Azure dashboards, and all over the place.
Kusto is based on a relational database management system, so you'll see database tables and columns.
Some query operations include calculated columns, searching and filtering on rows, grouped by aggregates, storing functions.
If you're used to using SQL, you know what I'm talking about.
Kusto queries execute in the context of some Kusto database that is attached to a Kusto cluster.
Kusto is generally composed of the following entities.
Clusters, database tables, columns, functions.
Let's talk about them quickly here.
Clusters are entities that hold databases.
Databases are named entities that hold tables and stored functions.
Stored functions are named entities that allow reuse Kusto queries or query parts.
Tables are named entities that hold data.
Columns are named entities that hold scalar data types.
And then you have external tables, which are identities that reference data stored outside the Kusto database.
These both count as tables.
That's why it's not in the list up here.
But generally, these are pretty self-explanatory.
Metric Explorers is a sub-service of Azure Monitor that allows you to plot charts, visualize correlating trends, and investigate spikes and dips in the metrics values.
To visualize a metric, you need to define the scope, the namespace, the metric, and the aggregation.
We're on to the last page here.
Alerts notify you when issues are found within your infrastructure or application.
They allow you to identify address issues before the users or system notice them.
Azure has three kinds of alerts, metrics, logs, and activity log alerts.
Sorry, there is a diagram.
If you remember our follow along, I actually break down all the structure of an alert.
You should go review that.
I didn't put in the cheat sheet because it just would have been too much here.
Azure dashboards are a virtual workspace to quickly launch tasks for day-to-day operations and monitor resources.
Azure workbooks provide a flexible canvas for data analysis and the creation of rich
Visual reports within the Azure portal it tells, and justice to highlight what Azure workbooks are for, it tells a story about the performance availability about your applications and services.
Then we have Application Insights, and this is an application performance management, an APM service, and it is a sub-service of Azure Monitor.
That's why all these things are under Azure Monitor.
Automatically detects performance anomalies, includes powerful analytics tools to help you diagnose issues to understand what users do with your app.
Designed to help you continuously improve performance and usability.
Works for apps on the.NET, Node.js, Java, Python, hosted on-premise, hybrid, and public cloud.
Works everywhere, basically.
Integrates with your DevOps processes, can monitor and analyze.
from mobile apps by integrating the Visual Studio App Center.
To use Application Insights, you need to instrument your application.
To instrument, you need to install the instrument package SDK or enable Application Insights using Application Insights agents when supported.
Apps can be instrumented from anywhere.
When you set up your Application Insights monitoring for your web app, you create an Application Insight resource in Azure Monitor.
You open the resource in the Azure portal to
Order in order to see and analyze telemetry collected from your app, and last the resource is identified by the instrumentation key, the I key, so there you go.
Let's take a look here at Azure Backup Service.
And this is a backup layer that spans multiple Azure services.
So you're not going to be able to type up in the search bar in services for Azure Backup Service.
Nothing's going to show up.
Where it is going to show up is under individual services.
And it probably will have like a backup tab.
And from there, you can enable backup and set a bunch of options.
So what can you do with Azure Backup Service?
You can back up on-prem, your Azure VMs, your Azure files.
SQL servers that are running on Azure VMs, SAP HANA databases running on Azure VMs, Azure databases for Postgres server.
And so why would you want to use Azure Backup as opposed to rolling your own or using a third-party provider?
Well, it's very easy to offload your on-premise backup systems.
You can easily back up any kind of VM.
It scales really well.
You get unlimited data transfer, so there's no limit and no charge.
And to me, that's an amazing benefit there.
It will keep your data secure, so it has built-in security at rest and in transit.
It has a centralized monitoring management tool.
It has app-consistent backups, meaning that you can restore an app back to an exact state.
It has automatic storage management, and it has a lot of storage options.
So there you go.
And again, you know, you just can't search for it.
It's directly integrated with a lot of services.
Let's take a look at Azure Recovery Service Vault.
So Azure Recovery Services is kind of a layer of backup stuff, kind of like Azure Backup Service, but it has a concept of vaults.
And vaults is a storage entity in Azure that houses data and recovery points created over time.
And so the idea is you're going to be copying your data or configuration information for your VMs, workload servers, or workstations.
And this is going to allow you to back up a variety of different Azure services, such as VMs for both Linux and Windows, Azure SQL databases, and it supports integrations with a lot of different kinds of services, like System Center, Data Protection Manager, Windows Server, Azure Backup, and a whole list of others.
In terms of feature set, it has enhanced capabilities to help secure backup data, central monitoring for your hybrid IT environments.
It's going to have role-based access controls, so you can give it fine-tuned controls of what people can access in the vaults.
It'll have soft delete, so just make sure you don't end up deleting things by accident.
It's going to have cross-region restore, and so that's generally what vaults are.
Now let's take a look here at the MARS agent, which stands for Microsoft Azure Recovery Services.
Azure is weird like this, where sometimes they'll add the word Microsoft in front of it, or they won't, and this will change the initialism, but it really is the...
the same service, so just don't be thrown off by that one word.
But this agent, which can be installed on your virtual machines or your on-premise machines, help you backup files, folders, and system state only for Windows servers.
So just to give you a little visual there, imagine you have your own on-premise machine, and it has the Mars agent installed on that machine, and then you have your own VM running your own VNet, and it has the Mars agent installed.
It's going to back that stuff up to the Azure Service Recovery Vault.
And so another thing you need to know is that the Mars agent is also known as the Azure Backup Agent, which is really confusing because you'll see both in the documentation, you'll think they're two separate things, but the same thing.
This also makes me think that Azure Backup and Azure Recovery Services are the same thing, but I don't have any definitive proof, so that's just what it is.
But it doesn't seem to really matter, but it just shows you how things can get confusing in Azure.
The Mars agent does not support Linux operating systems, so you did see previously that Azure Resource Recovery Service is able to back up Linux virtual machines.
How it does that, I don't know, but it's clearly capable of storing those in the vault.
But really, we just need to focus on the Windows side here.
To install the agent, what you're going to need to do is create yourself a vault, because it has to back up to a vault.
You need to create a backup policy, which we'll look in the next slide.
You'll probably have to configure a secure route in case you're connecting to your on-premise.
You'd use ExpressRoute.
Maybe you want to make sure that the backup stays within the Azure network, so you might need to create a private endpoint.
These are totally optional or required, depending on your use case.
You'll have to download the MARS agent.
You'll have to install and register the agent to your Windows machine.
So there you go.
Let's take a look at how we would make an Azure backup policy.
So what you're going to do is you're going to go into your vault and you're going to click on backup policy.
And then the first thing you'll do when creating your policy is choose whether you want to choose a Postgres database or an Azure VM.
I don't know why there's no other options but the Postgres server, but those are the two options we have.
And then you're going to have this nice big form, which I've expanded out to show you all the options.
And so you're going to choose the frequency of your backup.
You're going to choose how many snapshots you want to retain.
And then you have these retention ranges.
So the idea is that there's like daily, it says weekly, monthly, and yearly backup points.
So you're defining those points there.
And that's all there really is to it.
So there you go.
Let's talk about Azure Site Recovery.
And this is a hybrid.
which means on-premise to cloud, backup solution for site-to-site recovery.
So ASR is one of the tools useful for your business continuity and disaster recovery strategy.
So BCDR.
And I just threw that line in there because of that initialism, and you might see that language used in the future, whether it's...
in an exam or on the job, so I figured why not put that in there.
And so site recovery replicates workloads from a primary site.
Generally, this would be your on-premise, but it doesn't have to be, to a secondary site.
In case the primary site suffers a failure, site recovery will failover to the secondary site to ensure the continuation of services.
So it can replicate between Azure VMs.
So if you want to do cross-region replication, that's what you could do.
It can replicate Windows, Linux, or any OS.
It can go from on-premise to Azure.
That's usually the case that people are using it for.
It can actually replicate it between different cloud service providers.
Not sure how it does that, but they say that it can do it, so that's why I'm telling you that here.
And it can work with VMware, Hyper-V, and physical machines.
And then I just want to leave you with a couple of terms.
Because I didn't really do like a concept on backup strategies and disaster recovery in this section, but I just wanted to introduce you to two terms you really do need to know.
And that is recovery point objectives, RTOs.
This means how quickly you can recover from a backup after experiencing a disaster and recovery time objectives.
So RPOs, how often you back up.
So how much data loss can you tolerate?
And those two terms are just really like when you're talking about creating a strategy for backup, those are the two
things that you usually need to define, okay?
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from ExamPro, and in this follow-along, we're going to be looking at backup solutions for Azure.
So let's make our way all the way to the top here and launch ourselves a virtual machine that we are going to be using as a means to backup.
So what I'll do is create a new group here, and we will call it Picard.
And we'll call this Virtual Machine Picard.
And scrolling on down here, yeah, I want to stick with the Windows Server 2019 Gen.
2.
So go over here, select it as Generation 2 there.
And for the machine, you want to make sure it's a B2S because you need at least two VPCUs and 4 gigabytes of RAM to launch a Windows server there.
For the user, it's going to be Azure user.
For the password, capital T, Testing123456.
Capital T, Testing123456.
We'll have RDP.
I'm not sure if we'll end up using it.
But if we do, we have that open.
We'll go ahead and go to the review page.
Wait for it to allow us to hit Create.
Give it a moment.
Great, we'll hit Create.
And then we'll give it a moment to see that it is deploying.
And if it's deploying, I'll see you back here in a moment.
Great, so it looks like our virtual machine is ready to go here.
So what we'll do is go all the way to the top here and type in backups.
We go to Vaults directly, but let's take a look here at the backup center.
where we can kind of have a bit of an overview of stuff.
So the idea is we have vaults where we're going to store our backups.
We can create backup jobs, backup policies.
So let's get to it and 1st create ourselves a vault.
So we'll go ahead here and create ourselves a new vault.
And we have two options.
We have recovery services vault or a backup vault.
So
The difference here is that one is just for backing up things like databases, disks, and et cetera, where recovery services is more like a site-wide recovery.
So you're going to notice it includes virtual machines and all these other stuff.
Generally, you'll probably want to go with recovery services vault because it is just basically a new version of the backup vault.
So let's go ahead and do that.
And we'll place this in our Picard resource group there.
And we'll just say Picard backup.
or vault, there we go.
And we'll go ahead and hit review and create, and we'll go and hit create there.
And we'll just give it a moment there to deploy.
All right, so our recovery services vault is ready, and we'll go ahead and click backup, and down below it'll ask us what kind we are running.
So we have Azure Stack and on-premise.
It's just Azure, and we have a virtual machine, so we'll go ahead and hit backup.
a backup.
And notice that we'll have to set up a backup policy.
And here we have a default one.
But let's actually go make a new one so we can kind of learn some of the settings that we can set.
So we can say the frequency, the time, et cetera.
Probably want to set this to my time zone.
So I'm in Toronto, if I can find it here, which I believe is negative 5.
I was trying to type to see if I could do that, but I wasn't getting there too well.
We'll just say Central Canada there.
That's okay.
It's off by an hour, but that's close enough.
And you can have weekly, monthly, and yearly backups, but we're going to stick with the daily backup for 30 days.
And this is okay.
We don't have to enter that in.
We'll hit All right.
Okay.
And now we can add our virtual machine.
So we'll go here and select Picard, hit OK, enable backups.
Please select at least one that has backups enabled.
So what we'll do is open up our Azure tab here, make our way over to our virtual machine, just make sure that that stuff is enabled.
So we'll go over here.
And we'll go to backups.
And here, we can actually even set it from here.
So I guess we'll select our existing vault here.
We'll say enable backups.
Let's set it up with a default one, right.
So I'm a bit surprised we couldn't do it that way.
But we'll make our way back here.
As long as it works.
That's the thing with Azure.
It's just you'll do something and then you'll find that you have to do it slightly different.
But we'll just wait until that's done there.
So after waiting a very short while, it looks like our backups are turned on.
So if we were to go to our overview and go to backups, you can see we have one backup item.
If we go over to our backup items, we'll see under virtual machines we have Picard.
We did set the default policy.
So I guess if we wanted to switch that out, we probably could if we just go back.
And let's just go create a policy of our own just so that we are familiar with that there.
And we'll say an Azure virtual machine one.
So my special policy.
Okay.
And this is for 180 days.
We can go ahead and hit create.
And once that policy is deployed, we'll be able to associate.
I can't remember if this will be super fast, but we'll give it a moment here.
Yep, it is super fast.
And then once we have that policy, we can go into it and then start assigning things to it.
Actually, I think when I made the lecture content, I don't even remember there being a backup center.
So to me, this is all a little bit new.
So maybe I'll go back in up to the slides because I usually say there is no centralized service, but they have one now.
So that's pretty darn good.
So for associated items, we don't fetching data for services completed.
So I'm just trying to figure out how we can change that policy there.
go to backups and we can just change it over here.
I'm not sure how to switch out the policy, but I know at least if we want to do backup now, we just press that there.
It's really not that important to know how to swap out a policy.
It's just more so the fact that you know what a backup policy is and you can apply it to machines and things like that.
Yeah, so there we go.
We just had our own backup there.
And you
Yeah, there's not much else here to look at, but there you go.
So that's backup policies.
So I guess what we'll do is go ahead and tear all this down.
And so that was our book card there.
We'll go ahead and delete this resource group.
And there you go.
Hey, this is Angie Brown from ExamPro, and we're looking at Azure Backup Cheat Sheet, so let's jump into it.
Azure Backup Service is a backup layer that spans multiple Azure services, such as on-premise Azure VMs, Files, SQL Server, SAP HANA, Azure Database for Postgres.
Azure Backup is directly integrated with these services, so you're not going to find...
You're not going to find it by searching based on the service name.
You're just going to have to know that it's there.
Offload onto on-premise backups, backup your VM, scales easily, get unlimited data transfer, keep your data secure, centralized monitoring and management, app consistent backups, automatic storage management, multiple storage options.
It does everything.
Azure Recovery.
Service ARS Vault is a storage entity in Azure that houses data and recovery points created over time.
It has enhanced capabilities to help secure backup data.
It has central monitoring for your hybrid IT environment.
It can use RBAC.
It has soft delete.
It has cross-region restore.
It's a really great service.
Then we have Azure Recovery Service, also known as MARS.
It's an agent, so that means it gets installed on a machine.
It's responsible for doing the backups.
It can back up files, folders, system states on your on-premise machines or Azure VMs.
Backups are stored in the recovery service fault in Azure.
MARS is also known as the Azure Backup Agent, and that gets really confusing if you don't know the two.
And the MARS agent does not support Linux operating systems, but no surprise, because most things in Azure does not support Linux.
Azure Site Recovery, ASR, is a hybrid on-premise to cloud backup solution for site-to-site recovery, and that is everything you need to know for Azure Backup.
Hey, this is Angie Brown from Exam Pro, and we're looking at Azure Container Instances, also known as ACI, and this allows you to package, deploy, and manage cloud applications using containers, or the way I like to think of it, as fully managed Docker as a service.
Azure Container Instances allow you to launch containers without the need to worry about configuring or managing the underlying virtual machines.
And you're going to be able to design isolate containers for simple applications, task automations, and build jobs.
Let's talk about some of the reasons why you'd want to use containers over VMs.
So containers can be provisioned within seconds, where VMs will take several minutes.
Containers are billed per second, where VMs are billed per hour, so you'll save a lot more money.
Containers have granular and custom sizing of VPC
VPCUs, memory, and GPUs, where VM sizes are predetermined.
So those are the benefits between containers and VMs.
ACIs can be utilized for both Windows and Linux containers.
You can persist storage with Azure files using ACI containers.
And honestly, if you have containers or functions, you have to have an external storage mounted to persist.
It's just the way you do it.
ACIs are accessed via fully qualified domain names, which is one of the things I really appreciate about Azure services, because most of the services are like that.
Azure provides quick start images to help you start.
Launching example apps, but you can also source containers from Azure Container Registry, Docker Hub, and Privately Hosted Container Registries.
It looks like that the choice option there.
Let's just talk about container groups, because this is pretty much the only major component you have to worry about.
These are a collection of containers that get scheduled on the same host, and the containers...
The containers in a container group share lifecycle resources, local network storage volumes.
So the idea is that you have these tightly coupled containers.
So all of them act as a service within that container group.
So here you can see an example of a couple containers that are mounting Azure files on different directories there.
And underneath all of that is running on an Azure virtual machine.
Container groups are similar to Kubernetes pods.
Yeah, and it says similar to, but not really the same thing.
Multi-container groups can currently support only Linux containers, which is kind of a bummer, but that's just what it is.
And there are two ways to deploy a multi-container group.
You can use ARM templates when you need to deploy additional Azure service resources, or just a YAML file when you want to deploy, when your deployment only includes container instances.
Let's take a look at container restart policies, and what these do is allow you to change how the policies restart, and there's three different ways.
We have always, never, and on failure.
So the first one here, always, means always restart the container, and the idea is to keep your container running as long as possible.
The reason why you'd want that is if you're running a web server, some other providers would call that a service.
Then we have never, so run only one time.
This is great for background jobs, and so other providers
we just call this a task.
Then you have onFailure, so containers that encounter an error, that's when it should restart.
And so it's as simple as just choosing that option when you are creating that container.
Let's take a look at container environment variables, also known as nVars, that allow you to pass configuration details to your containers.
And you can do this through the portal, the CLI, PowerShell, which
That's always the case with Azure.
And so it's as simple as just putting in your key and your value.
And one other thing I want to point out is that you can also pass in secured environment variables.
So the idea is that sometimes you don't want them plain text.
So if you have like, see how that stripe secret key, you don't want anyone ever seeing that in production.
So the idea is that through, and I don't think you can do this through the portal, but you can do this through the CLI or PowerShell is provide the secure environment variables over the regular one, which isn't environment variables, and that way you can pass it securely.
it's never exposed to human eyes.
Let's talk about persisting storage.
And we talked about that a little while there when we were looking at Azure Files.
But containers are stateless by default.
So when a container crashes or stops, all state is lost.
To persist a state, you need to mount an external volume.
And there's quite a few different things we can mount Azure Files, secret volumes, empty directory, cloud Git repo.
So you got a few options
There, and to mount a file volume, you need to do this via PowerShell or CLI.
You're going to give the following details.
So, when you launch the container, there's going to be nothing in the portal, so you've got to do it this way.
All right.
Let's talk about some of the CLI options that we can use to troubleshoot our containers.
A lot of this stuff is probably accessible via the portal, but it's great to know how to do this via the CLI.
So the first thing is getting the logs.
So you can use az container logs, and that's going to bring you the logs back.
Then you can use az container attach.
And this is going to give you diagnostic information about when the container is starting up, probably with Cloudinit information.
Then you have az container exec, and this allows you to execute
remote commands, but what you can do is use bin sh, which actually will allow you to have an interactive container.
So it's like having the terminal right to the container, which is very, very, very useful.
And the last is just going grabbing metrics from Azure Monitor.
So azmonitor metrics list.
You could use the portal for that, but I just wanted to show you all those things because they might show up on the exam.
Hey, this is Andy Brown from Exam Pro, and we're going to take a look at Azure Container Instances.
So here it is.
So all we got to do is go to Container Instances.
We'll hit Add.
And the nice thing is that Azure provides us with a Hello World one, so it's very easy for us to get started.
It's a Linux machine, and it looks like it's pretty inexpensive there, so we'll stick with that.
I'm going to create a new group here.
We're going to call it Banana, and we'll name the container instance Banana.
And East US 2 seems fine to me.
You'll notice we're on a quick start image.
If we wanted, we could use something from the Docker Hub and provide our own link, but we'll just stick with the quick start image for today.
We're going to go ahead and hit next to networking just to see what we have as options.
You can make it public or private.
We'll go to advanced.
Hold on here.
Yep, those are just the ports you can expose.
We'll go to advance, and for the restart policy, we can set on failure always or never.
We can pass in environment variables, and I've covered this a lot more in detail in the lecture content, so we don't need to really dive deep into this.
And we'll go ahead and create this instance.
And so we'll have to wait a little while here, and I'll see you back in a moment.
Okay, and so after a short wait, our container instance is ready.
We'll go to that resource there and take a look around.
So on the left-hand side, we can go to our containers, and there we can see it running.
We can see the events down below of what's going on.
So you can see that it's pulled the image, it successfully pulled it, and then it started the container.
Some properties, nothing interesting there, the logs, if we wanted to see stuff, and if we wanted to connect to the instance, we could also go here and hit connect, which is kind of nice.
I don't have any purpose to do that right now, and it's also not going to work the way we're doing it, but I just wanted to show you had those opportunities.
You can do identity, so that means manage it with role-based access controls, but what I want to see is actually this.
Hello world working.
I'm assuming there must be a hello page.
I've never looked at it before, so we're going to go here, grab the public IP address, and paste it on in the top, and there we go.
So we have deployed an instance onto Azure Container Instances, or a container, I should say.
So nothing super exciting to talk about here, but we do need to know the basics there.
If we wanted to deploy other containers, it's just the one there, so that's all you really need to do.
But yeah.
So yeah, hopefully that gives you an idea there.
I'll just go back to the list here so we can see it.
And we'll go ahead and just delete that, probably do it for the resources on the left hand side, like I always like to do.
And we will go into banana here.
And we will delete banana.
And there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're looking at Azure Container Images Cheat Sheet, and this is a two-pager, so let's jump into it.
So ACI allows you to launch containers without the need to worry about configuring or managing the underlying virtual machine.
ACI is designed for isolate containers for simple applications, task automation, build jobs.
Containers can be provisioned within seconds where the VMs can take several minutes.
Containers are billed per second where VMs are billed per hour, so you get greater savings when you're using containers.
Containers have granular and custom sizing VPC
and GPU.
When VM sizes are predetermined, ACI can deploy both on Windows and Linux.
You can persist storage with Azure files.
ACIs are accessed via fully qualified domains.
So it's just like a domain name.
Then we have container groups.
These are a collection of containers that get scheduled on the same host machine.
The container is a container group share.
So you've got lifecycle resources, local network storage volumes.
Container groups are similar to Kubernetes pods.
Multi-container groups currently support only Linux containers.
This is one of the cases where it's not Windows, it's Linux, okay?
There are two ways to deploy multi-container groups.
You have that via an ARM template and YAML file.
I imagine you can do them via blueprints as well.
A container restart policy specifies what a container should do when their process has been completed.
ACI has three restart policies, always, never, and on failure, okay?
We'll go on to the second one here.
So Azure containers are stateless by default.
When a container crashes or stops, all state is lost.
To persist state, you need to mount an external volume.
You can mount the following external volumes, so either Azure File, Secret Volume, Empty Directory, or Cloud Git Repo.
For container troubleshooting, these are just Azure CLI commands you should really, really know.
So I'm just going to list them out here.
You've got az container logs, az container attached, az container exact, which is for execute, and az monitor metrics list.
So there you go.
That is the ACI.
AI Images Cheat Sheet: Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're looking at Azure Container Registry, also known as ACR, which create and maintain Azure Container Registries to store and manage your private Docker container images and related artifacts.
So Azure Container Registry is a managed private Docker registry service based on the open source Docker Registry 2.0.
And the idea here is that you can use container registries with your existing container development deployment pipelines.
And it also has this thing called Registry Task to build container images in Azure.
And the idea here is that you can pull images from your container registry to various deployment targets like Kubernetes, DCOS, which I forget what it stands for, but it's basically an
operating system for containers, Docker Swarm, and there's also many Azure services that directly support ACR, so AKS, Azure App Service, Azure Batch, Azure Service Fabric, and a lot more.
So it's just a matter of saying, hey, use this from ACR, and it works right away.
Developers can also push to Container Registry as part of a container development workflow with delivery tools such as Azure Pipelines and Jenkins, and it's so easy to push.
To Container Registry, there are many ways to work with ACR via the CLI, the Azure PowerShell, Azure Portal, Azure SDK, and there's also this really good extension called Docker Extension for Visual Studio Code, something you absolutely want to install, and maybe I'll make a full slide on it because I like it so much.
Let's take a look here at ACR Tasks, which allow you to automate OS and framework patching for your Docker containers.
And we have a few different options here.
So the first is Quick Tasks.
These allow you to push a single container image to a container registry on demand, and you don't need to be running a local Docker Engine installation to do it.
So that's a really good benefit.
You can also trigger some automated build actions.
So maybe you push some source code updates, you update the container base image, you want to do it on a timer that's on a schedule.
You can also have multi-step tasks, so you have to go through the various steps to complete that task.
For each ACR task, it has an associated source code context.
This is the location of the set source files used to build a container image or other artifact.
Tasks can take advantage of run variables, so reuse task definitions and standardized tags for images and artifacts.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're taking a look here at Azure Container Registry Cheat Sheet.
So ACR is a managed private Docker Registry service based on the open source Docker Registry 2.0.
It uses Azure Container Registries with your existing container development, or sorry, yeah, development and deployment pipelines.
Use Azure or use ACR tasks to build containers images in Azure.
Pull images from an Azure Container Registry to various targets.
And targets could be Kubernetes, DCOS, which is, I can't remember the name of the full name of that operating system, Docker Swarm.
For ACR tasks, this allows you to automate OS and framework patching for your Docker containers.
You can trigger them, you can trigger automated builds by source code, updates, updates to container-based images, triggers on a schedule.
You can create multi-step tasks.
Each ACR task has an associated code context.
and tasks can take advantage of run variables.
That's the end of it.
There you go.
See you in the next section.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exampro.
We're looking at Azure Kubernetes as a Service, also known as AKS, and this is a fully managed Kubernetes as a Service, as the name implies.
So Azure Kubernetes Service makes it simple to deploy a managed Kubernetes cluster in Azure, and it will manage for you the Kubernetes
master, the health monitoring, the maintenance, and you'll only have to maintain the agent nodes.
Now, AKS service is free, so you're not being charged for a control plane.
That's a big deal.
Other providers charge you like $100, $150 on a month-to-month basis just to have that control plane.
And here in Azure, it's free.
You're only paying for those agent nodes within the cluster, not the masters.
When you deploy an AKS cluster, Kubernetes master and all the nodes are deployed and configured for you, but you have the option to configure some additional features during your deployment process, like advanced networking, Azure AD integration, so you get...
role-based access controls with Kubernetes, monitoring, Windows Server containers are also supported with AKS.
And one thing I want to point out is like, why would you use AKS over ACI?
And that's when you need full container orchestration.
So you need service discovery across multiple containers, automatic scaling, and coordinated application upgrades.
If you're doing something simpler, just use ACI.
But if you need these...
these features, then this is where you're going to be using Kubernetes.
This is a feature that I really liked, so that's why I'm including it.
It's called Bridge to Kubernetes.
So this thing is an extension of Visual Studio or Visual Studio Code that allows developers to write, test, and debug microservice code on their development workstations.
So the idea is in Visual Studio Code, you're going to go ahead and install
that extension.
And what this is going to do is it's going to include a locally running service to your AKS cluster.
So sidestepping, creating a Docker Kubernetes configuration.
So just to give you a clear example, for the lifetime of the connection, a proxy is added to your cluster in place of your Kubernetes deployment that redirects requests to the service to your development computer.
When you disconnect, the application deployment will revert to using the original version of the deployment.
deployment running on the cluster.
Just to make this a little bit more clear, I'm going to get my pen out.
So imagine you had something running here, right?
We'll call it X.
And you're like, I want to test out or make changes to that.
And so I'm like, pull it to my local development, run it here, but it's still within the actual Kubernetes cluster, right?
So the idea is you've pulled this locally.
You can fiddle with it and then push it back, while always in the same cluster.
To me, that is super powerful, and so I thought that was worth the time to tell you about this feature.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we're going to learn how to launch a Kubernetes cluster here on Azure via Azure Kubernetes Service.
And so, before we go ahead to the Kubernetes Service, we have to make sure that we have...
The service registered for use, and the way we do that is via our subscriptions, so in the top type subscriptions, and we will go there, and I only have one subscription here, and then down below we have our resource providers, and if we start to type in Kubernetes...
We can see whether it's registered or not.
So without these registered, Kubernetes will just not work.
It's as simple as going here and clicking here with the register, but I figured it would be a good habit for us to start using the Cloud Shell more and getting used to PowerShell.
So I'm going to register these via Cloud Shell here.
So I'll go ahead and click that button there.
It's going to start a new session.
If it's the first time you've ever launched.
The cloud shell, it's going to ask you whether you want to use Bash or PowerShell.
We want to stick with PowerShell today.
And the first thing I want you to do is use the actual CLI that Azure has.
It's called AZ.
So if I type in AZ, it will print out some default information for me here.
But I want to just confirm that I'm in the account that I think that I'm in.
So we'll type in AZ account.
show, and by default that will return JSON.
To make this a bit more readable, I'm going to type in output table.
And so here we can see that this is my home tenant ID.
This is the tenant ID that I'm currently in, and this is the subscription I'm using.
The reason I'm showing you this is that it's very easy to get turned around when you're using the Cloud Shell because sometimes the portal does not reflect the changes you've made.
There might be a delay, and so this gives you an absolute confirmation that you are in the right place and you're not second-guessing yourself.
So now that we can see where we are, what we should do is run some PowerShell scripts here.
So if you pull up the Azure documentation, you go under PowerShell references and resources, you can get all the PowerShell commands, the AZ PowerShell commands that we can use.
And what we're looking at right now is the AZ resource provider.
Azure is very conventional with this naming, so it makes it really easy to find stuff.
If I was to type in AZ resource here,
provider.
You can see these are the three commands that we have available to us.
So let's give them all a go.
The first one I want to run is going to be called get Azure resource provider.
So we'll type in get AZ resource provider.
And I believe if I just leave that by default, it will return all of them for me.
Yeah, it does.
So that's all of them here.
And so we
What I want to do is I want to look at very particular ones.
And I think we can do that by using the provider namespace and the providing the actual name, which is over here.
So let's give that a go.
So I'm going to hit up on my keyboard and I'm going to type in hyphen or just hyphen provider namespace.
And I'm going to type in Microsoft.kubernetes.
And that should get me some information.
And so notice that it's returning more than one item here.
Anything that matches, it's going to return.
So we are getting multiples there.
So you can see that they are unregistered.
All right.
And so what we want to do is we want to register this for you.
So what I'm going to do is hit up and hitting Control A will bring me to the front or to the left here.
So Control A and Control E are very common commands when you're in terminal.
Those are two you should remember.
And I'm going to type in register.
And so that is going to go ahead and register that there.
And then we want it for configuration.
All right, and so that one is registered here.
So now if I go ahead and give this a refresh, these should be registered.
And this is what I mean.
I don't always trust the Azure portal.
It's a very flexible system, but it doesn't always tell you the truth.
If you're very paranoid here, you can just hit register here as well.
All right, but I'm pretty confident that we did trigger that registering action there.
And so that's just the portion of CloudShell that I hope you learned a bit there.
So it does take a bit of time for these to register, so we will wait a little bit here, and then we will proceed.
So just wait and just keep on checking until those are registered, okay?
And we'll proceed to the next part.
Yeah, and the mine are registered, so we're good to go.
All right, so let's go ahead and proceed to create our actual Kubernetes cluster.
So go all the way up here, click on Microsoft Azure, and we will type in Kubernetes in the top here, make our way over to the service.
We're going to go ahead and hit add, the Kubernetes cluster.
And so what I'm going to do is make a new resource group where I'm going to call this Borg, because anytime I think of containers, I always think of the Borg here.
Maybe we have to hit the create new button there.
And then I'll just give it the same name.
So we'll just call that Borg.
The region, US East, is fine for me.
We're going to keep it to the default T here.
And for production, it's recommended to have 3 nodes for development, which is what we're doing.
One node is good enough.
And one thing I definitely want you to do is change the node size, because this affects cost.
So if we open this up, it's not obvious where the cost is, but if you stretch these on over, we will eventually see the cost here.
There it is.
And notice by default, the DS2 version 2 is $136.
I want this to be as cheap as possible.
Just if I forget to turn off this cluster later on, I don't want to be paying a lot of money.
So that's what we're going to do here.
I'll go ahead and select that.
And now we're in good shape.
In our node pools, we'll leave this as the standard.
We do not need enable, we don't need virtual nodes.
We can leave this alone.
We can't do anything with it.
Here we can determine whether we want the authentication method to be the service principal, so that's the service itself, or system assigned managed identity.
I prefer the latter.
If you want to learn about these things, it's not so important, but you can click and read these links here.
We're going to stick with role-based access.
We'll stick with AKS Managed Azure Active Directory.
Encryption by default sounds good to me.
and we'll go to networking.
We'll leave the default settings as is.
You might have a conflict here, so you might have to change it because this is a fully qualified domain.
Think of like having a custom domain name.
So if it's taken, you might have to change it there.
All these other settings are totally fine.
We'll go into integrations here.
We don't have anything to register, or there's no containers registered for this example here, so we're not really worried about that.
We don't want to really worry about Azure Monitor at this point in time, so I'm just going to disable that.
We'll go ahead and go to next.
And we can put some tags.
I'm fine for that.
And we will wait for review and create to validate the process here.
Sometimes it's fast, sometimes it's slow.
What you have to be is patient.
And so we have a validation issue.
It could be with our DNS here.
The MV must have two cores or 4 gigabytes of memory.
So I guess I can't launch our cheaper option there.
So we'll go back there.
And I guess we need 2 cores.
So I guess we pretty much have to use what is here.
I mean this.
It said four cores, right?
What did it say?
Let's go back to that and try that again.
I've already forgotten.
We need 2 cores and 4 gigabytes of memory.
Okay.
So we want 2 cores.
So we'll just go up one more.
We'll go check the price on that.
$89, a bit better than before.
Okay.
And let's see if it takes this one here.
Great.
And so we'll go ahead and create that cluster.
And so this shouldn't take too long, but I will see you in a bit.
All right, so our cluster has finally created there.
And so what I want you to do is go ahead and go to your resource there.
And on the left-hand side, we want to make sure that our nodes are running.
Notice down below it says one node pool.
And so if we go also down here to node pools, we should be able to see that it is in a succeeded state.
That is what we're looking for.
And we have our single
Node there, most of the things with Azure, or sorry, with Kubernetes is done through the terminal, so there's not much we can actually do from here, so we will absolutely 100% have to open up Cloud Shell.
Now, if you want to do this in Bash or PowerShell, it's up to you, because we're just going to be using the...
Azure CLI, and it works in both.
The syntax is slightly different for system variables and things like that, but the CLI itself, the commands are identical.
So, to work with the Kubernetes, what we're going to need is to be using the azaks command.
So again, you can pull up the docs and go to the Azure CLI reference AKS, and we get a lot of detailed information.
So we were just looking at the node pool.
If we wanted to look at that ourselves, we could list it here and show it.
Let's go give that a try.
So I'm going to type in AZ AKS node pool list.
And I might have typed this wrong here.
Let's just hit up there.
And I'm going to get as much room as I need here because we don't need to see anything else.
The following are required.
Oh, right.
So you have to provide it some information.
So here, we named it, I named it the Borg.
Yours might be slightly different.
So I'll just call it Borg.
And the cluster name, I think, is the same.
So we'll call it Borg as well.
And while it's thinking there, I'm just going to double check the names.
I'm almost certain that those are correct.
But, oh yeah, there it goes.
It just takes some time.
All right, so we're getting some information.
And if you find it a bit easier to read, we can go to output table, which is something I do a lot.
There's probably some way to default it.
I can't remember how.
So yeah, so there we go.
And that was the same thing we looked.
There's one in the succeeded count.
So the next thing we should do is get the nodes.
So I think that's probably...
Actually, you know what?
I think we have to do credentials.
So if we go over to this here, I remember there's a command called get credentials.
Get the access credentials for managed Kubernetes clusters because we need to actually set that up first.
So it looks like we just need our name and our resource group to run that.
So that's what we're going to do.
And if you want to save yourself time, you can also just copy paste here.
Unless it doesn't like the copy paste, I'm just going to type it by hand.
And then the name was Borg.
And the resource group is also Borg.
Okay.
And so now it has context for that, so we can proceed to the next step here.
What we're going to do is just verify our connection is actually working.
And so now we're going to use kube CTL.
So that's kube CTL is the Kubernetes controller, and that's why we had to authenticate so that we could use it with that.
So just hit enter here.
And if this executes fine, then that means our credentials are great.
So great.
So we're able to talk to our Kubernetes cluster.
The next thing we want to do is set up a deployment.
So what we can do is deploy like a pre-made image.
So I'm just going to go here and type in kubectl create deployment.
I'm just trying to think what I'd want to deploy.
I wonder if we could deploy Apache or something.
Let me take a look.
So where these clusters would be probably would be on Docker Hub or like these images.
So I could go here and if I had Apache here, so it'd be like HTTPD or something like that.
Or we could do NGINX, I suppose.
Yeah, let's do NGINX.
I think that'll be easier to do.
So what we'll do is just go and type in create a kubectl create deployment.
nginx, and then we'll do image nginx.
Okay, and so it's created that deployment there.
And so the next thing we'll need to do is get our pods.
So we'll type in cube CTL get pods.
And here we can see that we have a single pod running, and there is our nginx.
And so now what we want to do is go ahead and do a deploy.
Okay, and our deployment's all good.
And I'm just trying to remember what we would do next.
Yeah, if we want to actually access this, we'd have to probably expose our thing here.
So we'll type in kubectl expose deployment nginx port 80, because we're not going to use, we're not going to be using
SSL here, and we'll just type in load balancer for the type.
All right, and so now that that's all set up, we can go ahead and do a get service on that.
And I've got to spell it right for it to work.
Great, and so our service is running.
So notice that it's also a load balancer type, and we get an external IP.
So now that we have that, I guess what we can do is go ahead and try to connect to it.
So I believe that this is the public IP.
So if I copy this here and make a new tab and paste that in there, there's our NGINX.
We could try this with Apache as well.
I don't know if we'll be successful, but we'll give it a go.
It doesn't hurt to do this more than once to get into the habit of it.
So what we'll do is we will go ahead and create an image again.
So if we just go back up to create, this time I'm going to use HTTP.
I think that's what it was.
Yeah.
So we'll do httpd.
And we have that there.
So we'll go ahead and create that deployment.
And we probably should check the pods so we can see what we got.
So now we have HTTPD pod.
Notice it has one of 1 running.
This one has zero of 1 running, and it's still creating the pod.
So we're going to go hit up.
Now the pod is now in a running state, so we're in good shape.
Let's go ahead and get deployments so we can see what we have here.
Great.
So we can see we have each one of 1 deployed.
And so now let's go ahead and expose the...
service there.
I think we can use load balancer again here.
That should probably work.
And now that we've done that, we'll go ahead and check on the services here.
And so this has its own IP address here.
If I'm right, I should be able to see the default Apache page.
Did I grab the right IP address here?
Oh, it's still pending.
Sorry.
I just grabbed the one that I saw.
So here it is.
There we go.
So it's as simple as that.
I thought we would see the default Apache page.
I'm not sure why we see it works, but that is totally fine.
It's probably just what is the default built into this module here, but it's not what I'm used to seeing.
So now that we're in that good shape, we'll just think, let's think about what we'll do next here, okay?
All right, so I think one more thing that we should probably try before cleaning everything up here is actually how do we scale out our pods and our nodes?
Because right now we're just running a single instance of each of these things, which are our nodes.
So before we can add more nodes, we need to add more pods.
And so that's what we're going to do first.
So what we'll want to do is I'm going to type in kube CTL scale, and we're going to add replicas.
And this is how many more pods we're going to have.
So we're going to go from one pods to, let's say, three pods.
And then we need to say what it's for.
So it's deployment, and we could do the Apache one, or I guess it's HTTPD.
And so what that will do is increase us to three pods.
If I go and check kube CTL get pods, it should show me how many pods I have.
And it looks like we now have three, so we're in good shape here.
Probably the next thing we want to do is add the nodes.
So that's what we'll do next.
If you want to remind like delay, it's because I'm trying to figure out the commands as we do it here.
So it's going to be AZAKS scale.
We're going to have to provide our resource group here.
We called it the Borg.
I don't know if we need the single quotations.
I just always do that.
It's out of habit.
The name is Borg again.
And we're going to increase that node count.
And let's do it to the max to three.
And we'll just wait for this command to execute.
It is running.
All right, so after waiting about, I don't know, five or six minutes, and it really depends on how many you're scaling up to.
It took a bit of time there, but it looks like it created them for me.
I got a bunch of JSON back.
That kind of tells me that, but to be very certain,
We should type in the kubectl get pods or actually get nodes, I suppose.
And we should see more nodes here.
Good.
And if we go to pods, we are in good shape here.
So you can see that we have a lot more going on.
All right.
So just to, one other thing that we can do is just check the distribution across it.
So we were using the get pods command, but we can also do get pod hyphen o.
You do not have to remember this, but I just want to show you so that you understand that nodes are distributed and how they are distributed.
So we'll type in pod colon metadata.name.
See if it does that there.
I'm not typing right.
I'm going to try this one more time.
So we have equals, I typed in customer, it's just custom.
Custom columns, node, spec, node, name, pod.
Let's try that.
And so there you go.
So there we can see how they are distributed.
We're in good shape here.
So I think all that's left now is to clean up.
Before we do that, maybe we could peek around the service to see if there's anything interesting there.
Because I don't think we saw anything of interest, really.
I'm going to open up a new tab to make it a little bit easier.
Go over to Kubernetes service.
Actually, it's right there on our homepage here.
We'll just look at the nodes.
There might not be really anything of interest here, but I'm just taking a look.
here we can see our deployments over here.
we can see our pods.
So it's just another way of looking at it.
It's the same information.
You might find this a bit easier.
We can even drill down into them, take a little bit look here.
Not a whole lot of information.
But yeah, if you prefer using the console, there's some better ways of visualizing that than having run commands.
But the thing is, in order to launch nodes and things like that, I'm pretty sure, actually, hey, can you do it through here?
You know, I'm so used to not being able to do it is because on AWS, they don't give you the option to have any ways of doing it.
So I just assumed that maybe that's the only way you can do it.
But it looks like you can actually provide YAML or JSON configuration.
So that's kind of cool.
Yeah, so I guess you can, you can provide a YAML file through here.
That's kind of interesting.
But anyway, that's not a big deal.
We're not going to do that today.
It's not necessary.
Let's just go ahead and clean up our stuff.
We'll make our way back over to the command line here.
And we'll do some cleanup.
Well, I mean, if we can do it there, maybe we can just delete them in here.
Yeah, it looks like we can.
So we could go ahead and go hit delete there.
But I think what we should just do is use kubectl.
And I'm going to say deployment, and we will go ahead and delete nginx.
And I'm going to go ahead and delete httpd.
And then we will go and type in kubectl, get pods, get nodes.
Okay.
Notice that they say they're all terminating here.
And while that's going, we can go check and see what's going on here.
Yep.
And so they've already vanished.
Deployments are gone.
These pods are still running.
I think, I'm just trying to think.
I don't know if we have to delete these pods because if we delete the resource, it should take them all with it.
We'll just do this get pods.
These are all gone now.
We'll go back here.
They still say they're running.
Oh, you know what, I bet you there was other ones here.
So I was just mistaking them for the other one.
So I believe that they're gone.
So I think we're all good to tear down this cluster.
So what we'll do is go back to Borg here, we're going to hit delete, we're going to hit delete there.
And we'll just wait for that to delete.
shouldn't take too long.
If we're not confident there, we'll click on Kubernetes here.
And just keep on refreshing.
Again, the Azure portal likes to lie to us a lot, so you got to wait.
So yeah, we'll just wait till that's done, okay?
All right, so after waiting about, I don't know, 4 or 5 minutes, it finally deleted that cluster.
So what we'll do is just go here, just double check the Kubernetes service to make sure that it is gone.
And it is there.
If there's anything lingering around there, you can go to your all resources here.
And you can just check for it.
So we'll go for Borg.
and nothing shows up.
So we're all in good shape there.
So there you go.
And yeah, I noticed that it's still showing it here, but that's the thing with the Azure portal.
It's just, you know, it's just what it is.
You know, it doesn't always tell you the truth.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are looking at Azure Kubernetes Service Cheat Sheet.
This is a really short one I probably should have made it longer, but this is what I got for you today.
So, AKS makes it simple to deploy a managed Kubernetes cluster in Azure.
Azure will manage for you.
the Kubernetes masters, health monitoring, maintenance.
You only have to maintain the agent nodes.
AKS service is free.
You only pay for the agent nodes within the cluster, not the masters.
You should use AKS for scenarios where you need full container orchestration.
So if you need service discovery across multiple containers, automatic scaling, coordinated application upgrades, that's what you're going to be using it for.
And one thing I want to mention is Bridge to Kubernetes is an extension of Visual Studio, Visual Studio Code.
It makes it super easy to debug Kubernetes.
But I feel like I should have put a bit of security stuff in here, but I'll probably update this in the future, just so but there you go.
To understand Azure DNS, let's first define what is a domain name, and that is a service that is responsible for translating and resolving a service name to its IP address.
And so Azure DNS is a hosting service for DNS domains that provides name resolution by Microsoft Azure infrastructure.
So imagine you have a domain, you want it to be managed by Azure DNS, and then you can make records like www to point to a specific Azure resource.
That's the idea behind there.
There's two types of DNSs you can make.
You've got a public DNS, an internet-facing one.
This is the one you're likely going to be using.
So this allows you to manage your domain for internet-accessible domains, point your domains to your website, or creating records that you own the domain or that you are pointing
emails to your e-mail server, so things like that.
Then you have your private DNS, which is internal facing.
This allows you to use your own custom domain instead of the Azure provider domains.
So Azure has its own provider domains, which are fully qualified domains for a lot of services.
A great example of this is Azure Storage Accounts.
And so that link there is its fully qualified domain.
One thing I want to point out is that you cannot use Azure DNS to purchase domains.
If you want to purchase a domain, you can actually do that through app services, or you use like a third-party provider such as Namecheap or GoDaddy, and then have Azure manage that DNS stuff.
Let's get into the details of zones, records, and record sets.
So the first thing is what is a DNS zone?
A DNS zone is a container for all your DNS records for a specific domain.
And so the next thing is what is a record?
And a DNS record is a rule that says where to send your domain name.
A record can be composed of a name, a type, and a value.
So the name would tell the record how to listen.
So maybe you want to do something with your www..subdomain.
Then you have the type.
That's how you're going to handle it.
So if you had
a type of A, which stands for address.
Maybe you're going to send it to an IP address.
And then the values, so you're going to actually provide the IP address so it knows how to take that subdomain and send it to that specific server.
Then there are record sets.
And record sets are pretty much just a grouping of records.
And they're just called record sets.
But when you're using Azure DNS, you're never creating a record per se.
You're creating a record set, which can contain a single record or multiple records.
So just be aware when you're using record sets, just think of record sets and records as the same thing.
Here's an example of a record set.
So this one is one that gets created for you by default when you set up a new zone.
And so what we have there are multiple records in the values there.
And these are for name servers.
So the idea with name servers is that this actually says where the domain is being managed.
And so for whatever reason, if one of the
servers became unavailable, then people would know to go to the second, third, or fourth name server.
So there you go.
Let's take a look at record sets because this is where all the magic happens for Azure DNS.
And I just want to remind you again that you don't create individual records.
You create record sets which can just contain a single record or multiple records.
And the first thing you're going to need to do is name your record.
It's not like naming other services.
because it's all about your domain.
So the first thing is that you can provide a name to the record, such as www.
And to you, that would look like a subdomain.
That's how I would describe it.
But that would also be known as a fully qualified domain, because you're completing the domain.
So I just want you to remember that.
Now you can also provide no name, and when it's left empty, that's now considered either apex or naked domain.
You can also provide a wildcard.
This acts as a catch-all, meaning that anything that gets
passed along, it's going to get captured here.
So the priority really does matter here as well.
But you can also not only just do an asterisk, you can do an asterisk.trek.
So if you just want a subset of things being matched, you can do that.
Not all DNS providers or services that manage DNS for you support that, but Azure does.
Then there's this at sign symbol.
This represents a shorthand for saying origin.
It's basically you saying I'm pointing to the naked domain or the zone that is hosting the domain.
And so you'll see that in some of the default records if you're just wondering what that is.
Another thing you can set on your record set is the time to live.
This is going to tell you, or this is going to tell other servers requesting your domain how long it should cache the record so it doesn't need to frequently ask what to do or asking for the same information over and over again.
And so you can either set a long TTL or a short TTL.
The longer it is,
Generally, the more it's going to reduce costs.
I don't know what cost it's going to reduce, but I know that it would.
I guess I'm just not working at scale, so I'm not too sure about that.
But the idea is that if it's longer, then there's going to be a lot less requests hitting the DNS.
Now you can set a short one, and you might want to do this if your records are changing frequently or you need failover.
So if you're using a record for failover, what you want is you want your TTL to be very low, because if it's set to like an hour or a day, that means that it has to wait till your servers or that the server that has the cache expires so that the failover can occur.
So be really careful with that.
Let's talk about the details of the actual record types.
This is the meat of your actual record because it's really going to tell it how it's going to work.
And we have a lot of ones here.
We're going to actually cover them all.
Starting at the top here with A, which stands for address.
This allows you to point your domain to an IPv4 address.
Then you have 4 A's.
This lets you point your domain to an IPv6 address.
Then you have CAA.
This is for certificate authorities.
These are records authorized who can issue certificates for their domain.
I assume it has to do with something with SSL certificates.
I'm not sure.
Then you have CNAMES.
These are canonical name records.
These create an alias from one domain to another, so you can set the record value to a domain.
So imagine you wanted www..exampro.co to go to freecodecamp.org.
Then the value would be freecodecamp.org with the actual...
www.
and CNAME there.
Then you have MX records.
These are mail exchange records.
So if your domain, if you have like a custom e-mail that has your domain, so like androidexampro.co, the idea is that you need MX records in order for that to work.
Then you have NS, which stands for name server records.
This identifies multiple DNS servers for the domain, and there are multiples in case the primary DNS server fails.
Then you have PTR, which stands for pointer.
And these are used to point to domain or host name, but it's used for reverse DNS lookup.
So it's just like an A record, but the difference is that it's for reverse DNS lookup.
Then you have SRVs.
This is a service record, and it's used to identify computers that host specific services, like locating domain controllers for Active Directory.
So we see a little bit more of this utility when we're working with Azure or Microsoft workloads.
And then you got TXT, and this is a record that is just text and consider multiple purposes such as documentation or as a means of verification.
I'll give you an example for verification.
Imagine you want to use Gmail.
And so, Gmail says, How do we know you own the domain?
So, go create a TXT record, and then we'll go check and see if you put in the value we gave you, and that's how we're going to verify that you own that domain.
There's one more here I don't believe it's something you can set, but it's something that you should always have, which is a startup authority.
This record contains administrative details about the domain.
All right.
One more thing, last thing about record sets is that you can set your own special record type, or sorry, you can set Azure's own special record type called alias.
And this works with either A, the four A's, or the CNAME record.
And the idea here is that I'm going to set that and then I'm going to actually choose an Azure resource.
So instead of saying go to this IP address or go to this host name, I'm saying go to this very specific service.
Why would you want to do that?
And the reason you want to do that is imagine that you, let's say you weren't doing that.
Let's say you just had
Like a load balancer, and you're directly pointing to its hostname, and for whatever reason, you deployed a new version of that service or something like that, and now its hostname has changed, and what could happen is that you could be left with a...
a domain or a domain record that is dangling.
It's pointing to nowhere.
And so what you'd have to do is manually update it.
But if you use this alias feature, you wouldn't have to do that.
It would just always point to the right place.
So whatever is being utilized underneath, whether it's an IP address or a host name, the point is that Azure always knows how to find it.
And so that is the power of alias.
And if you can use alias, you should always, always 100% use it.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from ExamPro, and we are going to learn about DNS Zones, or specifically Azure DNS.
Do not worry, you do not have to purchase a domain for this.
We're just going to go through the motions of it so that you have an idea here.
Maybe we'll try to launch a virtual machine and see if we can attach an alias, which is a custom.
Record set or type, so I'm going to go ahead and launch a new virtual machine, as always, as we've been doing a lot here.
We'll make a new character or a new resource group called WRF.
We'll name this virtual machine WRF, and we'll switch this over to a Linux machine.
I'm guessing Ubuntu 18 LTS, and we will choose...
B1LS because that is the most cost effective.
Watch for that price.
It should say like $5 a month.
That is cost effective.
Going to password, capital T, testing 123456.
Capital T, testing 123456.
That was supposed to go into there.
Our user should be Azure user, okay?
I'll slow down.
So we don't really need any ports open.
I guess we can open port 80 for fun.
And we can make our way over to the advanced here, and we'll make a shebang.
I think it's, oh, it's hash that, and then it's user forward slash sh.
And then we want to do sudo apt install apache2 hyphen y.
That should be right.
If it doesn't work, that's totally fine.
It's not really critical to what we're doing here.
And so we'll go ahead and create ourselves a virtual machine.
Again, I don't know if the alias will work without us actually hooking up the domain, but we'll give it a go anyway.
Now at the top, back to our other tab here, I want you to type in DNS, because we're going to create ourselves a DNS zone.
And so we'll go ahead in there and hit add.
Notice that we are making a public DNS record.
We're going to place that into our WRF resource group.
And we're going to name this, we'll just call it wharf.com.
We obviously don't own that domain, but we'll go ahead and create that anyway.
Once that is created, we'll just, it shouldn't take too long here, so we'll just wait a moment.
There we go.
And if we go over to here, what you'll notice is that we have some name servers.
So you would have to.
update this with your...
So the thing is that these are the name servers, right?
And so let's say you purchased the domain on GoDaddy.
You would then update your name servers on GoDaddy and provide these ones.
And then the domain would be managed here by Azure.
Down below are our records.
So we can go ahead and create a record set.
A record set is a collection of records, but it always has at least one.
And so here we could point things to different things.
So here we have an A record, which would go to IPv4.
But if we had a C name, we could say point
Google.warf.com to google.com.
That's how we would alias that.
Or CNAME that, I should say.
Now, if we wanted to point to our this here, we could go ahead and create ourselves a record set and set this as site as an A record.
And then we would just put the IP address in, the public IP address.
The only thing is that if you were to do this, and let's say this IP address changed, then you would have a dangling IP, right?
That means this would no longer be referencing the same one.
So what you could do is either give this virtual machine a static IP, or what you can do is use an alias.
So if we go here and I just say, we'll just say site 2, and we go choose a record alias.
then what we can do is drop down here and possibly choose, the other it is, this IP address, the WARF IP, which is attached to the machine.
And so no matter if it changes, it will always point to that, okay?
I don't think this would be on the exam, but if you're curious about child zones, because this is actually something I use, but imagine you have a service, and actually I do this with our platform, or the ExamPro platform, or the teacher seat platform, but imagine you wanted to have like subdomains, so you wanted to have
mytenant1.app.wharf.com.
That's what a child domain would do, okay?
So we go here.
And it shouldn't take too long.
Zones are pretty fast.
There we go.
And if we flip back here, it looks the same.
But now this is app.wharf.com.
Could you make a child of this?
I don't know.
I've never tried making a child of a child.
If you could, I guess that's great.
I wouldn't see the need there.
But if you had different tenants, like let's say you were making a multi-tenant app like a Squarespace, and you wanted to have them all on that, like on like that, you could do that and have all their sites.
So that's pretty much it.
It's not a terribly complex service.
So what we'll do is make our way over to our resource groups, and we'll look for Wharf here, and we'll go ahead and delete this resource group.
And that's all we need to know for DNS.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are looking at the Azure DNS Cheat Sheet.
This one's a page in a bit, so let's jump into it.
So Domain Name Systems, we're just defining the concept, is a service that is responsible for translating or resolving a service name to its IP address.
So Azure DNS, which I think is Domain Name Service, is a hosting service for DNS domains that provides name resolution by using Microsoft Azure infrastructure.
One thing that's super
important, maybe not for the exam, but just for practical knowledge, you cannot use Azure DNS to buy a domain name.
It has two things.
We have public DNS, so that's internet facing, allows you to manage domains for internet accessible domains, pointing your domain to a website, setting your records to preview on the domain, records to connect your domain to the e-mail server, and then you've got private DNS, so that's internal facing, allows you to use your own custom domains instead of the Azure provided domains.
So for the DNS zone, it is a container for all your DNS records for a specified domain name.
DNS record is a rule that says where to send your domain name.
A record is composed of name, type, and values.
And for the types, we have A, which is an address, 4 A's, which is for IPv6, CAA, which is certificate authority, CNAME,
MX, NS, PTR, SRV, TXT, SOA.
If there's ones you want to remember, it's going to be CNAME, A, and probably this next one here, which is the alias.
So Azure has its own special record type called alias that works with A, the four A's, and CNAME.
And the purpose of Azure Alias is to ensure that when you point to an Azure resource, because instead of choosing IP or whatever, you choose the resource you want to point to, it will always make sure it points to it.
So it helps us avoid dangling
domains.
We have record sets.
This is a group of records.
Azure always creates a record set, even with a single record.
And then the last thing here is time to live, which says how long a value should be cached for, so that if it's something that's very common, it's going to save some requests.
So there you go.
Let's talk about networking for Azure.
And so everything kind of revolves around the virtual network, also known as the VNet.
And this is a logically isolated section of your Azure network where you launch your Azure resources.
And here's a very simple diagram of using VNet, but there's a lot of networking components that you're going to be utilizing.
And we're not going to go through the exhaustive list here, but let's just go through some of them.
Just to give you an idea of all the things you can do within Azure networking.
So you have Azure DNS.
This manages your DNS domain.
Then you have the VNet itself.
And so underneath that, it'll have like address spaces, route tables, subnets.
Then you have network security groups.
This acts as a virtual firewall at the subnet or NIC level.
You have ExpressRoute.
This helps you create a very fast connection between your on-prem to your VNet.
Then you have virtual WAN.
This is a centralized network to route different network connections.
Then you have Virtual Network Gateway.
This is a site-to-site VPN connection between VNets and local networks.
Then you have your NICs, your network interfaces, and these are virtual network devices to allow VMs to communicate using IP protocols.
And then you have all your load balancers and other things like that.
So again, not an exhaustive list, but just shows you that there's a lot you can do with the networking on Azure.
One interesting concept is VNet peering, and this is where you can connect multiple VNets so they act as one network.
And there are two types of peering.
We have regional peering.
This is when you peer 2 VNets from the same region.
And then you have global VNet peering.
This is when you peer 2 VNets from two different regions.
Let's take a look at network interfaces, which are software or hardware interfaces between two pieces of equipment or protocol layers in a computer network.
And so network interface controllers, also known as NICs, that is the actual piece of hardware that connects a computer to a computer network.
And they go by a bunch of different names, such as network interface card, network adapter, LAN adapter, physical network interface, or even Ethernet interface controller card.
So if it was back in the 1990s, you definitely would have had one of these in the back of a computer.
And if you're a gamer today, then you have one.
because you want that wired connection, so you have a super fast connection.
And so these cards, or NICs, communicate using the Internet Protocol, also known IP.
That's going to allow them to communicate on layer 2, the data link layer, and the physical layer of the OSI model.
And so the way these work in Azure is they're called the Azure Network Interfaces, and they have the same initialism, NIC.
And so the idea is that you're going to attach a network interface to an Azure VM instance.
And without one of these, your Azure VM just can't communicate because it's just, imagine not having that card in your computer.
It would have no way of communicating.
And the difference here is that they're just virtual network interfaces, right?
So I'm sure at the data center, Azure has a bunch of these actual cards, but they are abstracted away.
So you know, you just treat them as virtual.
And an Azure VM, it has to have at least one NIC, but it can also have multiple NICs if you want.
And so here's just a nice little graphical representation of a VM that has a NIC attached to it.
So there you go.
Let's take a look here at network routes and route tables.
And so a route table is a table of data stored in a router or network host that lists routes to next destinations.
And the way I like to think of it is routes are the roads to the virtual network.
Without them, your data is just not going to go anywhere.
One thing that confused me is because I'm used to using AWS.
And when I used Azure, I launched a virtual machine and it was reaching the internet, but I couldn't find a route table for it.
So I was confused.
How does it know how to reach the internet?
You need a route table.
And the reason why it was doing that is because Azure has some system default routes.
And they already had a route to the internet for me that was already associated with my subnet, and so the thing is that there is actually a service called Route Tables, and you can type it up in the top of your Azure portal there, but I couldn't find like this route table that was managed by Azure, and the reason why is that they just hide it from you.
And so they have these default routes for you.
So they have one to your virtual network, one to the internet, and then there's just some RFC ones here for very specific use.
And these are not all the default routes.
There's a few other ones.
They don't really matter for us to know, but if you turn on some specific networking services, there's a few other ones that would be applied.
So let's talk about applying our own routes.
And so the idea here is those are called user-defined routes.
So you could just create a route table and then assign it to an actual subnet.
And so one thing you need to know is that a route table can be assigned to multiple subnets, but a subnet can also have just one user-defined route table.
And so the idea here is that if you want to override existing routes, you just create a route.
and it would just override the default one.
All right?
And so a good example of this would be, let's say you wanted to make sure that no internet could reach your subnet, like you're making a private subnet.
So what you'd have to do is you'd have to override that route to the internet and set the hop to none.
So over here on the right-hand side, I'm just going to call my route no internet, give it the same address prefix, and then say none.
And so that will override the original one.
I'm talking about hops for a moment.
There's a few different options here.
And again, a hop just says where to go.
So you have a few there, virtual network gateway, virtual network internet, virtual appliance, or none.
And those are pretty straightforward.
The only one that needs a little bit of clarity is virtual appliance.
So virtual appliance is just a virtual machine that runs a network application.
So an example of a network application could just be a firewall.
And in this hop type, you're going to have to provide that private IP address to that virtual machine.
So there you go.
Let's take a look here at address spaces.
And so an address space is a range of available IP addresses that you're allocating for use within your virtual network.
And so the amount of IP addresses available is determined based on the CIDR range notation.
So that's where you see an IP address followed by a forward slash enter number.
And that forward slash number thing is called a CIDR block.
And this is going to allocate the amount of addresses.
So a forward slash 24 is 256 and a forward slash 27 is 32.
This all has to do with binary map.
And so, if you only had a address space of 4/32, that would actually equal a single IP address.
I know that doesn't make a lot of sense, but we'd have to show you a little bit more to make sense of it, but we'll get into that later.
So here is an example of a couple address spaces, and this is actually in the same virtual network.
And to me, that's amazing because I'm used to using AWS, and over there, when you define a VPC, which is the equivalent of a VNet in Azure, you actually only get one address space.
But in Azure, you can define as many as you want, at least I think it's as many as you want, in a VNet.
So you can see there we have a 10.0.0.0.0.
In a 1921680, totally different address spaces.
The only one thing is that they obviously can't overlap.
And the other thing is that even though it says there's 256 address count there, that's not the actual available IP addresses because...
There's going to be always be some reserved IP addresses, and there's exactly 5.
So the first one is the network address.
The next one is reserved for the Azure, for Azure for default gateway.
Then you have a two and three, and this is for Azure DNS IPs and VNet space.
And then the last one in the range is going to be for network broadcast address.
So it's not always going to be 255.
It's whatever the address range is.
So if it ends at 128, then the last, then it's 128.
So there you go.
Let's take a look at subnets.
And A subnet is a logical division of an address space.
So we just looked at address spaces, so we're cutting it up one step further.
And subnets help you define different kinds of workloads and allows you to apply virtual isolation within your network.
So when you launch an Azure resource, you choose the subnet you want to launch within, and an IP from that subnet is assigned to your resource.
So the thing is that
When you create route tables, that's how you are associating the subnet, so it can access the internet or access anything, and then there's public and private subnets, but this thing is interesting because, again, if you're using AWS...
Those are very clearly defined things, but in Azure, they don't have this concept of public and private.
You have to define it yourself.
So really a public or private subnet is just a subnet that doesn't have access to the internet.
And so we saw that when we had the route table and we overrode the access to the internet to none, that essentially made it a private subnet.
Another thing you can do with subnets is you can associate a network security group.
And this is going to help protect your traffic entering and leaving the subnet.
So you're making rules based on the IP address, port, and protocol.
And then there's a special thing called a gateway subnet.
So it's a specialized.
Type of subnet, and it's just for Azure Virtual Network Gateways, and so it's interesting.
You'll go in and there'll be a separate section just for it, and so you'll create it.
It's just for that service.
So Azure Private Links allows you to establish secure connections between Azure resources, so traffic remains within your Azure network.
And so I got this big old graphic here.
And so let's just define a few things.
I'm going to pull out my pen here.
And so imagine you have workloads on your on-prem, or you have your own virtual network on Azure, and so you have some VMs doing some stuff.
And the idea is that you want to connect them to some other services over here.
But the thing is that
If you wanted to connect them, they might try to transverse the internet.
So if you're on-prem, it's going out here, it's going over here.
And so the issue with this is that it's not necessarily secure.
Another issue could be, you know, it's just faster if it was to stay within the actual network, because if you're already connected, you know, your stuff over here, then why wouldn't it just go through?
The actual network, another thing is like data transfer cost, so it's always going out the internet and coming back in, and that's not a great scenario, so I'm just going to erase all that stuff there.
The idea with PrivateLink is that it's just keeping everything within the Azure network, and so that's what it's doing.
So, if you want to...
connect your workloads in your VNet or your on-prem that connects to a specific VNet, the idea is that you can launch a PrivateLink endpoint, which is a network interface, and this is what's establishing that connection, and you're going to have to give that private endpoint a private IP address from your VNet.
And so then the idea is that on the right-hand side, that's what you want to connect to.
There's a lot of Azure services by default works with PrivateLink, so there's no additional configuration.
You'll just be able to say use PrivateLink, and they will.
Same thing with some third-party providers.
in the marketplace.
They might be powered by PrivateLink.
And then there's a third case where let's say you have like a private subnet and you have some VMs there.
So what you could do is if you have a load balancer and you need to have an internal load balancer there, you can launch the PrivateLink service.
And this is going to basically make your workload in that VNet become compatible or powered by PrivateLink.
So there you go.
So Azure Express Routes creates private connections between Azure data centers and infrastructure on your premises or in co-location environments.
And so connections don't go over the public internet and as a result offer more reliability, faster speeds, consistent latencies, and higher security.
So here's a big old graphic here kind of representing what's going on here.
And the idea is that you're going to have connectivity from different things like from any to any.
So that's IPVPN network, a point-to-point Ethernet network,
virtual cross connection.
And this is all going to be going through a connectivity provider at a co-location facility.
So this example would be an edge partner.
And so you would be the customer network.
That'd be your on-premise or whatever you want to connect so that you can make it all the way to your Azure services.
And the way you would establish connection is you create these express route circuits.
It's pretty common to have more than one because you want to have high availability just in case the other one goes out.
The idea is that you can route this traffic to a couple different places.
So the first one would be things like peering to Office 365, Dynamics 365, or even your Azure public services.
So when we say public services, imagine you just launch a virtual machine that is in a public subnet that has an IP that's reachable from the internet.
That could just be to that.
Or maybe you're using like Cosmos DB or like you have fully qualified domains for other services.
So it's just a way that you can get there.
And then let's talk about the other side, which is doing private peering for VNet.
So the idea is that you have a private VNet, so the subnets are private.
And so the only way is going to be access it, you want a direct way to access it that way.
So that's the two ways there.
And just to note, there is ExpressRoute Direct.
And so this is like ExpressRoute with an additional benefit that has greater bandwidth connections from 50 megabytes per second up to 10
Ten gigabytes per second, and this is really ideal if you have hybrid solutions where you're moving massive amounts of data or where latency matters because you want to feel like these cloud services are right there with your on-premise environment, and you're going to need a lot of speed for that.
Azure Firewall is a managed cloud-based network security service that protects Azure VNet's resources, and it's a fully stateful firewall as a service, so you're going to get built-in high availability and unrestricted cloud scalability.
And what you can do is essentially create, enforce, and log application network connectivity policies.
Across subscription and virtual networks, so Azure Firewall uses a static public IP address for your VNet resources, allowing outside firewalls to identify originating from your virtual network, and the service is fully integrated with Azure Monitor for logging and analytics.
So, here is a representation.
of Azure Firewall.
And so the idea is that you're going to launch an Azure Firewall into its own VNet, and then other VNets and your on-premise or other things are going to pass through that central VNet onto wherever they want to go.
And the idea is that we're going to be able to do things like utilize Microsoft Threat Intelligence.
This is going to block known malicious IPs and FQDNS.
That stands for Fully Qualified Domain Names.
And by default, the traffic is set to deny, but you can set
connectivity policies to filter out traffic in a variety of ways to make sure that you are protected there.
So yeah, that's all there is to it.
Taking a quick look here at Azure Network Watcher, which provides tools to monitor, diagnose, and view network metrics.
It also enables or disables logs for resources in your Azure virtual network.
And there's a few things you can access from this service, like IP flow verify checks.
packet capture, troubleshooting VPNs and NSGs, NSG flow logs, diagnostic logs, traffic analytics, network performance monitor, and a bunch of other stuff.
And so Network Watcher can monitor and repair Azure resources you provision, such as virtual machines, virtual networks, application gateways, load balancers, but it's not really designed to monitor fully managed services because Azure already takes care of that stuff for you, so like monitoring or web analytics kind of stuff.
And another thing is that it's disabled by default.
I think that it's disabled except for a few key regions.
I don't remember because whoever set up our Azure account might have turned on a couple things.
So now I believe that.
Some of the default ones might be turned on for you.
But the point is that if you want to utilize this in different regions, you're likely going to have to enable it because it's disabled by default at a per region level.
One other thing I just want to show you is the topology feature in it.
So if you look there, we have a topology and we have this nice graphic.
And what it does is it visualizes the topology of our V-Nets.
And so you can download that as an SVG, so you can use it in presentations and documentation.
And you can click through on any of those elements so that you can do a bit more of an investigation or stuff like that.
It's cool.
I don't have much utility for it myself, but I just thought it was cool that Azure had that.
So Network Performance Monitor is a cloud-based hybrid networking monitoring solution that helps you monitor network performance between various points in your network infrastructure.
And it also helps you to monitor network connectivity to services and application endpoints and monitor the performance of Azure Express routes.
And so the idea here is that you're going to be using this.
If you want to use Network Performance Monitor, you're going to have to create yourselves an NPM resource.
And the way you do that is you're going to actually have to create a log analytics workspace.
And so this solution can generate alerts and notify you when a threshold is breached for a network link.
It also ensures timely detection of network performance issues and localizes the source of the problem to a particular network segment or device.
The Network Performance Monitor detects issues such as traffic blackholing, routing errors, and unconventional network issues.
And this service is found within the Network Watcher, so it used to be somewhere else.
And now when you want to access it, you just go to Network Watcher and it's all consolidated under there.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are going to be looking at Azure Firewall, which is great for protecting your virtual networks.
So what we'll do is launch an instance, and then we will use Firewall to protect it, and then we'll connect through the Firewall to our server there.
So what I want you to do is make your way over to virtual machines.
This will also set up the virtual network that we will need.
So I'm going to go here and add a new machine.
I'm going to make a new resource group.
This one I'm going to call Cardassia.
And what I will do here is name this Cardassia Prime.
And this is in Canada East.
I think that's totally fine.
If we're going to do that, let's do that.
We'll probably want to use a Windows Server 2019 to get there.
Go to Windows Server, choose Gen.
2.
For this, we'll have to choose something like a D2v3.
That's what I find the most cost effective because you have to have at least
two CPU vCPUs and four gigabytes to run that.
So that's probably the most cost effective I can find.
We're going to type in Azure user here, testing 123456 with a capital T.
Okay.
Scroll on down here and everything else should be fine.
So we'll go ahead and hit review and create.
And then we'll go ahead and create.
Now we're going to want that firewall.
So what we're going to do is make our way back to our resource group.
So if we click here and we go into overview, it should show us that virtual network.
I guess it's still creating it.
So we're just going to have to wait here a little bit for that.
Usually, it's pretty darn fast, so I'm surprised the VNet is not there.
If it's not there, we'll take a look over here into virtual networks.
There we go, and so we could go and go to firewall and create it that way, but I find it a lot easier.
I'm just going to show you if I go over here.
You can create it here, but I find that it's a lot easier to create it from the blade because then it'll put it in the same resource group and fill in some of the things for us under the virtual network.
So on the left-hand side, we'll go to firewall, click here, and it's going to pre-populate some stuff for us, as you can see.
And so what we'll do is name this, you know, Space Defense.
And we'll stick with standard.
You also got premium.
There is a difference in price there.
I'm not really sure.
There's a
firewall policies and classic rules, I'm going to stick with classic rules for the time being.
I'm not sure if they'll really show you on the exam, whether it's going to be policy and rules, but you just generally have to know how to set up a firewall here, we need the virtual network name, I really thought this would have filled it in.
And so what I'll have to do is just make open a new tab here.
And it's called Cardassia v net.
This is already a resource with the same name and type with the current resource group.
Oh, sorry, use an existing one.
That's my problem.
I thought I had to fill it in.
I'm being silly here, so we'll just hit next there.
Must have a subnet named Azure Firewall Subnet.
That's totally fine.
So what we'll do is just right click up here and make our way back to our VNet.
And we will go to subnets.
And we have subnet gateway subnet.
We just want a regular one here.
And what we'll do is grab this name here.
Whoops, won't let us do that.
Azure Firewall Subnet.
And hopefully it'll tell us more what we need to do there.
So we need to fill in more stuff here.
This is 10.0020 forward slash 24 as our default.
So I'm just going to try 10.0.03.0 forward slash 24.
is not contained in this virtual network space.
I hate, I hate networking.
I've done tons of stuff on this stuff.
Maybe I have to set up the address space first.
So we'll go over here.
Yeah, we don't have one yet.
So we'll go 10.0.3.0 forward slash 24.
And we'll say, okay.
And then we'll make our way over back to that subnet.
I think that's what it wanted first.
At this point, I don't remember anything.
It's all muscle memory, right?
So I just know what to type.
Azure firewall subnet.
And we want the range three.
Yeah, we just defined it, so it auto-filled it in for that.
is good.
I don't know if we need to set really any of these other things, like network security group and stuff like that.
So I'm going to go ahead and save that.
And I'm going to make my way back on over here.
And we will choose the Cardassia.
Oh, we can't use that IP address.
I guess we will add a new one.
Hold on here.
We'll just back out here because it's quite messed up.
And we will go ahead and try this again.
So Cardassia, space defense, second to standard, we'll go with rules.
We'll use an existing virtual network.
So we'll drop this down.
And it doesn't want to show me anything today.
Oh, it's in the wrong region.
I don't know why it's doing that.
So I think it's in Canada East.
And we'll go back here.
Cardassia.
We're going to need a new IP address.
Firewall IP.
Go ahead and hit OK.
Force tunneling.
Force tunneling to create an additional subnet for firewall managed traffic.
The subnet will have direct access to the Internet.
I don't know if we really want that right now.
We'll go ahead and hit create.
And we'll just wait here and I'll see you back in a bit.
So our firewall is deployed, but we're going to actually have to set up a route so that our subnet actually goes through the firewall.
So what I want you to do is right click on your resource group there.
And from here we are looking for our
virtual network.
We'll open that up into a tab so that we have that as a reference.
What we're also going to do is open up another one because we need to go into our subnet and into our default one.
We need to override the route table.
Now, if you remember from my lecture content, route tables do have default routing, but we are going to explicitly overwrite this with our own logic.
So what I want you to do is type in route tables at the top here, and we'll add a new route table.
We, for me, this is going to be in Cardassia.
So we are in Canada, this one.
And for the name, we're going to just say firewall route.
And propagate gateway routes.
I think that's okay.
Yeah, we'll leave that on there.
That's fine.
Great.
And so we'll go ahead and create that row table.
Once that is finished deploying there, we'll go ahead and hit go to your resource.
And on the left hand side, I want you to make your way over to the routes, oh, sorry, over to the subnets.
And we're going to go ahead and associate our V net here.
And we will choose our default.
And I believe we have to do both.
So I'll just give that a moment to create.
And I'm going to go ahead and associate my other one, which is this one here.
sorry, we don't need to do that just yet.
But we do need to associate the default there.
So what I want you to do is make your way back to your subnets here.
And I'm going to click into this.
And now we have this firewall route table.
We didn't select it prior, but we'll go ahead and save that.
And so now that subnet is saved, we can go ahead and add some routes.
I'm going to make my way back to my firewall route here.
I'm going to make a route.
I'm going to add a route.
And in here, this is going to be firewall.
I don't know why I named this firewall route.
This should be route table, but this will be firewall route route.
And I'm going to drop this down to virtual appliance.
This is going to be 0.0.0.0/0 because we want to go to the Internet.
And under our virtual appliance, we would need to choose the next hop.
So the next hop address, I think, is the IP address.
So I think we'd have to go over to the firewall and find it there.
So this is the firewall.
It should have a private IP address.
There it is.
So I'll copy that there.
We'll go ahead and paste that on in.
We'll hit OK.
And I'll just click off and click back here.
I'm just going to wait for that rope to show up.
Let's see here.
There we go, there it is, and so now all our stuff is hooked up, and so we are ready to set up some rules.
All right, so let's set up some classic rules.
I wasn't really sure what to set up here, so I pulled out the trusty docs and I got some good examples for us to go through here.
So, for an application rule, this would be like if you want to say allow this.
address through like Google.
Network would be something like DNS servers.
And then an app rule is going to allow us to do the RDP.
So let's go here and set up an application rule first.
We'll call this the Google Collection rule.
I'm going to say 200 here.
We're going to go down to targets.
I'm going to put allow Google.
We're going to set the source type.
And the source is going to be whatever the VNet is for the default here.
That's 10.0.2 or 10.0.24.
So 10.0.0
20 or 4.0 forward slash 24.
We'll do HTTP, HTTPS, www.google.com.
So that's that one.
We'll go to our network rule.
We'll set this one up next.
This is for CenturyLink.
And they have some DNS servers there.
So that's what we were setting this up for.
We'll say 200 under the IP addresses, we're going to say allow DNS.
And the protocol is going to be UDP.
We'll have the source IP again, 10.0.2.0/24.
The destination IP, we have them over here.
I'm just going to copy them on over.
And then the port is port 53.
We'll go ahead and hit add.
Last one here.
Oh, it didn't like this one.
Another operation on this is dependent.
Which one did it fail on?
I'm not sure.
It might have not liked the fact that I was doing one or two at the same time, we'll give that a better look here.
It's not saying why.
this rule created, we can give this one another go.
Make sure it's not doing anything else.
Okay.
And we'll try this one more time.
So let's say collection rule, CenturyLink.
Under here, we'll go here and again, allow DNS 10.0 dot 2.0 forward slash 24.
we will say, oh, we didn't select it, it's going to be UDP here, the destination IPs, we'll just copy them from here.
So that is 2092440320922404.
And we'll put in 53 here.
And I'm just going to double check to see if I was missing anything.
I don't think so.
That's pretty much everything there.
So we should be able to create that we'll hit Add again.
Oh, yeah, we'll set 200 up here.
And we'll see if we have a better chance this time around.
Again, probably should wait between them.
But there's just so much to do.
I like to just get to it.
I think that's probably what the problem was.
We'll go over to our NAT rule.
And we'll take a look here.
And for this, we will just call this RDP.
NAT collection rule.
We'll set the priority as always to 200.
For the name, we'll just say allow RDP here.
The protocol is going to be TCP.
And for this, we'll do 10.0.
forward slash 2.0 forward slash 24.
For the destination address, that's going to be the public IP address for the firewall.
So
We'll have to go over here and then make our way back to our firewall.
So we'll just type in here.
And we'll click into here.
We'll go grab our public IP address.
Click into here to get it.
There it is.
And we will paste that in as the destination for the port is 3389.
That's for RDP.
For the translated address,
We need the private IP address for...
I'm not sure.
Let me see here.
Oh, that's going to be our virtual machine.
That's probably what it is, right?
So I just thought about that.
It makes sense because, you know, what else would it be?
So we'll go over to our virtual networks.
Actually, we'll just go over to our virtual machines.
And we will click into here.
And I would imagine that we'd need the public IP address, right?
No, probably the private.
Sorry.
I keep on changing my mind here.
It is...
Where is it?
There it is.
Because it'd be under private network.
You wouldn't be connecting to it publicly.
That wouldn't make any sense.
And probably the port would be the same.
Yeah, it's the same.
There we go.
And if that looks all good, we'll hit...
What does it want?
It's not going to let us take it.
No, maybe it's because we were creating something at the same time.
Let's go see if our NAT rules is there.
Okay, great.
So we'll give it a refresh.
I don't trust it.
I'm going to give it a hard refresh.
And we'll try this one more time.
So we'll go back to our NAT rule.
RDP.
NAT.
200.
Allow RDP.
I always thought RDP was UDP, but I guess not.
10.0.0 forward slash or 2.0 forward slash 24.
Destination IP is the public IP address of the firewall.
So we'll go back to our firewall.
We'll click into here.
We will click
into here, and there it is.
And what is it?
3389?
3389, and we need the private IP for our actual virtual machine, which was 10.0.24.
There we go.
And it still won't let us hit add.
Why not?
Oh, it doesn't like the translated address.
One, two, three, four, one, two, three, four.
I mean, that should be it.
Okay, we'll double check here.
I'm just not very confident about this.
I'm just going to hit refresh here.
We'll go into this.
That's the address, so it should just take it.
I don't know why it's giving it a hard time.
Is there a space in front of it?
Oh, there we go.
That's our problem.
You think they just truncated for you there.
So now we can go hit add.
And so we'll just wait for that rule to finish and then we can go ahead and test a bunch of stuff.
Okay, so our last rule is there.
We have all three.
Now let's go give it a go.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to make my way over to our virtual machine.
I'm just going to close some of these tabs so we can clean up here.
And so I'm going to go back to our virtual machines here.
I'm going to click into here.
And what we're going to do is change our DNS servers for the network device.
So what I need is to go to probably networking, and there it is, the network interface.
And then we can go to DNS servers, and we can change this to custom.
So that's what we were doing earlier when we were doing that CenturyLink stuff.
So I'm going to just go grab those addresses there.
So we have
It was 209-24403, and then 209-24404.
And we'll go ahead and save that.
Great, and hopefully that propagates very quickly.
I'm never really good with DNS servers, so I could not tell you if that's the case.
But the next thing we'll need to do is actually remote into that desktop there.
So I'm going to just open up Remote Desktop Connection.
And what we can do is provide the IP address of what we want to connect to.
And so we want to connect through the firewall.
So that's what we're going to do.
I'm just going to move that off screen.
I'm going to go grab our firewall IP address.
And we want to go to firewall here.
We're going to grab that address there.
I'm going to paste it on in.
And I don't know, I mean, we do have a username.
It's Azure user.
I don't know if that's what we need to type in here, but we'll see.
I rarely ever open a remote desktop connection like this.
Usually I just press a button and it works.
And we'll see if it lets us connect here.
Oh, and I guess those DNS settings were still going.
Remote access to the server is not enabled.
The remote computer is turned off.
The remote computer is not available on the network.
I'm not sure about that.
But let's just double check our server here, making sure that it's nice and warm and woken up.
So what I'm going to do is just go
to my virtual machine here.
I don't think it has a public IP address, so I shouldn't be able to use it this way, but we'll give it a go anyway for fun.
I'm expecting it not to work in this regard here.
and noticing that it can't seem to establish a connection.
So that's probably, yeah, there we go.
So that means that's good.
That means that it has to go through the firewall.
So we have to just kind of figure that out.
Why it's not working through the firewall, I don't know.
So I'll have to do a bit of debugging here.
All right, I'm back.
And so I figured it out.
I just reviewed the rules that I set up and just made sure they made sense.
And I realized that this here I set as the source to the default subnet.
That doesn't make any sense because you want the source to be something like anywhere on the internet.
So all I did is I just put, I just updated this to be an asterisk.
You could also put your own IP.
That would probably be more secure.
I just didn't want to do that.
I just made it that.
So just do that.
Save that.
With the new asterisk in the source, and so, coming back to our remote desktop connection again, this is the IP's address for the firewall.
If we want to go find that again, what we're going to do is go up to here, and oh, we already have it here.
So, if we go to firewalls, click into there, click on the IP address.
It's that 4086204105.
So bringing this on over 4086204105.
And I have the Azure username.
If you don't see it, hit the show options there.
If it's on Mac, I do not know what the experience is like.
We're going to type in testing 123456 capital on the T.
We'll hit OK.
We'll say yes.
And now we should be able to connect to it.
If we go down to the internet here, the idea was that we wanted to test the google.com.
So we go Google
This is blocked.
What if I give it the www dot.
So the rule, the firewall is working.
This is the application rules here.
I'm not sure I'm gonna be able to easily fix this here.
But we can give it a go for two seconds to see if we can make any kind of difference.
We'll go here and edit the rule.
But I'm pretty sure this is right.
So we have allow IP address 10 04024.
Is it a four?
Why was I read no two before?
10 02.
Oh, it's two.
Okay, maybe that's me again.
Okay, so we'll go here, we'll just change this to two.
It's not going to work if you don't set the rules, right.
We'll go ahead and save that.
Did I set that one wrong?
It's wrong as well.
Let's go take a look here.
That's two.
Okay, minor mistakes.
It's great to learn some debugging here.
And so we'll give that a little bit of time here.
And then we'll see if it works.
Alright, so our firewall there for our application rule has updated.
We go back here and just give it a double check here.
I think I have it 10.0.2 now, so that's all correct.
Let's go see if we can now connect.
I still have RDP open here.
I don't know if I have to close and reopen.
I don't think I would have to, right?
We'll give it a go here and hit enter.
Look, and so that's difference.
That's good.
Content from the website listed as being blocked by Internet Explorer Enhanced.
So this
If I will add it there, I will say add and go back here.
Oh, boy, gee static.
Sure.
So Google works.
That's perfect.
And if we go to Microsoft, that's not going to work.
And that's perfect.
So that's what we wanted.
That was everything we wanted to accomplish with this firewall here.
We didn't look at firewall policies.
We could try taking a look here.
I'm not sure what we could see here, but it looks like we can migrate it over.
So let's just see what happens if we do that.
Let's say create this policy here.
And I'm not sure how fast this will be, but I'll see it back here.
We'll take a look at what the firewall policy looks like.
Okay, so it looks like our policy is all set or migrated there for our rules.
Let's go take a look and see what that looks like.
So it looks like pretty similar.
So we have our application rules, our network rules, our NAT rules, rule collections, policies.
It looks a little bit more broad.
I imagine the other thing is that we might be able to associate these two other things.
Is that the case?
If we go over to firewall policies here.
Yeah, there it is.
So that seems like it'd probably be a better thing to use than classic rules.
I'd probably go with that.
It looks like you can just easily add stuff there.
So it's not a big deal.
You get a bunch of extra stuff.
So yeah, that's firewalls there.
So we'll just go ahead and tear on down all this stuff here.
I'll make my way over to Cardassia here.
We'll go ahead and delete that resource group.
And we will delete.
And that should get everything.
That's good.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are going to be looking at virtual network peering.
And so there are two types of network peering.
We have local and global.
Local is where you are peering 2 virtual networks that reside in the same region, and then the other is when there are two different regions.
There's a lot of benefits to virtual network peering, such as low latency, high bandwidth connections.
So, you know,
There's a lot of good use cases for that, and it's something we should definitely know, especially if you're studying for the administrator.
So let's go ahead and do that to make our lives easier.
We're going to be launching Windows Server.
I know they're expensive, but don't worry, we won't have them for long.
But we're going to have to launch three.
We're going to need two in a single region with different virtual networks and one that is in a different region with a different virtual network.
And then we're going to use PowerShell to just test the connection between them.
So let's make our way over to virtual networks.
I'm going to go ahead in here, add a virtual machine, and I'm going to create a new resource group.
And I'm just going to call this peering test or peering challenge.
Sure.
And we'll go there.
And then down below, I'm going to signify what this is.
So this is going to be East A.
And so over here, I'm just going to go to US East.
And I'm going to change the image.
We're going to choose a Windows Server.
I'm going to go to Data Center 2019 Gen.
2.
And what we'll do here is just scroll on down and we'll have to up the size here.
Again, with a Windows Server, you need two and four.
So VPCU, a RAM 4.
So the smallest I'm going to be able to do is this one or...
I mean, I never do B2s, but I think what we can do is this D2 version 3.
You'll see me choose that a lot.
And so now what we'll do is just make it very easy.
We'll just set the password to Azure user and we'll make it testing123456 with capital on the T.
Okay.
And then we'll go ahead and we will just hit review and create.
actually, sorry.
We actually have to be really careful here because we want to make sure that everything is named properly.
We've got to make sure all the virtual subnets are different.
So this is Peering Challenge.
So we should make our way over to here.
And what we'll do is just change this to East A.
Okay?
So I was a little bit ahead of myself there.
We'll make sure all the names have changed.
And now that looks good to me.
So we'll go ahead and go here.
And we'll double check.
Our resource group is called Peering Challenge.
This is an East A, East US.
This is East A, VNet.
So that makes sure that is unique and we're all good to go.
So we'll go ahead and launch that one.
And we'll give that a moment.
And now that it's in progress, we'll make our way back to virtual machine and we'll launch East B.
It's the exact same setup.
So we're going to go down here.
We're going to choose peering challenge.
We're going to call this East B.
We're going to make sure that it's in US East 1, which it is.
We're going to make sure it's a Windows Server, Gen.
2.
We're going to choose the same size there.
We're going to set the username to be Azure User, and then capital T, Testing, 123456.
And then we'll scroll on down, make our way to disks, to networking, and then here we'll just make sure that the name has been changed.
So we'll change this to East East B VNet.
All right, and then we're good here.
So we'll go ahead and hit review and create.
And once that is created, we'll go ahead create there.
And now it's in progress.
So we'll go and deploy the last one.
And this one is going to be in a different region.
So we'll go virtual machine, we still want the same resource group.
So you make sure you choose peering challenge.
And this one is going to be West A.
And so we'll just look for West.
And there it is.
And we'll make sure it's Gen.
2.
That's all great.
Azure user.
And we'll do capital T, testing 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
And we will, whoops.
Must be the top one.
That's a mistake here.
There we go.
We'll go to next, and then we'll make sure that this one is named different.
So this will be, we said this will be West A.
Great.
And so we'll go ahead and launch that.
We're going to create that instance there.
This looks all good to me.
Click create.
And that one's in progress.
Now, while these are going, we can set up our peering because that will take a bit of time for these to launch here.
So what I want you to do is make your way over to virtual networks.
And we are going to go into USA and we're going to bridge A to B.
So on the left-hand side, we're going to go to peerings.
We're going to hit add.
And I'm just going to call this East A to B.
And we're going to allow we're going to block the traffic because we want this to be kind of a private connection, we don't want traffic from outside of that connection.
And then here, we'll just name it again, a East A to B, we're going to choose where we want to peer to that's going to be the B.
And I'm going to deny on the on the other side as well.
And we'll go ahead and hit Add.
And that doesn't take too long to create, let's give it a moment.
And now that we have that, what we can do is now peer east to west.
So I'm going to say east to west.
We're going to say block for the traffic, east to west.
And we will choose west here.
We will block the traffic here.
I'm going to go ahead and blow oops, sorry, won't allow the first one, we want to block the second part.
I'll just give it a moment there.
Great.
And so I think we can just check those connections really quickly here.
Just double checking, making sure all of my information is correct.
Looks good to me.
Yeah, that looks all correct to me.
So now we'll make our way back over to our virtual machines because we're going to have to wait here.
And once they're all running, then we're going to go ahead and RDP into some of them here and then just use PowerShell to give it a check.
Great.
So after waiting a little bit of a while there, all of our Windows machines are ready.
So let's go ahead and connect to them.
But before we do, let's just make note of what the IP addresses of the other machines are so we know what we need to connect to.
So we're going to RDP into East A to see if we can test the connection to B&A.
So what I want to do is just see what this one is.
So for B, the IP address for this is
We got to go to the networking tab.
And so we have 10104.
And then for West A, and we go over here, this is going to be 10014.
So it's just one is here and then one is there.
Pretty easy stuff.
And so the command we're going to be using is called test net connection.
So if we just pull up that in PowerShell here.
Just to show you what this is, this is a cmdlet that is part of Windows, not actually part of Azure.
And it's a way for testing a connection.
And so that's what we're going to be using today.
So for the computer name, we're going to provide that IP address.
We'll have to specify the port.
And we'll just ask for the level of detailed information that we want.
Okay?
So let's make our way back here.
And what we're going to do is click on East Day.
We're going to go ahead and connect in RDP.
And so we'll download this file.
I'm on a Windows machine, so I can RDP right away.
If you're on a Mac, you've got to download the RDP remote client.
It's free in the Mac store, but you need it in order to remotely connect.
Or if that's too hard, you can use the Bastion, which is a lot of work and kind of a pain, but it's up to you what you want to do.
And so here we go as we connect to this instance.
And so, you might have to wait a little bit for this to load.
I had loaded it a bit earlier just testing this to make sure everything works.
But let's go ahead and open up the start menu down below.
And we're going to type in PowerShell.
Now, I'm going to tell you right now, this is really small.
I don't really have any easy way to bump up this font, so I'm very sorry about that.
But what we'll do is we'll type in test net connection, and then we'll put in computer name.
And then we want the IP address.
So we said
A to B was 10.1.0.
I believe 4.
And so that's going to be on port 3389.
And we want that information level to be detailed.
OK.
And so if I typed all of that correctly, this should work.
So we're going to wait for response.
And there it says that it's successful.
So we have successfully created up here between East A&B.
Now we want to go check to see if we can do cross region.
So the only difference here is this one is now here.
And we're looking for the same response.
So there you go.
So we successfully established peering, and we've also showed that we know how to test for it.
So that's great news.
We'll hit close on there.
And what we'll do is make our way over to that resource group.
I'm going to go over here to all resources.
Actually, sometimes it's easier to go to resource groups.
I don't know why I don't ever click that.
And we will find the one we have.
It's just called peering challenge.
And we'll go ahead and delete that.
So let's go there and delete this.
Okay.
And we should be all good.
So there you go.
That's peering.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from ExamPro, and we are going to be looking at application gateways, which is for application load balancing, scale sets for being able to automatically add or remove instances when needed.
And we're also going to be learning how to debug or troubleshoot network issues.
using Network Watcher.
So what we're going to do is launch a new virtual machine and we're going to install Apache 2 so that we actually have a web server to work with.
So go to your virtual machines.
We're going to make a new one here.
I'm going to call this one Ryza.
And we'll just name the virtual machine Risa as well.
Whatever region it wants to be in, just make note of it.
And then we will want to use Ubuntu server LTS.
So just scroll on down below.
Make sure you're choosing LTS, generation 2.
And then we want to make sure we have the cheapest cost here.
So make sure you have standard B1LS.
And then if we scroll on down, I'm going to set the password.
I'm going to say Azure User.
And I'm going to make the password testing123456, capital on the T.
Scrolling on down, we're going to open up port 80 here.
It's going to be very frustrating if we don't do this here.
Sometimes I have issues with NSGs, so it's just easier if you set it there, okay?
And so it's going to make that standard so we save a bit of money.
That looks all good to me.
We'll hit review and create.
What we'll do here now is just hit create, and so we'll just wait for that server to be ready.
And once it's ready, we'll go in, SSH in, install Apache 2, and make sure that test page is in good shape.
All right, so our virtual machine is ready.
So let's go ahead and go to those resources.
We're going to grab that public IP address.
And what we're going to do is launch our Cloud Shell at the top there, and we're going to SSH into this machine.
So I'm going to type in SSH, and it was Azure user at sign, and then we'll paste in that public IP address, hit enter.
We'll have to
write yes.
And then testing 123456 capital on the T.
And then once we're in there, we can do a sudo apt install Apache two, and that will install Apache two.
This doesn't take too long.
But once it's installed, we will have the default Apache page.
And if we can view that, then we'll be in good shape.
Great, so that's now installed.
One way we can verify it's installed is we can do curl and type in local host.
This will return, it's like hitting the homepage.
The idea is if it returns HTML, which is the default page, we know that it will work at least with inside the virtual machine.
If we copy the public IP address and paste that into our browser, we should see this page, which we do.
And also, if you didn't see that there, if you wanted some debugging, what you can do on the left-hand side, if you scroll all the way down,
There's a thing called, where are you, connection troubleshoot.
And so here, if you wanted to test your IP address, you say, my IP address, it's the same as if I did it over here.
And if I went and switched this over to http://, and we hit test connection, we can see whether the connection works.
So just give it a moment there to verify.
Also, while we're waiting there, if we wanted to see if that server was running, we could use ps aux pipe and then write probably httpd or not http.
We could do, oh, sorry, grep httpd.
Or maybe it's Apache.
I'm not sure which one it is.
There it is.
So that's how we know that it is running on the server.
This connection shouldn't take this long.
It's just, I don't know why it's so slow here.
There we go.
So
I mean, here it's saying the Network Watcher is deployed.
So that's something we were also waiting as well.
Whenever you create a virtual machine, it's automatically going to provision Network Watcher for you for use.
So that doesn't generally take too long for you.
I'm not sure if it just triggered as soon as I pressed that button there.
Maybe it was just as soon as I did that.
But yeah, now see the connection is there.
So I guess Network Watcher wasn't ready.
And that's another thing that we're going to learn how to use is Network Watcher.
So what I want you to do
is go to the top here or right-click, and we'll make our way over to Network Watcher.
And this tool has a lot of stuff in it.
It's here to help us set up a bunch of stuff.
And you can see here we have a bunch of Network Watchers here for each, it looks like for each region.
So I think that was the first time I actually ever used it in that region, and that's why it was provisioning.
And so if we go down below, we have a bunch of different tools.
We have IP, Flow, Verify, NSG Diagnostic.
we have other things like NSG flow logs, traffic analytics, there's a lot of fun, cool stuff in here.
And you can get topology.
So if we drop down here, and I think this is no different than the resource groups that we see.
Yeah, it's the same stuff as always.
So let's give it a go and try out some of these tools.
Okay, so notice here that it already pre-filled stuff in for me.
So what it's doing is choosing the resource group, the virtual machine, and then the network interface.
And we have this TCP UDP.
It's pretty much the same of what we just did over with the test connection.
The local IP address, that is the one of the actual virtual machine.
If we go back to our virtual machine and go all the way at top to overview, it should show us the private IP address.
That's the public.
Now I have to go to network there.
And there it is, 10.0.0.4.
So if we wanted to say, can I test for my IP address?
I'm going to go into Google here and type in what.
That's my IP.
And we'll go back over here.
And what I will do is paste it into here.
It's on port 80 that we're trying to connect to.
And we'll go ahead and hit check.
And I kind of swore, yep, nothing over there.
we go.
So that one works.
So we'll look at the next one.
All right, so now let's take a look at NSG diagnostic tool.
Very similar, but revolves around your network security groups.
So it's going to give you detailed information, whereas the other one's just about packets going back and forth.
So again, we're going to go over here to RISA.
I'm going to select the virtual machine.
I'm going to select RISA again.
It's going to be for TCP.
We're checking an inbound port.
Now notice here it says IPv4 or a CIDR block.
So this is the source traffic.
Where's the traffic coming from?
Well, it's my IP address.
So I'm going to go grab that again, paste that in.
there.
The destination was already pre-filled.
That is the public IP address of our machine.
And this is port 80 because we're running HTTP.
I'm going to go ahead and hit check.
And we'll see what we get here.
Great, cool.
So we can see that works.
And it even returns the security group where it is allowed.
Maybe what would be fun is to go in and actually mess with the security group and purposely make it so that it doesn't work.
So, by the way, I clicked into there and I can see more detailed information about the NSG diagnostic.
So you can see we have that there.
Yeah, security rules.
We're not worried about that.
That's just if we want to add ones there.
But yeah, that gives you a better idea of what's going on.
I'm going to make my way over to my NSGs because I want to show you what it looks like if you don't actually have access, right?
So we'll go into here and here is this rule.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to change it, so I'm going to say it has to be 8080, which is not what we're going to connect to, and we'll go ahead and save that.
So now it should probably not work.
Okay, and if we go back to our diagnostic tools, and you know what, I'll just make a new tab here, and we'll make that our second tab.
We'll make our way back to the, oops, not network security groups.
We want to go to network watcher here.
And let's go back to IPv flow.
And we will give it another go.
So we need our remote IP address.
I'll go grab mine over here.
Paste that in there.
Oops, port 80, port 80.
We'll hit next.
And we'll see what happens here.
Great, access denied.
That's what we're expecting.
We'll make our way over to the NSG diagnostic, and we will again select RISA.
We'll choose virtual machine RISA, RISA, TCP, inbound port.
We will go grab our IP address because we are the source, and then we will say port 80.
And there we go.
It says traffic will not be allowed, which is what we want.
Denied.
We can click into there, get the full report, see what is going on, what is matching, what is not being applied.
We'll make our way back here.
Let's do connection troubleshoot.
This one's just a simpler version of it.
Preferred IPV version, IPV4, TCP.
Destination port will be port 80.
I find it a little bit easier to do it for the virtual machine, so let's do it from there.
So we'll go back down below.
and we'll check test connection or connection troubleshoot here because we might get something slightly different.
I just want to give you a lot of different options to debug so that you get better information.
So here we have port 80, TCP, my IP address.
It auto-fills it in for you, which is really nice.
And we'll see what it reports here.
Great.
And so here it says network connectivity blocked by security group, default rule denied, all inbound.
As you can see, that is not super detailed.
And so if you really want to have a better understanding, you're going to want to go use the NSG diagnostic tool.
And so what we'll do is go back and fix our port since we had mucked it up.
We'll put that back onto asterisk here.
And we will say save.
Once that is saved, we'll go back and we'll just test our connection again here in our virtual machine.
And we'll hit test connection again.
So that's making sure that works.
It's still complaining here, even though we've reverted it back.
Yep, that's all correct.
I'm gonna just click off and click on again here.
80.
Yep, that's what it was before.
If we're having issues there, what we can do is go back to NSG.
We'll select Ryza, we'll select virtual machine.
We'll check Ryza again, I'm going to put my IP address in again here.
We'll say port 80.
And we'll check that and we'll get a more detailed report here.
It's saying it's denying the traffic.
We're going to click in here and see as to why.
So it's saying it's not matching on this one, which is confusing because if you notice here, the protocol is TCP, the source is any, the source port is any, the destination is any, and the port is nothing.
So I don't know if we're just going to have a lot of trouble here and we'll just have to recreate our instance, but I'll just go do some investigation.
I'll be back here in a moment.
All right, so I'm back here and I honestly did nothing.
All I did was hit test connection again and it works all of a sudden.
So I think sometimes Azure is not consistent.
And what I mean by that is that when we talk about consistency, it takes time for things to propagate and changes to take effect.
So we're all in good shape.
So what we can do is close our virtual machine over here.
We'll close out the NSG over there, and we'll just focus on Network Watcher and look at some of the other advanced tools that we can utilize here.
So let's take a look at some other tools in the Network Watcher, such as Packet Capture.
So this can help us capture packets, as the name says.
So we go here to Risa, and we'll just say Risa Packet.
And we would have to choose a storage account if there isn't one.
I think it's just going to go ahead and create us one.
I don't remember creating that one myself.
Maximum packets is 0 to the default.
I'm happy with all the default.
We do have some additional options.
We actually only want TCP because that's all we're going to be using anyway.
And we'll go ahead and hit save.
And so now once that is created, we should be able to capture some packets.
All right.
So if I give this a nice refresh here, we'll
We'll just wait for that to create.
Oh, there we go.
So now it's just loading.
So we'll just wait for that to finish loading.
I'll see you back here in a bit.
Alright, so now our Ryza packet is running.
You don't want to wait too long.
Because when you create these packets here, you actually set a timeout, which is in seconds, that's 18 minutes.
And that's when it's going to capture data, right?
So the thing is, what we want to do is open up our website, if you're not sure how to get there.
We'll just do it the manual way here.
We'll go back to our virtual machine.
And we will go into Ryza here and grab that public IP address.
And so if we just hit enter, that should be sending packets to and from our virtual machine.
And that's what we want to do.
We just want to collect some information here.
And once we are happy with that, the thing is that this packet file is going to get stored.
in our storage account.
So if you scroll on down here, it should tell us where it is.
And it's not there.
So I'm just gonna give it a refresh.
We go back to status.
And so this is where it's going to go.
It's going to go into packet capture into our storage account.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to prematurely stop this if it'll let me.
There we go.
Because we don't want to wait 18 minutes.
And once it's stopped the capture, then it should create that cap file, and we should be able to go explore it.
And so the package is now stopped.
So I believe if we go ahead and click this here, we can now go ahead and download this file.
And what I'm going to do is open this up in VS code.
Just give me a moment here.
And I'm just going to go open this file up.
Oh, it's binary files.
We can't just open it in VS Code.
But the point is that we have that packet data.
So I guess the next question is, how are we going to open it up and look at it?
All right, so we downloaded that file there, but I couldn't open it in VS Code because it's a CAP file.
And in order to load a CAP file, we need something like Wireshark.
So Wireshark is an open source.
software to inspect packets.
And so here I've opened up that COP file, and you can see we have the source and destination.
So, you know, I'm not saying I know much what to do with this file, but I'm just showing you that we can view the packets that were sent to and from.
I wonder if we can see what my IP address was.
So what's my IP?
So 104, et cetera, et cetera.
I don't see that.
Do we see it anywhere in here?
No, but we see things like 10040.0.4, which is the private IP of our actual virtual machine.
And then we have 522359.
I wonder if that's the public IP.
No, it's 2081.
Again, not saying I'm a genius with this stuff, but I'm just showing you how you can kind of utilize it and work your way through that.
Okay.
But yeah, that is packets.
So what we'll do is go back to network watcher.
And since we are done with that, we can go ahead and delete that.
And I'll just close a few of these and we can look at some other network watcher features.
I figured another thing we should go check out is NSG flow logs.
So down below, we have NSG flow logs, and it's not enabled by default.
So what we'll do is create a new NSG flow log here.
And we will go here, we will have to choose a storage account.
This account must not be empty.
So we'll have to create a new one here.
This will just be Ryza.
Ryza storage account.
Only lowercase, that's why.
Let's see if it'll take that it probably has no issues there.
Maybe I just doesn't want the hyphens.
There we go.
It's already taken.
I don't know how it is.
But we'll just go 123456.
That one's not taken.
Great.
And we will put this in the same Ariza security group.
The LRS is fine because we do not need anything super fancy here.
Okay, and so that just created there.
And so now down below, retention is only available with V2 storage accounts.
That's totally fine.
I didn't notice what we chose.
I'm pretty sure it was a V2.
I don't know if it gave us an option.
Flow logs versions, we have versions one and two.
Version one logs ingress and ingress IP traffic flows for both allowed and denied.
V2 provides additional throughput information
bytes and packets.
Version two sounds good to me.
Traffic analytics provides rich analytics and visual visualization derived from NSG flow logs, and other Azure resource data drill down to go through that.
That sounds kind of cool.
I think what we'll do is go checkbox that on, we're going to set it for every hour, I'm not sure what traffic analytics costs, I'm just going to go check Azure very quickly here.
And if I scroll on down traffic analytics,
It's based on gigabytes consumed here, so we'll be okay.
And so I'll enable that there.
One every hour seems fine to me.
I'm going to do every 10 minutes because we don't have a lot going on here.
We already created a workspace earlier.
If you have not, you can go ahead and make one.
But this one is called Risa log workspace.
We'll go ahead and create this one here.
And go ahead and create that.
And we will wait for this to deploy.
That was fast.
Didn't even have to cut the video.
So we will go to the flow log and browse it.
And we'll give this a nice refresh here.
If we didn't get it that way, what we can do is click on Go to resource.
So it's not showing up in the list just yet.
Flow logs allow you to view information ingress and ingress from your network security groups.
We already filled all this in, so that back screen did not work very well when I hit that go to resource.
So we'll go back to here.
Now it shows up.
We'll click into here.
It's showing us the same thing again.
Not sure why.
Storage account is connected there.
Click into it.
It's trying to edit it.
Maybe we'll just checkbox it on here and go NSG view.
Nope.
Give me two seconds.
I'll be right back.
Okay.
So for some reason I was thinking there was some way to view that flow data right within here, but it's not.
They just put it in storage accounts.
So if we want to access that data, we're going to go to storage accounts and you can just open it in your explorer here.
And then from there, what I did, and this is actually a lot harder than you think.
I'm going to go all the way back to the beginning here, just to give you an experience of what it's like.
But you would go into your BLOB containers.
That's the one we stored it in.
And then you just click, click, click, click, click, click, click.
And you click forever until you can reach a JSON file.
If it ever, ever gets there.
I know it's really deep.
And there it is.
And so if we were just to take that file and whoops, if we were just to open download that file, it will not let me drag out tabs today.
I'll just close these other ones here.
Anyway, if we were to download that file, you can just hit the download on there and you open it up.
It is a bit of a weird format, so I had just formatted it using pretty JSON.
This is what it looks like.
And so we have this Duples data, which you're not going to be able to do much with, but it just shows you how it's, you see like inbound and outbound, allow and denying, things like that.
You really would want to ingest this data into like something like Grafana or Elastic, like Elasticsearch or something.
or like the elastic stack or gray logs, or even into traffic analytics.
I'd love to show you traffic analytics today, and we did enable it, but for whatever reason, traffic analytics is just giving me a lot of trouble, and it's not really a high priority right now, so we're not going to worry about it.
But yeah, that is your NSG flow logs, and we'll just move on to something else here.
So I think I've decided after we did all that networking stuff, I think we should just start fresh so that we can now set up an application load balancer and a scale set.
So what I'm going to do is go ahead and delete this resource group called Risa.
We'll spin that on down and we'll just consider the next section just application gateway and scale sets.
Okay?
So see you then.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are looking at Azure Networking Cheat Sheet.
This one's A two-pager, so let's jump into it.
So, VNets is a logically isolated section of the Azure network where you launch your Azure resources.
VNet peering is when you connect multiple VNets, so they act as a network.
You have regional VNet peering, and then you have global VNet peering.
Regional means between 2 VNets in the same region, global.
to VNets in different regions.
Let's just define network interface.
So a NIC is a software or hardware interface between two pieces of equipment or protocol layers in a network.
In our case, it's going to be a software NIC for Azure, but NICs communicate in the IP protocol.
And so for Azure, it's called the Azure NIC.
And Azure network interfaces are attached to Azure VMs.
Without a NIC, an Azure VM instance would have no way to communicate on the network.
An Azure VM instance has to have at least one NIC and can have multiple NICs if you wanted to have it.
Route tables is a table for data stored in a router or network host that lists routes to the next destination.
By default, Azure creates a route table with default routes, also known as system routes, and associate them to your subnets.
You can override system routes assigned to your subnets by creating a new route table and associate it with a subnet.
Then there's the concept of an address space.
It is a range of available IP addresses that you are allocating for your use within your VNet.
The amount of IP addresses available is determined based on the
Cider range notation.
For subnets, it is a logical division of an address space.
A subnet needs a route table so it can have access.
A public-private subnet describes whether a subnet is reachable from the internet or not.
Azure has no concept of private or public subnets, and so it's like there's no formal setting of it, so you have to like you have to configure your own subnets to ensure they do not reach the internet.
So it's not like you say private, you know, you just name it private, but that doesn't necessarily mean it's private.
You can associate an NSG to protect traffic entering in
your subnet.
Azure has a special type of gateway subnet that is used for Azure Virtual Network Gateway.
So if you want one, it's going to tell you you have to make one.
On to the second page, Azure Private Links allows you to establish secure connections between Azure resources, so traffic remains within the Azure network.
So Private Link Endpoint is a network interface that connects you privately and securely to a service.
service powered Azure private link.
It uses a private IP address from your VNet.
Private link service allows you to connect your own workload to the private link.
You need an Azure standard internal load balancer and associate it with the link service.
Many Azure services by default work with private links such as Azure Storage, Cosmos DB, and SQL servers.
Third-party providers should say providers.
Whoops.
Third-party providers
can be powered by PoweredLync, okay?
Or maybe it actually is.
Third-party provides.
No, it should be providers.
Sorry about that.
Azure Firewall is a managed cloud-based network security service that protects your Azure VNet's resources.
It is a fully stateful firewall as a service, so FWAAS.
They want to make everything an AAS.
Built-in high availability.
and unrestricted cloud scalability.
You can centrally create, enforce, and log applications and network connectivity policies across subscription and virtual networks.
Use a static IP address from your VNet resources, allowing outside firewalls to identify traffic originating from your VNet.
Fully integrate with Azure Monitor for logging analytics.
You can launch an Azure VNet in its own VNet, and other VNets pass through the central VNet.
That's what you would do.
You would launch it
its own VNET.
You get Microsoft Threat Intelligence out of that, blocks known malicious IP and fully qualified domain names.
Azure ExpressRoute creates private connections between Azure data centers and infrastructure on your on-premise or in a co-location environment.
Connectivity can be from an any-to-any IP, a network, a point-to-point Ethernet network, or a virtual cross-connection through a connectivity provider at a co-location facility.
ExpressRoute Direct allows for greater bandwidth connections from 50
Megabytes per second up to 10 gigabytes per second, and there you go.
That is the Azure Networking Cheat Sheet.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro.
We are looking at Azure Network Watcher Cheat Sheet.
This is the short one, so let's get it done.
Azure Network Watcher provides tools to monitor, diagnose, and view network metrics and enables or disables logs for resources in an Azure VNet.
It can do IP flow, verify checks, packet capture, troubleshoot VPNs, NSGs, NSG flow logs, diagnostic logs, traffic analytics, and NMP.
The watcher can monitor and repair Azure resources you provision, virtual machines, the virtual networks, application gateways, and load balancers.
Network Watcher cannot be used to monitor platforms as a service or monitoring web analytics, which to me is a huge disappoint, but that's just how it is.
Network Watcher is disabled by default in most regions, so you need to enable it at a per-region basis.
Network Watcher can visualize the topology of your VNets.
Network Performance Monitor, MPM, is a cloud-based hybrid networking monitoring solution that enables you to monitor network performance between various points in your network infrastructure.
You have traffic blackholing, routing errors, unconventional network issues, and generate alerts.
It will generate alerts and notify you when a threshold is breached for a network link.
There's a lot in the service.
It's hard to say if you need to know all of it for the exam, so I tried to boil it down for you, but there you go.
So network security groups filter network traffic to and from the Azure resource in a VNet.
And so an NSG is composed of many security rules.
And so here's an example of setting an inbound security rule.
And each security rule has the following properties.
So you can give it a unique name, which is all the way at the bottom there.
You can set the source or destination.
So you're going to set an IP address, CIDR block, service tag, application group, things like that.
Then you set the port range.
So it could just be port 80.
It could be all ports where it shows an asterisk.
It could be a range of ports.
You can set the protocol.
So you've got TCP, UDP, ICMP.
You set the action, whether it's allowed or denied.
And then you set the priority, which is a number between 100 and 4096.
And we have two types of security rules.
We've got inbound rules, which applies to traffic entering the NSG, and outbound rules that apply to traffic leaving the NSG.
Let's take a look at some of the default security rules that NSG sets for you.
So when you create an NSG, you're going to have some created for you by default.
And that's going to be for outbound rules and inbound rules.
So for inbound rules, you're going to be able to
accept any virtual networks through the NSG.
It's going to allow Azure Load Balancer to make its way in, and it's going to deny everything else.
All right?
Then for your outbound rules, it's allowed to go to any other virtual network.
It's allowed to make its way out to the internet, and then everything else is denied.
So there you go.
Let's take a look here at the logic for security rules.
And there's a lot of logic here, so we'll work our way through it.
And unfortunately, there's no fun way to visualize this.
So we just got to work through the text.
So you may not create two security rules with the same priority and direction.
You can have 5,000 NSGs per subscription and 1,000 NSGs rules per NSG.
For priority, rules are processed in priority order with lowest number processed before the higher number.
And network security groups
Rules are validated by priority using a 5-tuple information to allow or deny traffic based on source, source ports, destination, destination ports, and protocol.
Honestly, I don't know what they mean by that.
And I couldn't make any sense.
It's in the documentation, so I'm just showing it to you here.
Then there's flow records.
They don't exactly explain what they are, but I assume the idea is that when a request flows to the NSG, they're attaching additional information to it.
So the flow record allows a network security group to be stateful.
A flow record is created for existing connections.
Communication is allowed or denied based on the connection state of the flow record.
And so let's talk about statefulness.
So if you specify an outbound security port, you don't need to set the inbound port since it will be set for you.
You'll need to specify an inbound security rule if the communication is initially externally.
initiated externally.
And the opposite is also true if inbound traffic is allowed over a port, it's not necessary to specify an outbound security rule to respond to traffic over the port.
And the reason I know this, when another port is set with another one, that's when it's stateful.
If it didn't do that, then it would be considered stateless.
But it's stateful.
Let's talk about interruptions.
So existing connections may not be interrupted when you remove a security rule that enabled the flow.
And traffic flows are interrupted when connections are stopped and no traffic is flowing in either direction for at least a few minutes.
So there's the rules.
There's a lot of stuff there.
Honestly, I won't even remember 90% of this stuff, but I just wanted to go through it with you.
So there you go.
So the thing is that when you have network security groups, you can apply them at the subnet and or the NIC, and that's going to change how the rules work.
So let's look at these combination of scenarios.
So here we have the internet, and let's set ourselves up with a virtual machine that has a NIC, but it has no network security group.
So what's going to happen in this case?
Well, when there is no NSG assigned to the subnet or NIC, then all traffic is allowed.
Not something I recommend.
I think you should always have an NSG there, but that's what's going to happen.
Our next scenario here is that we have a virtual machine, and then we have a NIC, and the network security group is attached to that NIC.
So when an NSG is assigned to the NIC and no NSG at the subnet, the rules are predictable based on the allow or deny rule.
So whatever you send your NSG is what you expect it to be.
Then we have a scenario here where we have two virtual machines with their own NICs.
And one has a security group, and the other two, they have to pass through the security group that's applied to the subnet level.
So let's look at the one on the left first.
So the NSG applied to a subnet applies to the rules and all the resources in that subnet.
And so basically on the left-hand side, it's going to just act like the other one there, where all the rules you have there are normal.
But the last one is the interesting use case.
because if the first, so the first thing is the first NSG rules are evaluated at the subnet, and then the rules in the NIC are evaluated.
So the thing is, that if you want port 80 to be open, you actually have to open on both.
Otherwise, it's going to get stuck on the first one.
So if your subnet has port 80 closed, and then your NIC has port 80 open, it just can't reach it.
So they both have to be open.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from ExamPro, and we're looking at the Azure Network Security Group Cheat Sheet.
So NSGs filter network traffic to and from Azure Resources VNet.
NSG is composed of many security rules.
You have a name, a source and destination, a port range, and a protocol, and an action and priority.
Okay.
You have inbound rules which apply to traffic entering the NSG, and then you have outbound rules applying to traffic leaving the NSG.
By default, Azure will set a bunch of inbound and outbound rules for you.
You may not create two security rules within the same priority and direction.
You can have 5,000 NSGs per subscription and 1,000 NSGs per rules per NSG.
That's a lot.
You have to be a pretty big company to run out of those.
Rules are processed in priority order with lower numbers
process before higher numbers.
The flow record allows a network security group to be stateful.
If you specify an outbound security port, you don't need to set the inbound port since it will be set for you.
The opposite is true.
If inbound traffic is allowed over a port, it's not necessary to specify an outbound security rule to respond to the traffic over the port.
What I could not fit in this cheat sheet was the scenario where you have multiple
NSGs based on whether they're on the NIC or the virtual machine or etc.
There is graphics for that in the slides.
Make sure you review those before you sit your exam, okay?
So, Azure Virtual WAN is a consolidated networking service that brings many networking security and routing functionalities into a single operational interface, and it has functionalities that include branch connectivity.
Site-to-site VPN connectivity, remote user VPN to point-to-site connectivity for private connectivity, then you have intra-cloud connectivity, you have VPN Express route, internet connectivity, or routing, Azure firewall encryption for private.
connectivity.
And I know that sounds really confusing, but don't worry because I put extra care into this section here so that we really understand what the virtual WAN is.
But the most simple way to think of it is that virtual WAN itself is software-defined WAN, so SD-WAN.
And Azure Virtual WAN is a much better way to route to your branches, data centers, VNets, and cloud services.
So now that we got that text out of the way, let's actually jump in and try to understand what this actually does.
So let's try to understand the concept of pops.
And the way we're going to do that is set up a scenario here.
So imagine that we have our office here, and we want to connect to another data center in another branch.
And we've decided that the way we're going to talk to those other
branches and data centers is through the internet.
And so the idea is that you have this big cloud, which is the internet, but really what it is, it's made-up of a bunch of different networks, which are your internet service providers.
So you know when you want internet from your home, you get with whoever it is.
So like in my area, it's Bell or Rogers, but for you, it could be Vodafone, AT&T, Geo, NTT.
And so the idea is that first you have to get onto the network.
And so the way you do that is with a point of presence.
This is an entry at the edge of a network.
And so that would be like an internet service provider's data center.
So at our office, we're going to connect to the point of presence.
But now if we wanted to get to the other branch, then the idea is we have to go and go through another network.
So how are we going to do that?
Well, the idea is that there will be another point of presence
at two locations that are nearby, and it's going to hop the network.
So if you ever heard the term hop, that's what it means.
It's going between one POP to another.
And so then from Vodafone, we can make our way to NTT, and then we've made it, we can exit there out to the other branch.
And so with the other data center, it's going to do the same procedure.
We're going to connect to a POP.
Then we need to go from geo to AT&T, so we're going to do a hop.
And then we want to get to another pop and do a hop, and then we've made it to our office there.
And so the thing with this is that it's not really great for enterprises to traverse the internet, just because of performance of speed.
You don't have much control over the route that's being taken.
And so, you know, there has to be a better way, and that's what we're going to be talking about next, which is MPLS.
Let's talk about MPLS, which should be an improvement over just going over the internet.
So, imagine that we have a bunch of friends or other companies, and if we pay them, they're going to allow us to use their network, and that's going to allow us to establish a private connection.
And not only that, they're going to deploy these special network devices.
that can read these special labels that we're going to be putting on our packets to help them determine the most efficient route through the private network.
We're going to call this MPLS.
So here is our setup.
We have our office, the other branch and data center.
And instead of using the internet, we're going to establish that private network.
Our friends are going to set up these special devices, which are going to be called LSRs, so label switch routers.
And as packets enter the MPLS, see those little green boxes?
It's going to apply that label.
And now we know the most efficient route, because that label basically says this is the end destination, and they go, okay, great.
So you should take this route.
And so that is in that case, and same over here.
So now let's get into the technicals of MPLS.
So MPLS stands for Multi-Protocol Label Switching, and it's a method of packet forwarding where instead of using IP addresses and layer 3 information to make forwarding decisions, an MPLS label is used to determine the shortest route to the end destination.
And an MPLS is a private connection linking data centers and branch offices.
So it's a private connection as in it's going across a network.
It's not the data centers and branches offices themselves, just clarifying that.
MPLS is outsourced and managed by service providers.
It's possible that you're setting up your own, but likely you're going to be paying somebody else to use their network who guarantees network performance, quality, and availability.
MPLS uses a special network hardware that combines both a router and a switch, and that's why it's called a label switch router.
There's also
LER, which is what applies to label, but I'm not too worried about telling you about that.
It's not a big deal.
MPLS is efficient because the path of a label across the network will be predetermined, and that's called the label switch path.
And an MPL label, the data itself is inserted between layer 2, layer 3.
That's why you hear people call this an OSI layer 2.5 kind of thing.
And it's going to put it in your packet, and they call that little thing, they insert between layer 2, 3, a shim.
So why use MPLS?
Well, it makes it really easy to establish private connections for your VPNs.
You can do traffic engineering, so you can control how the packets traverse the network.
You get quality assurance.
That means you get a guarantee of performance and availability for your packets.
But what are the downsides?
Because if this is so great, why would we need to use something else?
Well, it gets really expensive because you are setting up all the special devices and stuff, and the larger network, the harder it gets.
It's not, it's private, but it's technically not secure.
So the thing is that this whole MPLS, it's just a routing mechanism.
There's no inherent encryption.
So that is another concern.
And also with the rise of cloud services, you still have to traverse the internet in many cases, which you're going to find out with SD-WAN next.
So let's get into that.
So let's set up a scenario as to why we'd want to use SD-WAN.
So here we have a diagram and we have our office and we want to connect it to our VNet that's in our Azure account.
So how would you connect those two?
Well, first you'd need to partner with a data center that's going to establish a express route.
And then in order for you to reach that data center, you're going to be traveling through your MPLS network.
And so now you have a straight path to your assets there in your VNet.
So that is pretty simple, but now imagine that your company also uses Office 365.
So how would you get there?
Well, you might think that you would take the same route.
So you go over the MPLS network, go through the partner data center, and then once you're in the Microsoft network, make your way to Office 365, and it's going to go out the same way, and that will work.
But it's not always the most efficient path, and in most cases, it actually isn't.
And for Office 365, you always want to take the route to the internet.
And the reason why is that Azure or Microsoft has these POPs all over the place.
So we saw POPs earlier.
earlier there.
But the thing is that if a POP is nearby, as soon as you enter the Microsoft network, you're moving like super, super, super fast, like incredibly fast, and you have a guarantee.
And so the thing is that you could just be a few hops away from the Microsoft network, and this will be a lot faster than if you were to go through this route here.
And also, it'd be a lot more cost-effective because you wouldn't have to pay for this and this, right, and all this stuff here.
But the thing is that it doesn't solve all our problems, and we still have to do a bunch of hopping.
And this is over the internet, so however many you have to get there might not be efficient.
And so this is where SD-WAN comes into play.
So SD-WAN stands for Software-Defined WAN.
And an SD-WAN decouples CPU-intensive tasks from routers such as the management, operation, and control plane that can be, and now all this stuff is being pushed into a central location remotely and virtually at your headquarters.
Since most Internet service providers support SD-WAN architecture, you can directly control the flow of your traffic through the Internet.
So SD-WAN can replace an LPS, so you traverse
the internet instead of a private network.
SD-WAN is more cost-effective and requires less configuration than an MPLS initially and at scale.
SD-WAN is secure because it will be using HTTPS, which is supported by your ISP.
And the SD-WAN, you are predetermining the path through the internet so you can perform the least amount of hops to the closest Azure point of presence.
So it's like getting the best of MPLS, but you're getting it to use the internet.
And also, because Azure has those nearby POPs, it's just a winning combination.
So the idea with virtual WAN is that you're pretty much just establishing a connection.
So the idea is that you deploy a VNet with a service endpoint on the edge of a region, which is called a hub, and then you're configuring virtual devices in your virtual WANs so your on-premise can connect to your hub, so it's the fastest route to your Azure cloud resources.
And there's a bunch of stuff on top of that, but hopefully that really
helps you understand what's the purpose of SD-WAN.
But the idea is that we have these routers and we've abstracted the stuff away, so now we can make the fastest route through the internet.
So there you go.
Hey, this is Andrew Brown from Exam Pro, and we are looking at Azure Virtual WAN cheat sheets.
Let's jump into it.
Azure Virtual WAN is a consolidated networking service that brings many networking security routing functionalities in a single operational interface.
These functionalities include branch connectivity, site-to-site VPN connectivity, remote user VPN.
Then you have for ExpressRoute for private connectivity, intra-cloud connectivity, VPN ExpressRoute, inter-connectivity, routing, Azure firewall encryption for private connectivity.
So it does a lot of stuff.
Azure Virtual WAN itself is a software-defined WAN, SD-WAN.
Azure Virtual WAN is a much better way to route traffic for branches, data centers, VNets, and cloud services.
A point of presence is an edge entry of the network.
Hop is when you change networks.
Now when we're talking about multi-protocol label switching, MPLS, I put this in here to help jog your memory why SD-WAN is so much better than MPLS LAN.
A network packet forward where instead of using IP addresses and layer 3 information to make forward decisions, an MPLS label is used to determine the shortest route to the destination.
And then you have software WAN, which we just talked about kind of here, so I probably should have moved these down
below, but that's okay.
Decouple CPU-intensive tasks from routers such as management operations control plane that can now be controlled in a central location remotely and virtually at your headquarters.
Replaces MPLS so you traverse the internet instead of a private network.
More cost-effective and requires less configuration than an NLPS initially at scale.
Secure because you will use HTTPS, which is supported by your ISP.
So there you go.
So virtual private networks, also known as VPNs, what they do is they extend a private network across a public network and enables your users to send and receive data across shared or public networks as if their computing devices were directly connected to the private network.
All right, and so now we have to talk about what is a virtual network gateway.
And so a virtual network gateway is the software of VPN device
for your Azure virtual network.
So that's how these devices are going to connect to your network.
So when you deploy a virtual network gateway, it will deploy 2 or more specialized VMs in specific subnets.
You need to create a gateway subnet.
And these deployed VMs contain routing tables and run specific gateway services.
You can choose the type of gateway you want it to be.
And this is going to determine whether you'd use something like VPN gateway or ExpressRoute gateway.
So it's a simple
As an option like that, but to really understand these virtual network gateways, we should just look at some VPN gateway design, so you understand why you're creating these things.
So, to understand VPN gateway, we need to understand the utility of the service, and so we'll look at some different topologies, and the first one is site-to-site.
This is when you connect...
Azure to on-premise data center or vice versa.
And the idea is you create a VPN gateway that's going to establish connection to your on-premise environment, creating an IPsec tunnel, which is a secure connection, IP connection there.
But you might be asking, well, isn't that what ExpressRoute is for?
Well, ExpressRoute goes through a edge partner.
So there's a lot more work involved in that setup.
This one just goes over the internet.
So it's not going to be as fast.
And there's some other downsides, but the idea is it's the easiest way to get connected from your on-premise to Azure.
The next one is multi-site.
This is when you connect Azure to multiple on-premise data centers.
So it's just like the same model, except there's more than one tunnel here to more than one site.
Then you have point-to-site.
This is when you connect Azure to multiple individual computers.
So imagine you have a bunch of employees around the world, and they have laptops, and they just need to connect
securely to the private VNet or just the VNet in general.
And so that's where we're going to need a VPN gateway.
And the last one is VNet to VNet.
This is where you're going to connect two VNets in two different regions and subscriptions or have different deployment models.
And so that's, again, those are transversing the internet in all these cases here.
But yeah, that's pretty much it.
And I guess I think that if you were to set up ExpressRoute, I think you'd have to set up VPN gateways anyway.
But anyway, that's
what that is there.
So hopefully that now makes sense.
Hey, this is Andy Brown from Exam Pro, and we are looking at Azure Virtual Network Gateway cheat sheet.
So let's jump into it, and this one's a short one.
So a VPN extends a private network across a public network and enables users to send and receive data across shared or public networks as if their computing devices were directly connected to the private network.
That's the basis of this cheat sheet.
So a Virtual Network Gateway, a VNG, is the software
VPN device for your VNET.
When you deploy a VNG, it will deploy two or more specialized VMs in specific subnets.
You need to create what is called a gateway subnet.
These deployed VMs contain routing tables and run specific gateway services.
You will choose gateway types and that will determine if it's a VPN or ExpressRoute gateway.
When you create a VPN gateway, you are generally designing for one or more topologies.
Let's run through it.
I feel like that O is not supposed to be there.
I cannot tell.
This is like topologies.
So you have site to site, you have multi-site, you have point to site, and then you have VNet to VNet.
So there you go.