Hi, everyone.
In this video, I want to dive into learning Azure.
This is the third version I've created this video because Azure is vast.
There are many different ways to learn Azure.
There's many different aspects of Azure.
There is no right way.
Everyone learns differently.
But my goal is to go over what are some of the key steps and stages I would think about as you want to learn Azure.
Now, firstly, I think there are those foundational things that everyone should understand.
I would think about things like identity.
Now, that includes things like Entra ID, formerly known as Azure AD, understanding authentication, authorization, and how things like conditional access, risk, entitlement management come into that.
And identity is not just for users anymore.
We think about agents.
So those AI applications and capabilities with Agent 365, they get identities as well.
And then really expands into the idea of security.
And of course, identity is a big part of security in the cloud.
The network is no longer that moat around our services.
The first entry point is often identity.
But it is defense in depth.
We have many layers of security that we think about.
We don't rely on one thing.
We always think sort of 0 trust.
We constantly verify everything we're trying to do.
So understanding of security and its implications.
Governance.
So again, in the cloud, the process has changed.
Maybe we used to provision a resource in the old days or on-prem by putting in a ticket.
And then
An IT operations person would look at the ticket, check the request, and if it meets regulations and requirements, would go and create it for you.
In the cloud, you just directly provision.
And so when we think about the governance, we use policies in the cloud.
So that the control plane of Azure, the Azure Resource Manager or ARM, it enforces your requirements.
Then we also think about sort of cost management, some of those other aspects to it.
So governance is important.
understanding the basics of infrastructure.
Now that goes to compute services, it goes to network, it goes to data.
There's a whole set of different aspects to that, but understand the core building blocks we think about and also AI.
And AI is a super interesting one.
because it's both AI as services you can use.
So I might think about, sure, more traditional machine learning and classifications and content understanding.
But now the generative capabilities with the various, for example, open AI models, but many others as well.
But also as learning, AI can help us learn.
It can provide us guidance.
It can help us troubleshoot.
It can help explain things to us.
So
AI, I think, is a really useful one, both for performing solutions, but also for helping to understand.
Make sure you understand sort of core resiliency concepts about high availability, about disaster recovery, about recovery point, recovery time objectives, SLAs.
And you're always going to understand the idea of, well, what are these region things?
sets of services within a certain geography, and you're going to use multiple regions when we think about resiliency against some, maybe a natural disaster or some other problem.
But then I want to be able to distribute my workloads within a region.
You'll typically hear about availability zones.
So there's these three availability zones that your subscription sees.
And ideally what we want to do is when we have resources within a region,
We want to distribute them over those.
Think of different physical sets of data centers.
So now we're not going to be impacted by a single server or rack or cluster or even data center level event, compute, network, calling, control plane.
And so we want to be able to use those things.
And what are the types of replications, both synchronous, typically within a location, and asynchronous, going between locations?
And then, obviously, from these, you can branch off into other aspects: administration, app development, database design, database operations, again, more around the AI, DevOps, and ideally, you want to at least have a basic idea of those types of things.
Now, previously, I had a whole list of links.
to my content.
Obviously on my YouTube channel, where you're watching this, I have lots of different videos, but people would kind of say, well, is there some curated order that maybe I could go and look at this stuff?
So I did go ahead and create this site.
So this is just learn.onboardtoazure.com.
It's just links to my videos.
I do need to update this and update it after I record this.
but it just walks through a potential learning path.
And some of it's my content, some of it's links to Microsoft learning courses, some of it's links to the exam and maybe the exam simulator environments, then admin, networking, all the different topics you might think about.
It's not all of my videos at all, but it's kind of a curated list.
that may help you as part of what you're doing.
So that's why I created this site.
It just links to the videos and maybe if you're looking for it, would give you a little bit of a path.
Now the first thing you're going to need though to learn Azure is access to Azure.
You have to be hands-on.
Yes, you could maybe learn some basics through reading or watching my videos or someone else's videos,
But I really think you want to actually be using the technologies, because you'll see how it works, you'll see what doesn't work.
When it doesn't work, you'll work out how to make it work, and you'll learn it so much better.
So really emphasize getting some hands-on with it.
And there's different ways we can get access to Azure.
So obviously your company may just give you access.
as your organization.
They may give you access to a subscription.
And a subscription is like a logical billing boundary and security boundary for resources.
And that might be they've got part of an enterprise agreement.
It might be pay as you go.
But if it's you as an individual and you just want to kind of play around, you can absolutely create a free account.
And this free account gives you a number of different things.
So firstly,
you get $200 of credit that you can use for the first month.
But then what happens is there's a certain number of services that are free for 12 months.
We're going to dive into this.
And then there are some services that are just always free.
So you get a certain amount of the resource for a prolonged period.
So you can always do a certain amount at no cost whatsoever.
So, if we go and it's free for the first 12 months, so 12 months are free.
Well, I can see I get some AI custom vision, some compute, so I get a VM Linux, a VM Windows.
You get a certain number of hours of that capability of a specific SKU.
some containers, I get some database for free, both Cosmos DB, which is really that NoSQL document-based, can be multi-write, eventual consistency, and you can configure that through MySQL, through PostgreSQL, through SQL MI and service bus and networking.
So you get all these various things for 12 months.
And then there are also services that are just always free.
So you get a certain amount of, again, AI services here.
But also what's nice around here, for example, are things like, well, I get some data factory, I get some app service.
So 10 web or API apps.
I get a certain amount of batch functions, 1,000,000 requests.
And realize functions are serverless.
So I can actually do a lot with that.
Certain amounts of container storage and container apps.
So there's a lot of free things here.
Now if you look at the hours and the amounts of it, you're not going to be running a production environment off of this.
But one of the things we'll actually talk about a lot is the idea that, hey, we will go and...
start the service, we use it, and then we're going to shut it down.
So we can really maximize our use of the services we have available.
So I can get a trial account, I get 200 bucks in the first month, there's services for 12 months, and there's services that are always free.
And those always free ones, they kind of apply to all of the different subscriptions, even if it's kind of like a work subscription.
And the next thing we can then talk about though is let's say I've got MSDN or Visual Studio, where you get a certain amount of credit,
per month to use on Azure.
So Visual Studio Enterprise, I get $150 a month.
MSDN regular platform is 100.
Visual Studio Pro or Visual Studio Test Pro, I get $50.
And that may not seem like a massive amount, but again, if we're efficient with how we actually create resources, stop them, delete them, then I can actually get a lot out of that.
Which really brings me to the idea of being efficient, especially if we have limited credit.
But even if you don't have a limited amount and you're part of an organization, you want to be a good custodian of your organization's money and size resources efficiently.
Auto scale them.
So change the number of instances you have as the load changes over some seasonality.
Maybe you get a busy time of the day, busy time of the week, busy time of the month, busy time of the year.
So always adjust the amount of resource you have based on the amount of work it has to do.
If you're working in a lab, for example, you're creating a lab, you're doing some kind of test, one of the constructs we have is you're going to have this idea that you'll create an Azure subscription.
So everything lives within a certain sub.
And when we create resources, we group them together into something called a resource group.
Let's call this resource group one or give it a meaningful name, resource group test ABC or whatever that is.
If you're doing a certain test, a certain lab, put all of the resources that make up that lab or that test in the same resource group specific to that test.
So I create a virtual machine.
Well, that VM uses a managed disk.
That VM also maybe has an IP address.
These all cost you money.
Maybe it's also connecting to some kind of database that's being used as part of this.
Put them all together, because then what's going to happen is once we're finished with this lab, I can just go ahead and delete the entire resource group.
I don't risk just deleting the VM and forgetting to delete the disk or forgetting to delete some IP or forgetting to delete a database.
That's actually going to keep ticking along and costing me money.
Make sure you shut down compute services when you're not being used.
So a virtual machine, if I just stop it inside the guest operating system, it doesn't deprovision it from the Azure physical fabric.
So it's still taking up space on the server.
You're still going to pay for it.
You need to be looking for the words deallocated in the portal to show that, hey, it's not allocated to a machine anymore.
I'm not going to be paying anymore for the virtual machine's compute.
Now, you'll still be paying for its disk.
So that's why it's important, especially in dev environments, pick low performance options.
You probably don't need a really high performance disk in dev test unless you're actually trying to map to real world production performance.
If I'm just playing around, pick a standard hard disk drive, just see how it goes, make sure that's actually...
using the least amount of money possible.
So again, look at all the different options you have.
Often today there's scenarios, like a database, it'll give me a dev test option, it will pick lower SKUs.
So that can be really helpful.
Use Advisor for guidance.
So if I jump over for a second, so I actually go and look in the portal, you have this thing called Advisor.
And keep an eye on that because Advisor will actually give you guidance on things like, hey, we could pick a lower skew.
You could save some money.
It has this idea of recommendations.
But it will also give you hints about, hey, your security, your performance, your liability.
So it's just a really good place to go as you're learning to get some good hints of actually what I should be doing.
Which then really leads on to
How do I get good information about Azure?
And the portal's great.
So the first time you access the portals, you've gone and got a subscription or create one.
You'll go to portal.azure.com.
You're going to sign in with an Entra account.
That's kind of a corporate identity.
And you'll be in the home.
And one of the things you can do is just, you'll see some services in your favorites.
And you can adjust what is or isn't a favorite.
But if I just hover over it,
It actually starts to give me information.
So notice it's telling me recent resources, free trial.
training, useful links, for example, the documentation, all these other things, pricing information.
So it's giving me help about every single one of these, so I could go and learn more.
I can click all services, and I can do the same thing for everything.
And within here, I could then go and select, hey, do I want it to be a favorite?
Do I not want it to be a favorite?
I can enable or disable the idea of it showing in that menu bar on the left-hand side.
And again, I just hover over them to get these information cards for more information to help me learn it.
I mean, that's really the whole goal around doing this.
If one of the first things you're probably going to do is create a VM, or you'll create a virtual network first, and you'll go and create virtual machines.
But again, within here under virtual machines, I can see my VMs, but there's a getting started tab.
And if I hit that, it talks about all virtual machines.
Do I want to create more than one virtual machine?
Hey, let's look at viewing comparison charts of what my different options may be.
Help me find what is the best product for my workloads, like walk me through it.
It's also, let's go back up here.
Notice at the top, it's giving me this idea of
using AI, so this is the Azure Copilot.
Here's some suggestions in ways it can help me.
Check which VMs cannot access the internet, view virtual machines with critical alerts.
So it's given me help there as well.
Now, play around in the portal, look around the portal.
It is very intuitive.
It will guide you through things.
But also, Microsoft Learn is fantastic.
So learn.microsoft.com.
I can go and search it for any information I want.
You've got all the various documentation areas, it's got all the different products.
There's essential information, so I can browse all the product docs.
There's fantastic training.
So if I go and do this browse all training option, I can go and scan across all of the different Microsoft Learn training by the different areas that it has.
So here I can see I could search by product.
I could just go and search for a particular course.
I might search based on my role, the level of how advanced it is from over here on this left-hand side.
I could even say, look, just find me stuff related to particular courses.
And maybe only care about courses related to Azure.
So introduction to cloud infrastructure, let's have a look at that.
Okay, that would get me ready for AZ 900.
So that's really the Azure fundamentals exam.
So it's not just documentation, it has fantastic guides to actually get you up and running and learning and getting certified in the cloud.
Now you'll also at certain points start looking at CLIs like command line interfaces.
And yes, you could install things like the Azure PowerShell modules, the Microsoft Graph PowerShell modules, there's the Azure CLI.
but also I can access a cloud shell.
So the cloud shell will just open you up a shell instance within the portal and I can actually switch between PowerShell and the Bash CLI, depending on if I'm more of a PowerShell person or maybe I'm more traditionally a Linux person and I like to use a CLI, but I can go and interact with it, see the various instances.
It's automatically going to authenticate
with whatever identity you're currently logged into the portal with.
You can upload and download files.
There's an editor, like a VS Code version of an editor I can integrate with.
It's really nice, powerful way to experiment with the CLI as well.
And then I mentioned the idea of AI helping you.
So you'll notice here in the portal, you have this copilot button.
So this is Azure's Copilot.
And if I select this, well, A, before I select it, you'll notice it's kind of present as you bounce around different things where it thinks it can help you.
It's got suggestions about how AI could interact with you.
If I just select Copilot, what this is going to do, it has context around what I'm currently looking at in the portal.
So in this case, I'm looking at storage, so it's suggesting storage things.
And it's also grounded, i.e., knowledge it can go and hook into about the Microsoft documentation, so all that learn stuff it knows about as well, but it's really important to understand it can only see and act on the things you, the person signed in.
can see and act on.
So all of those role-based access controls, so role-based access control are the permissions that I have on a certain scope.
Subscription, resource group, resource, it's going to live within whatever policies you have.
They're still going to be honored as well.
Any locks, they're all going to be respected and enforced as part of this.
So this is just the model
is going to be sent context about what I'm currently doing, and it's also going to be able to go and search the documentation to help you with the things you're doing.
Some different resources have also created extra plug-ins, so it's even more useful for things like VMs and AKS to just help you do what you're trying to do.
But in this case, for example, I could A, ask it about the things I'm currently looking at in this context, but I can also just interact with it in general.
So I can say, hey, should I use Express Route Private Peering or a site-to-site VPN?
And so what it's doing now is it's looking at the documentation, it's looking at its pre-trained knowledge, but it's mainly going to ground itself in the documentation.
So it's going to ask me some questions.
Oh, okay.
So it's not just going to explain basic things, it's actually going to clarify and guide me through so it can give me the best information.
So now it's telling me the difference between them.
And hey, okay, if I want a more robust, consistent connection, Express Route would be the optimal.
Great.
Maybe I've heard about something new.
So what is NAT Gateway V2?
Like what's different about NAT Gateway V2?
And while it's doing this, realize I could also ask it to help me troubleshoot.
Why can't I do this, that, or the other?
Like it will guide me through steps.
It will look at information that I have access to and help me.
Okay, yeah, zone redundancy, oh yeah, performance, IPv6, great.
It can do more advanced things.
Can you help me create a script to set tag?
department to a value for all resources in a certain resource group.
So now it can actually go away and it will create me script to perform that function.
I could then go and iterate on it.
I could do whatever I want, but it's there to help me do different things.
That's the whole point of everything.
And you'll notice also on some of these,
it will actually go and then actually give me other suggestions.
So okay, it's asking me for a bit more detail and it will actually go and create the script.
But it's also suggesting other things and other ways it could help.
And of course also you can just think about regular AI.
So then you have the idea of things like just copilot.microsoft.com.
So this is the public version.
So I could ask it more general question, but this is only going to be grounded on public knowledge.
It cannot see your work resources.
It cannot see my Azure things.
But I might just help ask it to interact on more general research things, things I'm trying to learn.
I would not copy work information into this or attach it.
You should use your work's copilot, for example, or use Azure Copilot for those type things.
So always be careful with more generalized AIs that you don't send it work specific.
If you wouldn't be comfortable with information just being used to train things, you should not put it into general AI models.
Use your work versions of the services to get that sort of confidentiality.
I also create a sort of roughly 2 hour annual state of the unit.
I'm about to create my new version right now.
but that can give you a good overview of Azure.
I think if you are starting out, then I would probably think about the certifications can be useful.
You don't maybe need the certifications, but from a fundamentals perspective, my AZ-900 will guide you through core knowledge.
just about Azure, some of the basics around the key services, some of the basics around, okay, what is the subscription, how do I use it?
I have on my little learn site, so if I jump over for a second, I talk about sort of how to use Azure for free, but I've got an AZ-900 fundamentals course, so it's 9 1/2 hours.
Then I have a study cram.
And then I walk through the exam simulator, which is really, really good.
If you're going to take the exams, there's actually a sandbox, so you can get used to actually trying out what the exam environment would look like.
So that can help.
And then I go into a much deeper, I've got an Azure master class that's like 9 and a half, maybe it's even 20 hours long, of much deeper information.
Again, use Microsoft Learn.
It's fantastic.
It has really good documentation, really good training exercises.
I would also probably recommend doing the SC900.
That's kind of a core security one.
And also I would do AI900.
AI is everywhere.
I think those would be considered the core ones.
I mean, honestly, I know some people go and do all of the 900s.
They're all the fundamental ones.
There's obviously data.
There's more about co-pilots.
There's Power Platform.
They're really good things to have.
And then you can actually think about going to maybe say more specific, maybe Azure Administrator, maybe I want to go into an architect, maybe I want to go into a deeper set of AI capabilities, maybe DevOps and what they actually have.
And I link this in my site, but there is actually a poster just find it.
I'll scroll it from here.
So there is a certification poster that walks through all of the different certifications.
So you could see cloud, AI, security, and it talks about the fundamental ones first.
So the AZ, the AI, the data, and then the newer one is the ABH, the study cram on that power platform.
But then you could start to dive into more specific ones, and obviously they get more complex.
And so you get to sort of the advanced ones that tend to go deeper into certain functions, but really nice, clear path of the things that I may want to actually go and look at.
Now, Azure changes very, very frequently.
Microsoft do have an Azure update blog where they sort of post about the changes and what's coming out, and that's why I do kind of a weekly update.
So one of the things that I have on my channel is I actually have an update every week, every Friday.
I put out an Azure update where I cover Azure things, but also entry things, but also AI things, also things that kind of surround it.
It's normally like 10 minutes or less, but it's a way to kind of stay current on the various things.
But just it's the cloud.
The cloud is evergreen.
It's constantly changing, constantly new features, constantly new services.
So you want to stay up to date because the way you solve something today, tomorrow, there may be another option available to you.
And it doesn't mean you change to it, but you just know it's there and maybe there's some time where you reevaluate how you do things or you have a new project, you can use the most effective, efficient service.
So I think really the key point here is get those fundamental things understood.
Get access to a subscription so you can get hands-on.
Try things out.
Set yourselves little projects.
Go through the labs.
Maybe follow the certifications to give you just a guided set of things to go and look at.
Stay current.
And AI can be your friend here.
AI, you can ask it to explain things with you.
can ask it to role play.
You can help troubleshoot things with it.
It's just a really great time to learn.
There's so many different ways to learn things.
And I hope that was useful.
And until the next video, take care.