Hi, everyone.
In this video, I want to dive into Foundry IQ.
This, along with Fabric IQ and Work IQ, form that knowledge foundation for our AI apps and agents that enables us to unlock a lot of powerful capabilities.
Now, our need for any of these additional sets of knowledge comes from the fact that our generative models are trained on a very large but very finite corpus of information.
we think that we have this body of knowledge.
So this is our corpus of training data.
And this comes from books and websites and transcripts.
But it is a finite size and it has a certain cutoff date.
And it won't include anything non-public.
So then this is used to train our generative model.
So all of those neurons that make up the model get its different weights and biases modified based on the strength of those various connections, which then once it's done all that training, I can pass new prompts and then it can predict the next most probable token and the next and the next and it generates us these fantastic responses.
But if I need it to be able to utilize
and information that it was not trained on, it's not part of that pre-trained knowledge that makes up the model, well, I have to be able to give it that information.
I have to provide it as part of the request.
So the way that works is whatever our little AI application is, if there is some prompt,
that I want to give the model, but I need that additional data, what we actually do is we have some knowledge of information.
Maybe it's our internal company set of database, whatever that may be.
So this is all of our information.
The application makes a request to it first, and then it sends back the relevant info.
Then that info gets added to the prompt.
And now the model can take the request and the applicable information and generate that response.
So this is known as retrieving additional information to augment the ability for it to generate information or RAG.
So it's a super common term.
We're used to that.
And the quality of this additional information, we send it
is going to massively impact the quality of the response we get back.
Garbage in would be garbage out.
So we want to make sure we get the very highest quality and applicability of data that we send to the model so we get fantastic outputs.
So that's the fundamental issue.
The model is trained on a certain body of data.
It doesn't know about our company's data.
It has cutoff dates.
So for it to be really useful, we have to give it more info.
Now I drew this idea of sending a question and getting information back.
This is where Azure AI Search comes in for many of our different types of data.
So the whole point here is what we get is with Azure AI Search, it provides that ability.
to expose an endpoint.
So remember, we're used to talking to these things.
It's going to expose an API.
In this case, it's going to create a number of indexes.
We're going to talk to an index.
So the app would now, for this question, would actually send it this way to the API for Azure AI search.
And it sends it, hey, the query it's trying to find, an Azure AI search.
We'll do that, search for it.
will find the best, highest quality data, send it back, which it can then add to the prompt.
So that's the benefit we get from Azure AI Search.
But it's how it finds that information that is so powerful because obviously we, underneath everything, we have some amount of knowledge.
Well, it's not even knowledge.
That's actually a poor word.
I'm going to change that.
We have some information.
And there's a distinction between information and knowledge.
So we have a set of different information.
This could be in blobs, could be in databases, whatever that may be.
What Azure AI Search is going to do is a number of different ways.
So firstly, it's going to create an index.
So the whole point here is it creates a certain index for a particular set of information, a particular BLOB.
container, a particular database.
So in this case, maybe we create index one.
So I create index one, which corresponds to a single source of information.
Now, sometimes when we search, we are searching on maybe a SKU, a name of a product that has a very high discrimination ability against other types of data.
I'm just basically searching A lexical search.
I'm doing a keyword search to match on that.
So when we have these indexes in Azure AI Search, it has that.
Great.
It has that basic keyword lexical index, and it does a lexical search.
However, when we start looking at these generative models and how we interact with them,
We normally use natural language, and the problem of natural language is many words can mean the same thing, and one word can mean many different things.
Our language is full of idioms where what we say should not be taken literally.
It's raining cats and dogs.
If a computer took that literally, it would be taking automated actions to call a lot of vets to your location because it's assuming there's a lot of injured animals on the ground.
We know it just means it's raining A lot.
So what we have to do when we think about natural language, we have to understand the semantic meaning of information and then find the closest set of information based on what we're looking for.
Now the way we do this is we create vectors.
So in addition to this lexical, we have an idea of a vector index.
And what we have to enable this is whatever that source is,
We actually chunk it up into particular blocks, and then we use an embedding model to create this very high dimensional vector that represents the semantic meaning of the data.
And then when we're searching, we create another embedding, a high dimensional vector of what we're looking for, and we find the ones that are closest, because that means they have similar semantic meaning.
So then what Azure AI Search will do is it will run the search against both of those,
And then it does something called reciprocal rank fusion.
Basically a fancy term for mush them together.
Things that rank highly on both of them put overall near the top.
But then it does another semantical re-rank
So that list of results, it then compares again compared to what the search request was, reorders them, scores them, and returns the ones that give us an answer above a certain confidence level.
So this is fantastic capability.
The net result is I get fantastic results, but all of the searches we make are always against a single index, which is against a single
information source.
We really can think about this as our RAG 1.0 stack.
So that's how often we'll think about this.
Okay, so now we're going to think about Foundry IQ.
So if we now take, it's still Azure AI search.
Now this is built on Azure AI search too.
But what we're now going to have, use orange.
I always use orange for the new thing.
So now we're going to have Foundry IQ.
Now the big deal here is it's going to provide a true knowledge layer, not just information.
It moves from a single shot RAG.
Remember, we make a request.
It can look at an index, which represents an information source.
With Foundry IQ, we move to agentic RAG.
So now it's not just this single
shop, we can also think of it as a multi-hop.
I can now think about searching across more than one knowledge source.
So for example, in a single request at a very basic, basic level, what I could now do is, yes, he could still go and look at index one, but also we had index two.
it had some other type of data that when I think about a certain real-world entity or relationship or constraint, this has applicable information as well that needs to be considered.
So I can now group particular sets of knowledge sourced together and search across all of them.
And so maybe that's a key term of what we're going to do here is as I start thinking about this, what we're adding
are knowledge sources.
But it's also adding additional types of knowledge source.
So for example, these indexes it creates, it can also now index data in Fabrics OneLake, Fabric IQ.
So remember, Fabric IQ is Fabric's own ontology of the enterprise entities, relationships, properties,
that gives semantic meaning of the information.
So rather than it just being information in OneLake, it now actually represents what does it mean to the true enterprise?
So it becomes a lot more useful.
So these knowledge sources can now include Fabric and Fabric IQ, i.e.
data in OneLake and that ontology, those models.
It can also
Include a specific SharePoint site, so I can point it to a particular SharePoint site.
Now, with these, it is still going to go ahead and it's going to index it, so it's going to go ahead and again take the data, bring it into an index, create the vectors, create the embeddings, so it's now another index that is local to.
Azure AI Search.
But additionally, it supports the idea of remote knowledge sources.
So here I can think about this was a specific SharePoint site.
But I can also have the idea of actually just work IQ slash sort of M365 SharePoint.
Now, what this is now going to do is use M365's own semantic index to find the most relevant information based on the token, the user who is making the request.
Now, I would need a copilot license to be able to utilize that to get that semantic index access.
I can also make a request to the web, which is powered by Bing.
And also, I think in preview, I can point to MCP.
So remember, MCP is about a standard way to provide additional knowledge and tools, maybe even prompts, to my AI application.
And it reflects its capabilities to me, so I don't have to try and explain it to the app itself on how to use it.
It's a standard protocol.
So what I would probably expect here is if I was going to use MCP, it probably has some kind of search tool
that it exposes as part of that reflection of its capabilities.
So Foundry IQ, Azure AI search behind the scenes, would be able to call that to get the response.
So these are remote knowledge sources.
This makes 0 difference to the AI app.
It makes 0 difference to the user.
It's just for your information when you think about this.
If it's regular BLOB and information or data from OneLake or SharePoint site, it's creating an index within Azure AI Search.
And again, even when it does this stuff on a SharePoint site, it will still try and retain as much information and permissions as it can.
If I add these, like just SharePoint in general, not a particular site, then it's just going to use MS365 Work IQ's semantic index.
If it's going to search the web, it goes and searches the web.
It's not going to index the web itself.
MCP will call that search tool.
So we have those capabilities as part of what we're going to use.
And if we jump over for a second, so here I'm in Microsoft Foundry.
I'm looking at the new experience right here.
And the first thing to pay attention to is
You select a particular Azure AI search resource first.
So this has to exist.
I have to have created an Azure AI search resource and then I create one or more knowledge bases.
So you can see I have two different knowledge bases here.
If I select one of them, what you'll see is it comprises of a certain number of knowledge sources.
I have two.
One is the Azure AI Search Index, and one of them is web.
So I guess that's an important point.
When I think about, okay, knowledge sources, realize what sits above that is a knowledge base.
So I have a knowledge base, which is actually what I really interact with.
So a knowledge base is just a collection
of knowledge sources.
And today you have N number of knowledge sources in a knowledge base.
It's 10.
That could absolutely change in the future.
If we jump back again, but what I can see here is I can add existing knowledge sources that may have already created that maybe I'm using in another knowledge base, or I can go and create a new
type of knowledge source.
And this is where you can see it.
So I could use an existing search index I have.
I could just point it at a BLOB container.
It will go and grab them, chunk them, index them.
I can point it to the web.
I could point it.
So here the point is a particular SharePoint site index.
So it will actually create an index in Azure AI search.
Or I can just point it at SharePoint in general.
This is just saying use SharePoint.
And then it's going to use the remote semantic index of M365.
I can also point it to Fabrics OneLake where it can go and retrieve and then again it will go and create the index.
The ability to use MCP is in private preview today.
I've not got that signed up in this particular one, which is why I can't see it.
But they're all the different types of knowledge source you can actually add.
You saw already they live in a particular instance of Azure AI search, so I can add multiple Azure AI search resources with different sets of knowledge bases in it.
Different SKUs of Azure AI search support different total numbers of knowledge bases and different numbers of knowledge sources.
If I jump over and look at the limits page, and again, you'd want to check this, but today you can see the free version sports only three.
sources and three knowledge bases.
Basic is 15, unless you created it earlier on, it talks about the date, which goes to be 5, then the S1, S2, S3, et cetera, et cetera.
So the different SKUs support a different number of them.
Once I've created the knowledge source, again, I could use it in other
knowledge bases.
It's literally a knowledge base is just a collection of knowledge sources that I'm collecting together because together they represent some useful knowledge about entities of the enterprise or some other type of thing.
And then my AI app or agent doesn't need to care.
It can just point to the knowledge bases I've created and do useful things.
Previously, it was very complicated for agents.
If maybe I needed information from three different blobs, maybe different types of policies and information, then there was maybe something in a SharePoint.
I as writing the agent or the app would have to go and manage and do separate queries and then try and bring them together, it would get very messy.
So the whole point of this is we're separating that away.
So now the AI app or the agent can just focus on, hey, this is the knowledge base.
and it's going to just give me all of the information I actually need.
Now, what's really powerful here is how it uses these different knowledge sources.
It's not just saying, okay, before we had a request and we searched and we got a set of results.
This is not simply, well, now it searches whatever that search is across all of the different knowledge sources in the knowledge base.
It's a lot richer than that.
If we go and look at our knowledge base, we actually see a few different things straight away.
So one of the things we have here is, well, we give it a chat completions model.
So this is a generative model it can use
as part of its reasoning, its planning, there's different options that I can leverage.
And then it has this idea of a reasoning effort, minimal, low, or medium.
Now you'll notice minimum is grayed out because I have it in a certain output mode.
Actually, if I go and look at a different model for a second, that one's using web.
Web forces you to use a certain mode.
So here I can see all three of them.
Minimal, low, and medium.
So let's talk a little bit about exactly what is happening here, because it is a lot richer.
So remember we talked about this idea of this agentic RAG, this multi-hop capability.
So it's doing intelligent thinking to actually work out what it needs to do.
So as part of this agentic RAG, it's
not going to just use everything that exists in that knowledge base.
Now, that's actually not true.
If I set it to minimum, that minimum level of reasoning effort, then it does.
It just takes the request you send it, and it sends exactly that request to all of the knowledge sources.
So the effort you select does impact its behavior.
But if I select an effort,
of low or medium, well now it's going to do a few different things.
It's going to work out a plan.
And it's only going to use the knowledge sources what is needed.
So that's with low and medium.
So minimal, sure, whatever I ask it, it's just going to ask all of them.
Low and medium, it's going to look at the knowledge source descriptions.
It's going to look at the knowledge base retrieval instructions to assess, well based on what I'm being asked, what is the best way, the most efficient way,
to work this out.
And it's not just going to pass the query you asked it, it's going to go and maybe break that into sub-queries and send it to different knowledge sources to get the answer.
That's where the agentic part comes in.
So it's going to be selective about which knowledge sources it's going to use.
If it's a really simple question, it may just pick a single knowledge source.
If it's a more complex question, then sure, maybe it has to ask multiple knowledge sources.
And it's why it's so important to have quality descriptions.
So when I look at this, if I was, jump at my, I have multiple ones again.
If I look at my knowledge source, so say YouTube, I give it a description.
Transcripts from John Savill's technical training, YouTube channel content.
Because that's the understanding that the model used to say which knowledge sources it should use
That's how it's going to make that decision.
This one is just search of web information.
So I'm giving a description to the knowledge sources because it's going to help the model when it's trying to do its train of thought, when it's going to work out its plan.
Well, which of the knowledge sources should I actually use?
And then I can add in instructions to my knowledge base.
So I'm guiding it.
Look, if it's about technical items, prioritize using.
my YouTube knowledge source first all the time.
If you can't find an answer, then you're allowed to use KSWeb.
So I'm giving it very specific guidance of how I want it to go about actually answering and solving that problem.
So the whole point of this agentic, this multi-hop, is it's going to create a query plan, that chain of thought.
It's going to work out different queries that are most applicable to the knowledge sources it's going to select, and then it executes it.
Now what's nice here is if I do medium, it also then does a self-reflection.
So what that means is it's done this plan, it's queried the particular knowledge sources it selected, gets the results back.
With medium effort, it looks at those results, looks at what it was trying to do and says, have I solved it?
If it doesn't think it has, it can do a second follow-up pass to try and get a better output.
Now, obviously, it's going to use more tokens.
It's going to have a longer lag.
It's therefore going to cost more money, but I'm going to get a much higher quality of response.
So you get to pick what is that effort I want to do.
And Microsoft has a really nice sort of deep, techie article, and I'll put it in the link of the video, but it talks about that medium, low, and minimal.
So if I do that minimal, it's
Not doing any source selection.
It's not doing any planning.
It just doesn't do it.
It just searches them all.
Super, super basic.
It doesn't use the web as a knowledge source grounding.
But as soon as it goes to that low and medium, well, now it does do source selection.
It does do query planning.
And then really the big difference is we get this reflective additional retrieval step.
and additional classifying as part of those responses.
So we get additional rich capabilities on top of that.
Now, another thing we get is, you may have noticed as part of the knowledge base configuration, this time it's grayed out.
It's just answer synthesis.
The reason it's grayed out and it's answer synthesis is because one of my knowledge sources is web.
If it's web, it has to be answer synthesis and it won't let me do minimal reasoning.
But if I don't have web, I have a choice.
I have extractive data and I have answer.
Synthesis.
Answer synthesis is only available with low and medium.
So if I change this to answer synthesis, you'll notice I can't select minimal anymore.
Go back to extractive data for now.
So what is this all about?
What is this pointive?
We talked about before we have a particular API request.
And that particular API request was just asking indexes.
And that's why it would ask.
With Boundary IQ, my API, it's still the Azure AI search resource.
But instead of it being indexes, what we're going to change it to most of the time is knowledge bases.
There's also knowledge sources.
I think there's knowledge retrievals.
But as part of that, I have two choices into how it returns.
So option one is extractive data.
And that's kind of what we're used to in the old Azure AI search.
I'm going to make some requests.
A very common this would be, for example, if this was Foundry, and it was the agent service.
So I have a generative model.
It just is asking for, give me some data.
I'm then going to reason over it.
I'm then going to come up with the answers because I'm using it a certain way.
I just want you to give me a set of data back that's most applicable.
So this option one is just extractive data.
And we'll let's see this in action.
So if we jump back over.
So right now I have it in that mode.
Extractive data.
So if I go and look at my agent and I'm using that
knowledge base right now.
You can see I've added knowledge.
It's that just basic one.
If I go and ask it a question, what is ExpressRoute?
So it's going to go and use that knowledge base.
It's asking my approval.
Now you can change it so you don't have to keep doing this, but I wanted you to see it.
So I'm going to keep approving only once.
So that's going to go and call that knowledge base with these requests.
And we'll get the answer back.
But what I want to do is go and look at the debug to see exactly what gets sent back from that Azure AI search request.
So if I look at debug and I actually look at the usage of the knowledge base, so we can see it made the request.
But look at what we get back.
What we get back is just a set of chunks.
We got 11 documents retrieved.
It's just sending us a bunch of data back.
That's all we get.
And then my model can do what it normally does is use that as part of its decision.
Great.
The other option I can do
is I can think about answer synthesis.
So with answer synthesis, imagine now it is something else.
It's just maybe a chat app.
So I've written my own little chat.
Actually, I don't want to use that color, different color.
So I just write some kind of chat application.
And my chat app wants to make a response.
And really, I just want the answer back.
So here, my second option
is that answer synthesis.
It's going to give me a generated answer based on the various knowledge things it finds.
So then it can just return it as is.
It doesn't have to then go and do anything else.
It just wants me to give it the answer.
So if now if we go and look, and this time I'll change it.
So remember, we are other knowledge sources.
Either I could just change my existing one.
But if I look at my second one that uses both my index and the web, this one, because it's using the web, is always doing answer synthesis.
So I would change my agent to not use that, and instead we'll add that one.
We'll ask it the same question.
And what we should see this time, yep, prove.
is we'll actually get a generated answer and then it will tell us the information it used as references.
But it's actually going to give the answer as part of its response in that natural language.
It's going to work it out for us.
So it's doing that full answer synthesis.
So I as a more basic AI app wouldn't have to then do anything else.
It's just giving me the complete answer.
And you can see it's taking a little bit longer.
And it's throwing out some output.
But now if we look at the debug and I look at what it actually did this time, if I look at the information, it's giving me the description.
This is the answer.
It's just throwing out a complete answer.
And then it's telling me the various sources it used.
So it behaves in a very different way.
So you pick, you decide what is it you want it to do based on how is it going to be used.
So the key point here, again, if I'm writing a rich agent, I probably just want the data back.
I don't want it to then extrapolate out answers.
So I would want to just use the extractive data option for it.
Just give me the information that's most relevant.
Hey, a more basic chat thing.
Sure, maybe I actually want it to go ahead and create the full answer for me.
There's actually a nicer demonstration someone in the product group wrote, so we'll look at this.
So this is doing the same thing.
It's using a knowledge base.
If I look at the settings, you can see they've got three different knowledge sources, BLOB, OneLake, and the web.
Because it's using the web, it's going to have to be answer synthesis.
It's using a medium reasoning effort and you can just ask it a certain question.
But what this actually does is they've added some additional information about what Azure AI Search I Foundry IQ is actually doing behind the scenes to get the answer.
And it can show you the number of passes it's doing, the iterations.
It's a really cool just way of seeing everything that is going on.
So here I can see, okay,
It did 2 iterations, so two distinct planning cycles, 11 different activities, 60 different retrieval calls.
I can see the lapsed time, the planning tokens.
I can see the query planning steps, what it actually did as part of the requests, what it did on the second iteration, some additional queries it made, and then spat out the answer and all of the various references to it.
So it's just an example that you can kind of see some of the power that is really going into it.
So in summary, the whole point here is that Foundry IQ brings the ability to just query the knowledge base.
And that knowledge base gives me that single queryable entity that will then intelligently utilize all the available knowledge sources that can be, hey, local,
I can use remote, and I've which just gives me a list of the most relevant data, so I get a high quality inferencing from my agent or app, or it can just synthesize the full answer.
And that's the whole goal of all of this.
You see these interesting things about data and information and knowledge and wisdom.
And the goal of all of this is to build on top of that.
So we're used to the idea of just like raw data.
And then we do certain amount of processing to actually get useful information that we can then use.
It's why we bring data into OneLake, for example, in Fabric.
But then we add additional context.
We consolidate, we group it, we interpret it.
which then gives us the idea of knowledge.
And it's only once we have knowledge, we can actually reason over it.
It's only once we have knowledge that I can make judgments based on it.
So that's that idea of wisdom, which we can apply once we have that knowledge.
And that's what Foundry IQ is doing.
Foundry IQ is giving us knowledge.
That's why they call it knowledge bases.
It's knowledge we can now leverage in the same way
that I can think about, well, Fabric IQ does the same thing for the data in OneLake or shortcut to OneLake via its ontology to make it actually map to real enterprise entities.
It's the same thing Work IQ.
is doing for all of the data, yes, in M365, but it adds memory, customization, richer inferencing.
It's all about giving you knowledge.
And then once I have these different now knowledge sources, then the AI apps, the AI agents I write,
then can provide the wisdom on it.
And that's the goal.
So your AI app and agent now gets quality knowledge across these so it can now do the right things.
And the whole point is you use them together.
The work IQ would give you an understanding of the full user context.
Fabric IQ would give you full system operational knowledge.
Founder IQ would give you the full knowledge around any organizational information.
So together,
it can really answer any question for your AI apps and agents.
And that was it.
I hope that was useful.
As always, till the next video, take care.